PAUL: Yeah, hello everyone. Am I audible? Please let me know.
PAUL: In the chats, and just, be sure the audio is fine or not, okay? So let me know.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Audio and video is fine.
PAUL: Alright, guys.
PAUL: So, let's start our class.
PAUL: Where we can find the previous recordings.
PAUL: Alright, I think this should be familiar to you guys by now.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, I think everybody will have a course section, because in the…
PAUL: forum also, ISOP people, okay? And here you'll be seeing your particular course.
PAUL: So, in that course, like,
PAUL: I will just get as a view as a customer, okay, and you will be getting the recordings here.
PAUL: like, day-wise, and the topic names will be there, so whoever has this particular query, Okay?
PAUL: Please let. I think now everybody got it in the portal.
PAUL: Notion link, I will share, don't worry.
PAUL: Motion link I will share, don't worry about that.
PAUL: I think, okay. So, last class, the major notes and other stuff that I have added it here. Okay, so the thing that was discussed, I think everybody got the entire content in Notion.
PAUL: no other place that you need to visit, please let me know. The idea is that you guys should use Notion.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Alright, so I will just share the link once.
PAUL: Can you add all the links to study notes here? Majorly, the external links and the other stuff, whatever things where there are additional study material, next class to be discussed. So, majorly, I have added everything, so I think that
PAUL: There should not be any type of problems.
PAUL: Okay, so I've shared the Notion links also. Any instruction? No, like, you can just go through these notes, really, like, if you don't want to directly look into the lecture, this was the main component. Otherwise, just watch the lecture in 2x. Okay, like, whatever is the highest speed which is provided. That is the only thing that I will recommend.
PAUL: Okay, because seeing a 5-hours lecture, really, it's hard for me also, so I know it will be hard for you, okay?
PAUL: And, okay, so these are some estimated plans, like, tomorrow we'll be starting Lancin, like, today's paper, I feel it's important. How many of you gone through the paper at least once? Because there are so many things in this paper. I feel that if anybody's building a rag.
PAUL: Okay, right now in 2025, okay, like, a lot of things are there.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is to…
PAUL: know the things. Okay, the idea is we cannot go deep dive, because this single paper that we'll be discussing, okay, it has multiple subpapers. Okay, so for example.
PAUL: I hope everybody can see my screen.
PAUL: Please let me know.
PAUL: The idea is not to…
PAUL: read the entire paper, okay, because there are so many things. For example, here only. These are all different type of research papers, okay? Now, I will tell you exactly what are the things, step by step, okay, and the working of RAG, the different type of RAG modules, the idea is to explore all these things.
PAUL: So I kept it, because going forward, it will be much more practical. Today's class will be the class, I can say, theoretical class.
PAUL: From tomorrow, we will start with the practical implementations.
PAUL: Okay, a lot of things that get answered in this paper.
PAUL: Okay, now, like, this paper is connected to more than, I can say, 100 research papers. Okay, so I know that nobody can read 100 papers, okay, but the idea is that, you have to understand the evolution. Because of that, very specifically, I have created.
PAUL: this, okay? You read it? All of it, no. I read only the major papers, okay, which get famous, because there are so many papers.
PAUL: It's not possible for me also to read every paper. The idea is only to focus on the papers. So, for example, in this course, we'll be going through the major, like, 15 to 20 papers that I feel you should know. Okay, and that were majorly game-changing, which has been adopted very specifically. Okay? Alright.
PAUL: I think we can start.
PAUL: Please let me know in the chat.
PAUL: Yes, yes, this is publicly available, everything that I'll be sharing. Okay, and even you'll be getting this, I think, inside today's content. Here, I have added it, okay, the RAG Detail Survey. Okay, here…
PAUL: on today's class, you have this particular… later on, I'll be sharing the notes and the other things, because this paper has majorly all the diagrams that I feel. But, to…
PAUL: make the explanation, so I'll be writing it in notes.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Alright, so let's start.
PAUL: Okay, I don't need this anymore. Let me close it here.
PAUL: All right, so right now, as you can see here, so REG for LLM models, a survey. Okay, you can see here, 27 March 2024, so any paper that might come later on, those things won't be available. But the past
PAUL: 3 to 4 years, okay, the major research which has been gone. So, all those things have been listed.
PAUL: So, first of all, let's start with the abstract. I feel that the abstract is important, and, like, for every research paper, we'll be talking about that.
PAUL: So, the large language models showcase impressive capabilities, but encounter challenges like hallucination. Okay, then comes outdated knowledge. Okay, the same thing, referred to as, like, cut-off.
PAUL: training date. Okay, and non-trans…
PAUL: This is very important, like, non-transparent.
PAUL: Untraceable reasoning. I think everybody has heard about reasoning models.
PAUL: In some models, they call it thinking mode. I think people have heard about.
PAUL: Because the reasoning models are pretty much common right now. Okay, so… so that's why untraceable reasoning process. Okay, so it, the main problem is that, though you will get the answer, but exactly from which…
PAUL: data point it is coming, or basically what is the exact weight and bias. It's very hard to say at any point of time.
PAUL: Okay, so right now, major models that have emerged, starting from 2025, I can say. Okay, or that mid-2024, most of them will be reasoning models, if you look into. But I feel that reasoning models are pretty much heavy.
PAUL: Whenever you are doing inferencing, okay, your inferencing time will also increase. So, for example, if you use a reasoning model very specifically for a rat, okay, as compared to a normal general LLM.
PAUL: Okay, you will see that the inference time will always be high, really, and it uses a lot of token also. Because of that, I feel that the context window
PAUL: like, it gets full, okay? Like, with, I can see if the query is complex, the size of the context in the window will be pretty much big, okay? So that's why, like, I'm not a very fan of that, but if you're doing…
PAUL: knowledge-intensive task, okay, where you need to know everything in detail, step by step. At that particular point of time, I can say that, yes, reasoning models are good, but not for every use case. So you have to understand your use case, and then you have to decide.
PAUL: Reasoning models are agentic models? No.
PAUL: Can you define inferencing? Inferencing in the field of data science is simply, like, anything that you do as an input, and you get the output. So, what is the time difference between that input and output? You pass the input, you clicked on predict. Okay, so that particular.
PAUL: Guys, if you are asking about inference, really, then you don't know nothing about data science.
PAUL: I can see everybody's questions, so don't ask me again in the chat. Okay, so let me just give you the info.
PAUL: How many of you know about inference? Because this is…
PAUL: Starting from 2016, everybody talks about inference the same thing.
PAUL: Okay, so I think you can see.
PAUL: Okay, so at any point of time.
PAUL: Inference is also called, like, prediction.
PAUL: Okay, the same thing. The idea is that prediction… okay, now, whenever… Input.
PAUL: Okay, and then you get the output.
PAUL: Okay, now this… the time ticks.
PAUL: to process the output. That is referred to as info time.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a very common concept in the field of machine learning everywhere. If somebody has learned data science, I think this should be familiar to everyone.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Alright, so I think everybody is clear with inference, because going forward, the idea is it's prediction only in simple terms, but okay, people call it inference, majorly. So, that's why the term model inferencing comes into the picture.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a very common term.
PAUL: Which is widely used in the field of data science.
PAUL: for machine learning models, for deep learning models, for LLMs, for everyone.
PAUL: Yes, pretty much correct. Invoking a model and generating the output.
PAUL: Alright, so let's get back to our discussion.
PAUL: Okay, so I will just stop sharing, and let's get back to the paper.
PAUL: Alright, so this is our desktop tool.
PAUL: Alright, so… Now.
PAUL: We were back here. Okay, so the RAG has emerged as a promising solution by incorporating knowledge from external databases.
PAUL: The idea is, it's data sources, okay, but very specifically, they are written here, databases.
PAUL: This enhances the accuracy and the credibility of the generation.
PAUL: Particularly for knowledge internship tasks, and allows for continuous knowledge updates. It means that
PAUL: For RAG, you know that, okay, you can keep on adding the documents. You can always update your vector database at the end of the day. You just need to create the embeddings, and you need to upload them.
PAUL: Now, very specifically, When we are talking about,
PAUL: like, here, very specifically, integration of domain-specific information. Now.
PAUL: previously, like, till 2023 and 2024, okay, like, the idea was to keep LLM generic always. Okay, so that's why, very specifically, the…
PAUL: they have mentioned about that your vector database, or basically the external data sources, okay, they will be domain-specific. But right now, in 2025, the research is moving ahead much more towards domain-specific LLMs. The idea is that to train only for a specific purpose.
PAUL: Okay, so this one thing, so which has not been added, because right now, this is the current research.
PAUL: RAC, synergistically emerges LLM's intrinsic knowledge. So, intrinsic knowledge comes from which memory, guys? Please let me know in the last class we have discussed.
PAUL: Yes, the intrinsic knowledge up in LLM.
PAUL: It comes from which memory? Paramedic. Exactly correct.
PAUL: Intrinsic, knowledge with the vast, dynamic repose of external databases.
PAUL: And whenever we are talking with respect to external databases, we refer to the non-parametric memory. This comprehensive paper offers a detailed examination of the progression of RAG paradigms.
PAUL: encompassing the NAVE rag, Advanced RAG, and the modular rack. So, these three rag architectures that we'll be discussing today, okay? So, like, whenever we are even working in production, okay, we start with something small, other POC, which can be referred to as a nav, then you add some type of more features, then you add more and more features.
PAUL: And finally, the idea is to build something like a modular rack. The idea is to keep every component separate, so that you can plug and play at any point of time, just like the concept of microservices. Okay, if one service fails, the idea is that your entire application should not crash. Okay, so that's why.
PAUL: Now, this paper is not about introducing any type of rag, okay? In this paper, we'll be going through that entire history, major history, okay, that has been going on for the past, like, I can say 3 to 4 years.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why this is a survey paper, rather than introducing a very specific type of RAC. Going forward, we'll be looking into specific RAG papers.
PAUL: Okay, so it meticulously scrutinized the tripartite foundation of RAC frameworks, which include the retrieval, generation, and the augmentation techniques.
PAUL: The paper highlights the state of the art.
PAUL: Embedded in each of these critical components, providing a profound understanding of the advancements of RAG,
PAUL: Furthermore, this paper introduced up-to-date evaluation framework and benchmarks. Okay, at the end, this article delineates the challenges currently faced and points out
PAUL: prospective avenues for R&D. Okay, now, the idea is that we'll be looking into the complete history of that, so the same thing has been written. I think the abstract should be clear for everyone, please let me know, because there is no such
PAUL: I can say complex terminology, at least, here.
PAUL: Now, the introduction part. Okay, so I will be going through the introduction. The idea is that, majorly, like, there are a few terms, like, I think everybody knows about, like, LLMs means Large Language Models, RAG means, okay, retrieval Augmented Generation.
PAUL: Then comes PTM, pre-trained models, okay? So, pre-trained models, the other term can be base model, the other term can be a foundational model, okay? The same thing refers to pre-trained.
PAUL: Okay, then comes ICL, which is basically the, context learning. Okay, so these are a few full forms, which later on you might see, but again, like, we will go through that.
PAUL: Alright, so first of all, let's try to look into the history or the journey of RAD. Okay, how…
PAUL: it has emerged, because the basics of RAG, you guys already know. But, in the research, there were certain things that we have seen.
PAUL: we might not do it, okay? But I feel that at any point of time, you shouldn't.
PAUL: Okay, so first of all, let's focus on this particular diagram, okay? So, let me just increase the font here, okay? And this is the first image which gives you the rough journey of different types of papers, implementations, okay, that has been mentioned.
PAUL: So right now, this is the tree, the RAG research tree, okay, the technology tree of RAG research.
PAUL: Now, very specifically, there are 3 different stages that have been defined here, okay? So, right now, I can say the left-hand side is… refers to the fine-tuning stage. Okay, then there is a pre-training stage, okay, and then there is an inferencing stage.
PAUL: Three important stages, and if you ask me, so, which one is the most used one, or the most dominated one, that is the inference one.
PAUL: Okay, because pre-training, very, very costly, not possible. Fine-tuning, rare use cases. Not every time that we do forever. Okay? So, we'll be going through, and right now, you can see there are a lot of things which are written here, okay?
PAUL: So, right here, if you look into RAGI2E, Promptagator.
PAUL: Okay, then comes, AAR, FLIR. Now, these are all research papers, guys. So, you don't need to go into these research papers, because
PAUL: Major, if I talk about, we'll be talking few of them very specifically. And here, majors like self-rag. I feel that self-rag is a very important paper that even we'll be discussing, and even we'll be doing the implementation of self-rag.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Then, another important paper, I feel that Uni-MS RAG, okay, Unified Multiple Sources, okay, that's that full form. Okay, other than that, like, MKTOD, RAGROS, so these are other papers also, but not so much things.
PAUL: Okay, so here also, a lot of papers that you'll be seeing. So, don't confuse… okay, don't be confused that, okay, now what are these? At any point of time, if you want to know, you can just take the name and you can search for research paper, but be sure that everything is not a paper here.
PAUL: Okay, it can be an implementation also. Okay, like, for every implementation you might get, not a paper. Okay, that can be, because some can be custom-based solution.
PAUL: Okay, and models? No, these are not models, okay? These are majorly, like, RAG architectures.
PAUL: Okay? Now, let's start with the stages, because you have to understand each stage, okay? And majorly, as I told you.
PAUL: Inferencing is that we will be doing a lot. Okay, pre-training, like, very, very, like, I can say costly approach, where you, do training two times. Okay, so let's try to understand each of these things step by step.
PAUL: So, first of all, just let's go through the paper, okay, and then I will try to break everything step-by-step for you.
PAUL: Okay, the stages of involving RAT majorly includes pre-training. I think everybody understands the concept of pre-training.
PAUL: Yes? What is pre-training?
PAUL: And it means that you will be doing some type of task before training.
PAUL: Okay, so, then comes fine-tuning. What is the concept of fine-tuning?
PAUL: It means that you have some type of a base model, then you bring your own training data, okay, and then you create a new model.
PAUL: Okay? And finally, you have inferencing. It means that you are not changing the LLM, or the model.
PAUL: Okay, so this is majorly that we do. I think everybody is familiar with these three things, because these are simple machine learning concepts, so please let me know you guys are familiar with pre-training, fine-tuning, and inferencing.
PAUL: Everyone?
PAUL: What we do in pre-training, actually in pre-training, okay, you create a very, like, specific, type of task that you do for your training to be much more optimized.
PAUL: That is the pre-training process. That's why it becomes pre. It means that there are different types of tasks. It can be with respect to your data optimization, okay, those things that comes into the picture.
PAUL: Yes, pre-training means, like, from scratch, it means that everything that you will be doing, it means that you need always a data set, even for fine-tuning you need, but pre-training means simply that everything will be doing it from scratch. Scratch elements.
PAUL: Okay, for which you need a very big infrastructure. The idea is, like, training a model from, like, zero. That's why, like, you can think about in that way.
PAUL: Okay, so I will just highlight those points in the notes once, that going forward, these terms should be pretty much clear in your mind. Okay, so… three steps that happens, so… let's stop, just wait, okay?
PAUL: Because going forward, majorly, you guys will be working with three things.
PAUL: So, the first one is… pre-training.
PAUL: Okay, so for pre-training, what you need?
PAUL: Okay? So… so this I will refer to as, like, Scratch.
PAUL: Okay, about zero training.
PAUL: It means that you do everything from the starting point.
PAUL: Then you have your fine tube.
PAUL: In fine-tuning what happens? You already have a, like I can say, a pre-trained model, okay?
PAUL: Also referred to as a base model.
PAUL: The other term is foundational model.
PAUL: all things refer to the same stuff, okay? On top of an existing model, you bring your own.
PAUL: Domain-specific data.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: And then you get a new model.
PAUL: Okay? And the third approach, which is basically the… inferencing part?
PAUL: Kia.
PAUL: directly, Using a pre-trained model.
PAUL: Okay, so the examples you can think about.
PAUL: Gpt.
PAUL: Any type of GPT-based models are there. Okay, then you have your Cloud models, cohaw models, Okay
PAUL: So, in inferencing, you directly consume.
PAUL: Okay? But these two are, like.
PAUL: the very… I can say this one, pre-training is very, very costly, okay, because you do everything from scratch, so you need a very good infra. So that's why very less research here that you will be seeing, okay, as compared to the others.
PAUL: Okay, so I hope this part is clear for everyone.
PAUL: Okay, alright.
PAUL: Now, let's get back to our discussion.
PAUL: So, that's why if you look into the pre-training branch, you will see that very less papers are there.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, very less that I feel.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, one of the pre-training
PAUL: approach is like COG. Okay, now this paper is…
PAUL: little bit famous, I can say. Like, right now, Tiger is famous much more in 2024 and 2025, but this paper was very, very famous back in 2023.
PAUL: I think everybody has heard about the paper, attention is all you need.
PAUL: Yes, the most fundamental paper, even in the last class, also, that I have told you, okay?
PAUL: Alright, now,
PAUL: I think, there is one paper, referred to as, like, copy is all you need, okay, so…
PAUL: I'm just showing you the paper. Okay, later on, if you are interested, because this is a pre-training approach, so, like, we won't be discussing. So, this is, like, one of the famous papers.
PAUL: Okay, with respect to pre-training, very specifically. But again, like, in the RAG, we don't need… so, like, in this paper, if you read, there won't be a single term called as RAG in this paper.
PAUL: Okay, so not a single term that you will be getting with respect to this, because this research comes from Telson TI Lab, but again, like, I feel that
PAUL: back in 2023, like, one of the most game-changing papers, okay, to build LLMs, okay, very specifically. Okay, so that's why, like, the copy… COG stands for copy generator. So, copy is all you need, or copy generator is the actual need.
PAUL: Okay, so one sample paper that I showed, similarly, you have rags and other stuff.
PAUL: Okay, then right now, Tiger is very, very famous, so in 2025, very specifically, if I'm talking about…
PAUL: Okay, now let's try to understand
PAUL: The pre-training phase a little bit much more.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: No, we are not going to discuss pre-training. Pre-training is about much more building LLMs. This, is… this course is much more focused towards the inferencing. So, these are the main papers that we'll be discussing in this course.
PAUL: Okay, two…
PAUL: teach, pre-training, it might take 3 to 4 months. You have to understand. It's not like in one shot. To teach fine-tuning, it's much more easy, but pre-training is very, very hard.
PAUL: Okay? Now let's try to understand
PAUL: each of the phases, step by step, okay? So, what I will do, I will take a screenshot of this, and I will attach it in my notes. I think that will be better. Otherwise, I have to switch the screen multiple times.
PAUL: Okay, so just wait.
PAUL: Let me just… Take this money out.
PAUL: Now, let's get back to our Zoom, just wait.
PAUL: Okay, now it's, everyone can focus on the paper, or basically the nodes that I'll be discussing.
PAUL: Okay, alright.
PAUL: Alright, now, three things that I want to discuss once again. Okay, now, when… now, if somebody asks you, when we have to do pre-training?
PAUL: Okay, so that part also should be clear, okay?
PAUL: When you have to do pre-training, okay, so the idea is.
PAUL: Okay, so when, very specific, you guys, it means that you want to build your own Eden.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: build?
PAUL: Yoro?
PAUL: Elena.
PAUL: Okay, so that is basically the…
PAUL: pre-training part, very specifically. If somebody asks you, okay, then comes fine-tuning. Fine-tuning, I feel that this is a good approach for taking, somehow, cost key. It means that you take a open-source model.
PAUL: On top of that open source model, you bring your own data and you tune it. So here, also, you'll be getting, in fine-tuning, you get very good accuracy.
PAUL: Okay? So it means that domain-specific tasks
PAUL: Okay, domain-specific tasks.
PAUL: And, like, with respect to inferencing, which we use widely with respect to RAD, now, this is the cheapest option that we have.
PAUL: Okay, so I will try to break 3 points very specifically, okay, because
PAUL: pre-training, not everybody can do. Fine-tuning, some can do.
PAUL: Okay, but inferencing, everybody can do. It means that the LLM is hosted somewhere through API call, or through a local model, okay, or through local hosting, you know, cloud infra. You can do this type of stuff.
PAUL: Okay? Now, somebody's asking when you have to build a model from scratch.
PAUL: When you have to build a model from scratch, if you feel that
PAUL: If you feel that any type of pre-trained base or foundational model, it means that some type of pre-trained model is not available for the task that you are doing, then only you will try to build your own pre-trained model. It means that, simply just think about, you have an LLM.
PAUL: That LLM has been trained on some data.
PAUL: Okay? Trained on some data.
PAUL: Now, you feel that, okay, probably your data that you have.
PAUL: Okay? It's not relevant at all.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: It means that, simply, you can think about, okay, now this was trained on maps.
PAUL: Okay, and later on, somehow, you brought… bioinformatics.
PAUL: Okay, a simple example that you can think about two different subjects.
PAUL: Now, at that particular point of time, you can say that, okay, even if I do a fine-tuning.
PAUL: Okay, so what… what is the… if you do a fine-tuning.
PAUL: Okay, then also the main model, okay, which is having this max information, okay?
PAUL: that particular information will be pretty much dominant, okay, as compared to your information only, which is basically the bioinformatics, okay? So if you want only a model which is to focus on bioinformatics, in that case, you will be completely building your own LLM from scratch.
PAUL: Okay, so it totally depends upon the data.
PAUL: Okay, so if you feel that, okay, the current pre-trained model knows nothing about the task that I am doing, then you have to build a LLM.
PAUL: Okay? Is this part clear for everyone?
PAUL: Okay, when you have to build an LLM,
PAUL: Okay, see, really, nobody's building an LLM. Okay, it's, like, in India, only 3 to 4 major organizations are doing, in government and a few in private, but really, like.
PAUL: Pre-training is very costly. It means that, really.
PAUL: Okay, just think about… this is a rough estimation, $10 million.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: to build a good quality LLM. It means that the top benchmarks.
PAUL: Okay, it might increase to 100 million also. To do the research, you need at least 1 million USD.
PAUL: Okay, to do just the R&D.
PAUL: Okay, R&D for this one.
PAUL: That's why this is a very, very, like, expensive task, so nobody does it. You have to understand.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Then comes, your, fine-tuning. Fine-tuning is somehow cheaper, I feel that. You don't need millions, at least. Okay, it can be done probably in $10,000 to $20,000, okay?
PAUL: Now, somebody's asking why we're cutting LLM?
PAUL: That's the thing. Okay, the idea is to consume the elements, almost, okay? Or to perform a fine-tuning task.
PAUL: Because for RAG, one of the most core components is always keeping the LLM fixed. That's why this particular task of inferencing comes into the picture. Okay, which is the cheapest?
PAUL: Okay, it means that we don't do any type of modification to the existing LLM model, the large language model, or the small language model.
PAUL: Okay? So that's why it's all about the inferencing that we'll be focusing on.
PAUL: Fine-tuning also comes, but again, that is much more LLM-specific, not more, like, RAG-specific. Okay, so RAG-specific is much more about inference.
PAUL: Like, we have the other course of LLM, ops, very specifically there, we dive into much more towards this LLM techniques.
PAUL: Now, I hope this part is clear, pre-training, fine-tuning, and inferencing. Okay, when to do, what to do?
PAUL: Yes, can we proceed ahead with the next step? Guys, please let me know.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Okay, now, I'll be focusing on, one important thing, because, right now, based on these, branches, okay, there are a lot of important papers. Okay, so right now… okay, let me just increase the font here, yeah.
PAUL: So, like, I feel that self-rag is a very, very important paper, okay, that, I will be discussing going forward with,
PAUL: Okay, I think yes.
PAUL: the self-rad, okay, so we'll be doing the practical implementation also. I'll be taking two to three papers from finding. Okay, that I feel that it is important.
PAUL: Okay, so self-reg is one of them, then comes Uni-MS RAG. Okay, so unified multiple… the name Uni-MS is there, but at the end of the day of understanding, this is just taking data from multiple sources, and then building the RAG. Okay, so Unified Multiple Data Sources.
PAUL: Now, so, like, this particular branch, the orange color branch.
PAUL: we won't be focusing a lot. Okay, so I can say this will be, like, 0% focus to us. Okay, this will be somehow close to 10% focus, and this will be, like, 90% focus.
PAUL: This branch is the most important branch for us. Okay, which is the inferencing branch, because all the major papers that we'll be discussing, it comes under the inferencing. It means that we will be just
PAUL: Using the data.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And what will be changing? Probably, it can be the retriever part, okay, then probably with respect to generation part, those things very specifically that will be changing.
PAUL: So, it's all about the inferencing that we are going to discuss.
PAUL: Now, let's focus on a few of the models, okay? So, little bit about models that I feel that you should know. So…
PAUL: Let's stop, because I have kept them in one place.
PAUL: Alright, so, very specifically with respect to the modes of training.
PAUL: Okay, so going forward, PTM, always remember, it's referred to as the pre-trained model.
PAUL: FTM, fine-tuned model, okay, and INF, which is basically the inferencing. So in the entire paper, you'll be seeing these terms.
PAUL: Now, with respect to free trade model, I feel that COG, this is one important paper. If you have ever time, okay, you can actually go through this. I feel that somehow, yes, it is a…
PAUL: Game changer, but back in 2023. Then comes Tiger. If you are working very specifically in 2025, this is one of the major standards.
PAUL: Then come your FTM-based models. Okay, so in FTM-based models, self-rag, okay, this paper we'll be discussing in class, so not to worry.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And then you have FLIR. This, also, we'll be discussing in class.
PAUL: Okay, so Wrike Flare is right now at 2025 standard.
PAUL: Okay, and finally comes your inferencing. In inferencing, majorly, like, more than 10 to 15 people that we'll be discussing. But, a few major ones that I feel is, like, one is CRAG,
PAUL: Okay, which is referred to as corrective rack. Okay, so, like, very good. Then comes your iteration.
PAUL: Okay, so ITER…
PAUL: region. So, this is an iterative task, we'll be talking about these type of tasks today, but I feel that at least, like, a few of these papers, I'm just listing, that if you have time, you can go through. Otherwise, simply skip it, because in class, yes, the major ones, we will be talking about that.
PAUL: Again?
PAUL: Okay, yes, and That doesn't come here, like, CAG is there, which is Catch Augmented Correct Center.
PAUL: For riders. Who?
PAUL: Now, let's try to look into the core architecture of rank. Okay, so I feel that this part is important, because right now, if I tell you about every rank, do you want me to let… tell you about all these
PAUL: Architectures, probably in one line or two-line.
PAUL: Because, really, like, or the major ones. Okay. Because, I don't know a few people might be interested.
PAUL: Alright, so… Alright.
PAUL: This part will take some time, because this is much more theoretical.
PAUL: Okay,
PAUL: That's why in high level, I will just write at least few of the major papers that I feel. Not all, okay? Otherwise, like, you can do rest as homework, okay?
PAUL: That's why. Okay, so let's go through a few of the papers.
PAUL: For now, and then. It will take maximum, I think, 5 to 10 minutes, so… to major peoples.
PAUL: Okay, so, let's start, first of all, with the pre-training branch, okay? So, in pre-training, I have already told
PAUL: Okay, because this, with respect to pre-training, the papers will be much more focused towards one thing.
PAUL: Transformers, always remember. Because this is all about working and building elements.
PAUL: Okay, so they will be much more focused towards the transformers architecture. There will be modification with respect to the attention mechanism very specifically. Okay, so a lot of new concepts that will be brought, like swing.
PAUL: Okay, fine, transformers and other stuff. So, one of the major, papers… okay.
PAUL: like, majorly used is known as RELM, okay, and even you can see it,
PAUL: Very specifically. Okay, so this Realm paper was, like, the first time
PAUL: Where two things were trained. Okay, two things. One was the LLM, Okay, plow the Retriever.
PAUL: two things were trained. Okay, so a joint training.
PAUL: That was done very specifically. Now, what is the retriever? I think everybody remember last class, Dense Passage Retriever, where you have your two encoders, then the two embeddings, and finally you compare the similarity score. So, both of those things were very specifically mentioned.
PAUL: Okay, so somebody's asking for the paper link. I think you should have Sumit Mishra with you, okay? Now, I feel that this paper was game-changing, but again, like, it… only research can be done. Real-life applications, it's very, very hard, because training two things at one shop.
PAUL: Okay, like, very, very expensive task. Then comes a retro.
PAUL: This paper, I feel that, again, an interesting paper that you have.
PAUL: Okay, now, this is very specific to, like, creating transformers only for retrieval tasks.
PAUL: Okay, so, Anna… Okay, so retrieval… Based transformer.
PAUL: Okay, I see. When you actually into research, the idea was to create a transformer only to do a retrieval task.
PAUL: Okay, and this actually enhanced the task.
PAUL: Okay, like, the results were very, very good, but again, not everybody can do it. The idea is, if you want to make something generic, so the whole world can do it. So, but again, like, costly, but again.
PAUL: Totally, the idea is that for research, it's good, but for practical production, not so much good.
PAUL: Okay, then comes, another paper that you have very specific with respect to ATLAS. Okay, now, that paper was also
PAUL: Few papers are mentioned in this one. Okay, so this was, few-shot learning. How many of you know about few-shot?
PAUL: In prompt engineering, there is a concept of few-shot, where you provide few examples, okay, and based on those examples, okay, the ideas provide, like, few examples to the LLM,
PAUL: And based on that, the LLM will respond. This is the common concept with respect to
PAUL: the prompt engineering part. So, a very similar example here, you will be providing the training examples. In your train set.
PAUL: just think about the same question. Okay, we'll have different type of rephrased versions. Okay, so the data set was built in such a way. So, this Atlas paper was also, I feel that, like, a good one. Okay, so here also, few shot with retrieval.
PAUL: That you have.
PAUL: Yeah, because, yes, I've gone through these papers a long time back, but, really, like, right now in 2025, if somebody is really working with respect to pre-training, then only I feel.
PAUL: Then, came, like, 2023,
PAUL: Already, I've told, the main paper was COG. Okay, copy is all you need. That particular paper I have already shown you. Okay, so, which is referred to as copy generator.
PAUL: Okay. And very specifically here, decoder-based architectures are used, so… and this is also a very good paper. Now I will, directly come to, like, 2024.
PAUL: Okay, so in 2024, the major one is Tiger.
PAUL: So, when I'm talking with respect to Tiger, okay, so…
PAUL: This is the most advanced pre-training approach.
PAUL: If somebody is building an LLM right now into 2025 from scratch, okay, I will say that please use
PAUL: Tiger, okay, like, the most advanced pre-trained approach that you have.
PAUL: There is something called as Raven, so that is also famous.
PAUL: But,
PAUL: So, like, my personal favorite, if you talk, it's always Tiger. Okay, I feel that the results are somehow better, okay? So… and now, Raven, if you see, okay, so here you will see Retrieval.
PAUL: augmented. The idea was to build it for a rack.
PAUL: Encoder, decoder.
PAUL: This is somehow, like, the major standard, which I will always follow. This is the best one that you guys can go ahead. So, like, if you don't want to go through any research paper, only one research paper, if my suggestion, okay, if you want to spend some time on pre-training, go through Tiger.
PAUL: Okay? Others you can skip, because really, like, nobody has the time to do so much, but at least go through one paper. It will be very good from the interview perspective.
PAUL: If you are actually going for an interview, there are very less candidates who really knows about pre-training, or something related to pre-training. Nobody knows that, okay? So, that's why.
PAUL: Alright, later on in the notes, I'll be sharing the research paper links for Tiger and Raven. Okay, don't worry about it.
PAUL: Now, I'll be jumping directly to the, fine-tuning task, okay? Because few papers from here that I've already told
PAUL: And even few people, like Atlas and others also that I have…
PAUL: Okay, now, a few papers with respect to fine-tuning.
PAUL: fine-tuning papers, because these papers we will discuss in class. So, like, self-rag, Okay.
PAUL: So, like, this… you can think about self-dat refers to a self-improvement, or a self-healing. It means that, based on some threshold, if it gives wrong answer, okay, then we will try to again, like, reiterate, okay.
PAUL: The re… the idea is to re-invoke the…
PAUL: retriever and get, again, the result. So, there is a process based on the threshold that you have.
PAUL: So, this is one of the papers, even with respect to applications, like, we'll be doing a real-time application of self-right.
PAUL: We will be going through the entire code. This module is available in Linecraft directly with respect to agentic implementation.
PAUL: Then, the other one that I feel, which one is, FLIR. Okay, now, these are major papers of 2024 and 2025.
PAUL: Okay, so FEAR stands for, like, Forward Looking Active Retrieval.
PAUL: Okay, this paper also we'll be going through.
PAUL: Because from here, when you are actually building your own architecture in your organization, these papers actually help you to, like, completely, like, reformulate that particular architecture. Otherwise, it's always the NAIP version.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Then after FLIR, another paper, that we'll be talking about, which is the Uni-MS rag.
PAUL: This is the major standard. Okay, Uni-MS stands for… okay, so, like, Unified Multiple Data Sources. That is the simple concept, okay? Unified Multiple Data Sources. This paper also will be going through
PAUL: Okay, now these are all classes in I Will Teach, so you don't have to worry, okay? So, simply, you can skip it.
PAUL: Okay, then there is self name and others. Okay, so self memory.
PAUL: Okay, this paper was also good. Okay. But right now, for memory layer, we'll be using some other application very specifically.
PAUL: Okay, the idea was to give memory to your RAT, okay, and very specifically, right now, there are applications like Memo, then you have memory from Gibson AI. Okay, there are certain tools that we'll be utilizing. So, like, this paper, not so much relevant.
PAUL: But at a certain point of time, yes, it was that, I feel.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Then,
PAUL: few papers, okay, which are the major ones with respect to query optimization. How many of you have heard about query optimization?
PAUL: Yes? Like, the concept of, Heidi.
PAUL: Okay, because these things in class will be doing the practical implementation, query optimization.
PAUL: So, very specifically for this, hypothetical embeddings, Look at this…
PAUL: Heidi, very, very important, okay? Though it takes some amount… some amount of time, okay, it means the inferencing time will increase, but again, the results are good. Then you have wrapped up.
PAUL: Who this is… hypothetical embeddings.
PAUL: So, don't be worried. So, these are some practical implementations that we'll be doing in class later on, probably, like, next month, once we have covered all the basics.
PAUL: Okay, then you have Raptor. So, Raptor is also, like, it's at, tree level, okay, so,
PAUL: A 3-level retriever.
PAUL: So, this is also good.
PAUL: Okay, tree-level retriever, the concept of graph rack. How many have you heard about graph rack?
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: Few people might have heard about.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, that particular concept actually came from this one, okay? So, the graph rack concept.
PAUL: We'll be talking about that by taking an example, like, Neo4J, very specifically a graph database that we'll be taking, okay, and then we'll be doing the implementation.
PAUL: Okay, so these are a few of the major ones, okay, with respect to, I can say, inferencing. Now, these papers that I'm talking about, HID, Raptor, they are much more towards the inferencing part.
PAUL: Okay, then you have your… CRAC, already I have told, corrective rack, very, very good. Okay.
PAUL: there's also practical implementation that we'll be doing. Then comes your iter.
PAUL: Jen, okay, so an iterative task, this one also we'll be talking about. Okay, so these are the few papers that you guys can go through, and I'll be attaching the links. Like, for pre-training these papers, for fine-taining these papers, and for inference, like, I'll try to give at least 3 papers in every section in Notion, so that if you have time, please go through.
PAUL: Okay, now let's leave this part, and let's proceed ahead with the architectures of RAC. I feel that part is much more important.
PAUL: Alright, so with respect to the architecture…
PAUL: All right. So, right now, this is the architecture which has been mentioned here very specifically. Okay, so everybody can see my screen. Can you see the workflow right here?
PAUL: So, let's start from the right,
PAUL: Hand side, the top right, because this is the first part.
PAUL: So…
PAUL: right here, as we know in the last class we have discussed, to build a rack, what you need.
PAUL: you need some type of external data sources. Now, those data sources will be, like, indexed, or basically, you can think about chunks as to be created. Now, from those chunks, vector will be created.
PAUL: And finally, the vector, or basically the embedding that I'm referring, that embedding will be saved into some type of vector databases. So this is basically the starting point at any point of time.
PAUL: And can you see here, this input also coming here?
PAUL: Okay, so,
PAUL: At any point of time, I told you the input query. So, right now, how do you evaluate the fact? So, this is just a query, which has been provided as an example. Now, any type of input that comes, that also needs to be converted into the embedding.
PAUL: That was the concept that we learned in DPR. So, two types of embedding, and then we'll perform a similarity search. Okay, so with respect to
PAUL: Phase 1, so this is Phase 1. If you remember in last class, I…
PAUL: discussed Phase 1 is all about data ingestion, which is this part.
PAUL: Third top right, where indexing has been very specifically mentioned.
PAUL: Noted?
PAUL: Alright, so let's take this one.
PAUL: And I will take this image into the notes.
PAUL: Just wait.
PAUL: Ctrl 4… Let's just…
PAUL: Okay? So, if somebody is not familiar with the terminology, okay, I will just go through the figure, what is the representation which is being done here.
PAUL: So, right here, as you can see, a representative instance of a RAG process applied to Q&A, or basically question answering, or you can think about chatbots anywhere. It mainly consists of three steps. The first one is indexing. So, what is indexing? In simple terms, documents are split into chunks.
PAUL: then, chunks are basically encoded into vectors and stored in a vector database. Okay, so simply, you can think about embeddings. Okay, so embeddings are stored in a vector database, the same stuff. Embedding and vectors, don't get confused.
PAUL: Then comes the process 2, which is basically the retrieval. Okay, so what is retrieval? Okay, the idea is to find the top key chunks, okay, based on the similarity score, okay, or based on the semantic search that will be performed.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Image is hiding the sentence.
PAUL: Okay, so let me know if it is visible or not. You guys can open it from your side also, if you want, okay? So, here are the top keychums, most relevant. So, the idea is that, you can see here, this is the vector database, and in this vector database, if you try to…
PAUL: Search. So, what type of search? Similarity search for now. Okay. Now, once you perform the search, you'll be getting these type of answers, like chunk 1, chunk 2, chunk 3.
PAUL: Why chunk? Because, during the phase of data ingestion, you only get different types of chunks in your vector database. So, when you're performing the search, so based on that, you'll be getting a top K. So, K is a parameter. So, it can be top 5, it can be top 10, top 15, top 20 chunks, totally.
PAUL: Now, once you have those chunks, now, this chunks becomes the context. Now, this is a context, okay? And that will be combined with prompt, okay? And based on that, you'll be getting the answer. Okay, so here's a simple example that has been shown here, okay? So, alright.
PAUL: Now, finally, when you are getting… I told you, you have three things with respect to a rack. One, the context that is coming from VectorTV. The second, there will be prompt, and the third one is the query.
PAUL: Okay, so once you have these three things, the query, okay, the context from the vector DB and the prompts, then finally you will be getting your response.
PAUL: Okay, now, which is basically the answer. So here, they have simply told that, okay, like, without drag, simply telling that I am unable to provide comments on future events, because it has no access to
PAUL: recent events, in simple example. And with RAG, this suggests significant internal disagreement. Okay, so, like, based on the query, simply you can say that, okay, like, RAG is giving you the output because
PAUL: the information that, the system was looking for. Okay, it has… it is available in the external data source, okay?
PAUL: So, this is how the simple working opera… now, let me know that.
PAUL: any type of query that you have, because this phase, the top right-hand corner, that is the data ingestion phase.
PAUL: Then the user asks the query. The query will be converted into an embedding. Once,
PAUL: you have the embedding, then you will perform the similarity score. Based on the score, you'll be getting the top K chunks. Once you have the top K chunks, then it will become, okay? So I will just write the flow, and you people let me know.
PAUL: What is contextual prompt? This is context. Contextual prompt? There is no such thing.
PAUL: It is context and prompt, okay? So let me just write the flow, so that things become clear in your mind.
PAUL: So, let's get back to our notes. I will just stop sharing this screen.
PAUL: Because this is the main rag, which is referred to as the nav rag.
PAUL: That's why this architecture… we always start with this architecture, and then we will try to amplify it with more features.
PAUL: side Raul, that is, not in this paper, like, rack token and RAG sequencer.
PAUL: a rack, a token, majorly, I told you.
PAUL: That particular thing. Okay, so ask me this question with respect to ducts, then I will let you know.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: So, first of all, based on the flow that we had.
PAUL: Okay, I thought I copied that one just quit.
PAUL: Control 4…
PAUL: Alright, so with respect to the flow, okay, so two-level flow will be there, Phase 1 and Phase 2, just like our class discussion, okay? So, in phase one.
PAUL: Okay? You have your data sources, Okay? Those data sources…
PAUL: So directly indexing we can write, or the same thing. Okay, so chunks…
PAUL: Okay? Chunks will be converted into vectors.
PAUL: Okay, now vector to vector dB.
PAUL: Okay? So, now this is referring to this particular part that you have.
PAUL: Very specifically.
PAUL: Okay, so… Now, in the next phase that you have, which is the Phase 2, Okay? Now, Phase 2.
PAUL: The query will come from the user. So, user, then comes your query. Query will be converted into…
PAUL: Vector or embedding?
PAUL: Embedding and vector, the same thing, guys, so don't get confused here. Okay? Now, once you have the embedding, then you will perform the…
PAUL: Similarity score?
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, from the similarity score, you'll be getting the output of?
PAUL: Top gate?
PAUL: chunks?
PAUL: Okay? Now, these top key chunks becomes your context.
PAUL: Okay? So this becomes the context. So right now, if you look into this image, so this was the chunks, and now this particular chunk that you have, you can see here, chunk 1, chunk 2, chunk 3, so this becomes the context.
PAUL: Okay? And on top of that, like, prompts, very specifically, that comes into the picture. So… Context…
PAUL: Okay, so plus prompt.
PAUL: That's why in last class also I've discussed, so the same architecture remains here. Plus… quid.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And then, finally, you get your output.
PAUL: the same thing that has been shown in this image also, okay? So, see, here the query, the query is basically the question which is being shown here. With that, you have this, okay? Now, very specifically, they have not given an example of the prompt here.
PAUL: Okay? But, prompt is a set of instructions, just like, okay, like, you are a expert in this, okay, and you have to do this task. So, like, going forward, like, tomorrow I'll be showing you multiple prompt examples, so this is one of them.
PAUL: And based on that, you'll be getting the output. So this flow is clear for everyone. This is the raw working of a rank that has been mentioned.
PAUL: Why LLM in diagram?
PAUL: Because these three things
PAUL: goes to the LLM. That's why. If you want to break it much more, okay, you can think about… okay, just wait,
PAUL: The water.
PAUL: Okay, now let me pack these three things.
PAUL: In one place, okay, these three things… goes to the LLM.
PAUL: Okay, so I can…
PAUL: Okay, and finally, the LLM will give you the response.
PAUL: Okay, so a few people ask this question where LLM comes into the picture, because LLM is responsible for doing the generation.
PAUL: Okay. And now, if somebody asks you how the generation is done, based on three parameters, the context, the prompt, and the query.
PAUL: Is this part clear? I hope we can move back to the paper. Is query and prompt same? No.
PAUL: Query is the question that is being asked, so this is the query.
PAUL: Okay, and here, prompt has not been shown. Prompt is a different setup instruction. So, for example, okay, here if I ask, okay, query will be always an intricative question, majorly. Okay, it's just like a question you have to think about.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And, your prompt will be a setup instruction.
PAUL: Okay, set of instructions. So, prompt, and this, totally different. Okay? So, when we'll be doing the practicals, these things will be much more clear.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Somebody's asking why we need the query.
PAUL: Because, based on your question, you will be getting the answer. Prompt is just a set of instructions. For example, if you want a JSON output, if you want a CSGB output, what type of output, whether in Markdown, okay? So that's one.
PAUL: Okay, so I hope now this part is clear, we will move to the next phase. Please let me know in the chat, guys.
PAUL: Do we build a query prompt, or no? I'll be talking about prompt tomorrow, don't worry. For now, prompt is just a setup instruction, okay? So, if I show you that, prompt…
PAUL: Generally, to LLMs, we pass a prompt so that we get much more refined answer. That's why.
PAUL: the idea is to get much more refined and structured answer from the alums. So their prompt comes into the picture. But at the end of the day, there has to be a query, because based on a query, you'll be getting the answer. But prompts help you to make that, answer much more structured.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is to refinement of the response from the engine. Very specifically, that's why prompts are being used.
PAUL: It can be an AI system, message system, prompt, okay? In different frameworks, the names are different.
PAUL: All right, guys, so let's proceed ahead, then, with the next phase. Okay, so in the paper.
PAUL: Now, if you are comfortable with this architecture, now this architecture is referred to as the nive architecture.
PAUL: Okay, so… Now, here, you will be seeing these three architectures, okay?
PAUL: Now, please, let me know, with the first architecture you guys go through, okay, because this part we have already discussed. We have not discussed two things, the advanced rag and the modular rag.
PAUL: Okay, so I want you guys to look into the nave rag architecture, and it's something that you feel that you don't know, only this part, the left-hand side, because this architecture is referred to as the NAVRG.
PAUL: Please go through this, okay, and then let me…
PAUL: What is Frozen LLM?
PAUL: Where weights and biases are frozen.
PAUL: Why frozen LLM?
PAUL: See you guys!
PAUL: Whenever there is a model you have, you download the model and use it in your local machine. It's always a frozen version.
PAUL: Okay? The other version, like the actively trained version. It means that, like, probably every 2 weeks you train it, but there is always the frozen on top of frozen, if you want to do some type of modification.
PAUL: How many of you know the concept of transfer learning in deep learning?
PAUL: Where you freeze some layers, and few layers that you train.
PAUL: All good in name, okay?
PAUL: Alright, see, I'll… Frozen LLM, now, these concepts are, guys, basics of deep learning.
PAUL: That's why, like, deep learning is important. I will tell you in high level for now, just try to understand.
PAUL: With respect to fine-tuning, you can think about it, the task of fine-tuning.
PAUL: Alright, so let me just take a model. Okay, so for now, we'll just try to draw a model.
PAUL: Okay, in that model, you have multiple layers.
PAUL: Okay, so a lot of lines that I need to draw. So, you understand that, yes, there are others also in the process. Okay, now let's take an example. So, here. So, our model…
PAUL: Have?
PAUL: 200 layers.
PAUL: Okay? Now, this is our input layer, and this is our output layer.
PAUL: Okay? Input and output. So generally, with respect to, for example, if I do a fine-tuning, Okay.
PAUL: Okay? So, out of these 200 years, I will say that, okay, so let's keep 150 years, Frozen.
PAUL: It means that frozen, the meaning of frozen is… width…
PAUL: When biases value, you don't change.
PAUL: Okay, don't change.
PAUL: Now, you have your 50 layers. For 50 layers, I will say that, okay, let's do a retraining of these layers.
PAUL: Okay? Where your weights and biases will change.
PAUL: So, retraining, it means that now, retraining on what?
PAUL: On your specific data.
PAUL: Okay, that you want.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why. So when I'm… when there is a term called a frozen LLM, it means that all the layers are frozen. Okay, so there is no fine-tuning. I hope this part is clear with respect to frozen.
PAUL: How to determine which layer to which chosen, it's a hyperparameter. You have to take the decision.
PAUL: Okay, you have to understand.
PAUL: more layers you want to train, more will be a training time, and the cost will be much more higher. You can just choose the last 20 years or 30 years. It's totally a hyperparameter that needs to be decided by you.
PAUL: No, these are not new rooms, I'm talking about layers, guys.
PAUL: Retraining is changing the parameters? Exactly correct. Retraining is actually changing your weights and biases.
PAUL: So, okay, so that's why 150 year, which are the frozen weights and biases, and only for 50 years that you are doing the training. Okay?
PAUL: Transfer learning and fine-tuning, same stuff.
PAUL: There is a subtle difference. Very specifically, the transfer lending term is used much more with respect to vision-related tasks, whereas for NLP-related tasks, it's much more about the fine-tuning. But at the end of the day, the core concept remains the same.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: In fine-tuning, very specifically with respect to transfer learning.
PAUL: Like, only you can keep the architecture, you can remove all the weights, and you can retrain everything from scratch. Okay, that is one benefit, but the idea is always that you froze few years.
PAUL: Okay? That you have to understand.
PAUL: Alright guys, so let's move. I hope everybody understood the meaning of Frozen. The idea was to tell you Frozen, rather than discussing what is transfer learning, okay?
PAUL: The cost, I cannot say the cost of exactly, totally depends upon the architecture, guys. Okay, nobody can tell you what is the cost of finding tuning that can come.
PAUL: Okay, so please let me know. Everybody is now familiar with the NEBRAG, which is mentioned here.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, if I ask you what are the few benefits, in simple terms, or the characteristics here, very specifically of NEBRA?
PAUL: Okay, so let's quickly go through this, okay? So, with respect to NAV rag that you have.
PAUL: So one of the major… okay, can I say that it is a linear flow? Linear and pretty much sequential flow.
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: in Nevrak.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Linear and sequential. Okay, I will write it in the notes, but for now, just look into the diagram.
PAUL: Then the, next one, so there is a very specific pattern. Okay, so right now, if you look into this image, now, retrieve and read.
PAUL: Now, this is the pattern which is being followed by Nebran, okay?
PAUL: A retrieve, it means that you have to do the retrieval process to get the context. Okay, and then comes your final answer, which is referred to as basically the read operation.
PAUL: Okay? The final answer or the solution that you'll be getting from the LLM. So that's why this is a RR pattern that we see with respect to neighbor. Okay, first you get the context, okay, then only you can get the response.
PAUL: At any point of time, you will see that read, read, read will come at the last, which is basically the final response from the LLM that is referred to as basically the read operation.
PAUL: Thank you.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Okay, so this particular pattern is referred to as, remember, RR pattern. Okay, referred to as retrieve-read pattern.
PAUL: Because going forward, these patterns will change a lot.
PAUL: Then, after this, okay, so here, if you look, do you think that any type of optimization that can be done?
PAUL: Because in the next advanced rack, only two blocks had been added. Rest of the architecture is exactly the same.
PAUL: Because here, if you, know about, like, more concepts, like query optimization, okay, like, you can see query expansion very specifically, re-ranking, summary fusion.
PAUL: There are no such things. So, like, once you know what is advanced track, then you will know the limitations of NEBRAG, as simple as that.
PAUL: So, can we proceed ahead with advanced drag? Because in advanced drag, there are only two blocks that have been added. So, these two blocks has few functionalities. So, we'll be talking about these functionalities. Please let me know. Can we move to advanced rag?
PAUL: What exactly does read mean? Read means, basically, the response from the LLM. That is your final answer. That is the read, okay?
PAUL: Alright, so, now let's focus on this one, because there are two tasks, okay? So, let me just take a screenshot of this one, and I will add it.
PAUL: In the notes, let's get back.
PAUL: Because query rerouting and few other things are there.
PAUL: Bookstop, I think it's here.
PAUL: Okay, so the… advanced to rank.
PAUL: So, whenever you are doing a POC, always start with a NAVRAG.
PAUL: directly don't start working with an advanced rack. This is very, very important. I have seen people directly start working with something advanced, but always focus on the NAVRAC version, okay, and then the advanced rack version.
PAUL: So, here, if you look into, there are two blocks. So, one block is this, the pre-retrieval and the post-retrieval, okay? So, two new components that comes.
PAUL: So, the first one… In the pre-retrieval part.
PAUL: It means that before you invoke your retriever to find the top K chance, okay, before that, you will be doing this task.
PAUL: Okay, so the first one is, the query rerouting.
PAUL: Okay, it's routing first, later on, reroutes will come.
PAUL: The second one, okay, the rewriting.
PAUL: And the third one that you have is expansion.
PAUL: Okay? So, what is routing in simple terms, guys?
PAUL: Routing means directing to some type of source, I can say.
PAUL: Yes? Simple terms, directing.
PAUL: Too?
PAUL: data sources.
PAUL: Nikki?
PAUL: Now, let's try to understand query routing, okay, in simple terms.
PAUL: So, just think, okay, so…
PAUL: you have your two types of memory, as I have told you very specifically, okay?
PAUL: your parametric.
PAUL: Okay, and your non-parametric.
PAUL: The idea is that Okay, you should do a retrieval task when it is required.
PAUL: It is not that every time you invoke the retriever.
PAUL: Okay, so if you invoke the retriever, it comes under the non-parametric task. So, probably, if you have asked a question, I can see that the LLM might know, yes or no. Tell me.
PAUL: This is your LLM, your parametric memory. So, if somebody asks a question, okay, and you feel that the LLM knows it, do you think that you need to do a retrieval task?
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, that's why. It means that there has to be some type of decision-making. Okay, so based on this, like.
PAUL: I will be talking about research papers are also there, which, very specifically, a decision logic is there. That, okay, I don't have this information, then only I will do the retrieval task.
PAUL: If I have the information, then I know that, okay, the LLM knows the answer.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why this comes. So that's why this query rerouting, it saves your answer, so somewhere around in milliseconds, but yes, I will say that time will be saved.
PAUL: Okay? So that's why I feel that, like, query routing is a good
PAUL: Like, everybody should do it. If the LLM doesn't know, then only your retrieval should be activated.
PAUL: If LLM answer is not up-to-date, okay?
PAUL: Now, those things can happen, okay? Like, probably you might feel that it is giving an outdated answer. Okay, then through evaluations, you have to reject that answer, okay, and then you will be getting a new answer. Okay, so that's why. So those types of things can happen, but majorly, the idea is that
PAUL: the LLM has been trained on huge amount of data. So, out of 10 questions, I can say that the LLM might know at least one. So, at least for one also, okay, it's a very good thing. The idea is that once you start the retrieval process, that takes time. It's just like a bottleneck you can think about.
PAUL: Because once you bring the retrieval process, then what will be the top, K chunks?
PAUL: That becomes the context with the prompt, okay? It's a bottleneck. So if you don't really need to activate the retriever, okay, then it's pretty much direct, LLM, okay, so that's right.
PAUL: I'm not telling in every use case it will be applicable, but I can say that out of 100 queries, probably at least in one query also, it might save time.
PAUL: I hope you get that particular point.
PAUL: In native architecture, we do not do query routing.
PAUL: Then comes query rewriting. Okay, it means reformulate.
PAUL: Reformulate, or simply rephrase.
PAUL: the same question. The idea is that the answer will be same, but the question can be rephrased. It means that words can be changed grammatically, but the semantic meaning is
PAUL: I can say it is basically the same, okay? So, like, rewriting the question, like, what is my name? Okay? So, similarly, you can think about, like, what is the capital of Paris?
PAUL: Okay, what is the capital of France? The same question.
PAUL: If you try to rephrase it in some other way.
PAUL: Then comes… expansion.
PAUL: Okay. Now, very specifically rewriting when you want to do. When you want, okay, with respect to rewriting.
PAUL: With respect to rewriting, Okay, you want… The response… Okay, 2B… Exactly correct.
PAUL: Okay, then we… it means that question 1…
PAUL: Slash question. You can add multiple questions if you feel indebted.
PAUL: Okay. But question 1, the answer will be same, quotient 2 also answer will be same, and question 3 also. So you have to create a,
PAUL: very specifically, test set, okay, where for each of the three questions, you will be having the same answers. Okay, then you can actually do the evaluation for this particular task of rewriting.
PAUL: Okay, so rewriting, I feel that, like, generally, like, not…
PAUL: every time you have to do, sometimes, because for some, scientific task, okay, like, when you feel that, okay, this has to be the exact answer, then only. But otherwise, really, rewriting is not required so much.
PAUL: But routing is very important. Then comes expansion. How many of you know about decomposition?
PAUL: The term decomposition.
PAUL: Turesh is asking how one can take the decision. You have to take the decision in your architecture, whether you want routing, whether you want rewriting, whether you want your expansion.
PAUL: Okay, so all these components, guys, needs to be taken care of. It's not necessary, everybody will follow this architecture.
PAUL: This is a standard architecture.
PAUL: On top of that, when you try to build your own solution, you will be doing a customization. It's not copy and paste. It's not copy and paste, guys.
PAUL: You might take 90% of it and 10% your custom solution, whatever that you want to bring based on your own data, certain things will be there.
PAUL: Okay, so it's not. But this is a standard.
PAUL: That's why.
PAUL: Like, you can use few components from here, and few components from there.
PAUL: Tokay never chunking doesn't come under neither advanced track. That is a chunking mechanism to watch.
PAUL: All right. Now, coming to expansion. Expansion… Like, adding related terms.
PAUL: Okay, so when this happens, okay, now this happens very specifically, like query expansion, when you feel that the question which is being asked is not clear. Okay, so, unclear question.
PAUL: Okay, so just think about somebody has asked a query only in one word.
PAUL: Okay, it means that to get the context, even if you want to invoke the retriever, you need to have a specific amount of context. So, generally, like, it is suggested that, like, one word, you can do a vector search, it's not a big deal. But the idea is that it's a good system where at least you need to pass four words.
PAUL: Generally, I pay for, like, at least having four words gives
PAUL: a better, like, context fetching, okay? Otherwise, it becomes a problem. The content that needs to be fetched from your vector TV. Okay, so just in one mode, it becomes very, like, nave operation.
PAUL: Okay, if somebody just write DA. So, do you really think that the
PAUL: it is a meaningful thing that you are looking for. Okay, if somebody write off 2, okay, the idea is that you need more and more context at that particular point of time. You can ask, like, query expansion can be done through LLMs also?
PAUL: Okay, it means that probably I just… the… probably after that few things that can be suggested by them.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why these are all pre-retrieval techniques. Why pre-retrieval is done? So that your retrieval becomes better.
PAUL: Okay, and why we want to make… why we want to make our retrieval better? The idea is to get better context from the vector TV.
PAUL: So that's why these are the operations, very specifically. Now, generally, I use query routing. Expansion is an implementation, much more, because really, we don't know what the user can write. Okay, so generally, when one word is passed, okay, we can add…
PAUL: or we can pass it to the LLM directly to get that, how we can… so there are specific conditions that we write in our programs. If there is only a one-word input, okay, you can fetch it from the vector TB, but really, it has to be something meaningful.
PAUL: So that's why this pre… I can say your pre-retrieval steps. The idea is your pre-retrieval will help you to get better context. That is the only purpose.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: this part?
PAUL: Who will implement pre-retrival? Who will implement… Now, people are asking, who will do, who will do, everything you have to do. Nobody will do it for you.
PAUL: Okay? Yes, it can be cleaning also. Sometimes, we also clean stop words. If you know in NLP, what are stop words?
PAUL: Yes, Viraj, query gets converted into a embedding, exactly correct.
PAUL: Okay, so let me take some questions. It's a 10.30.
PAUL: Then only I will start. Yes, it's 10.37, okay? So let me take some questions, okay? I can give you a 10 minutes break, okay, because I need to interact with few people. Because most of the questions are pretty much generic. It means that I feel that
PAUL: Little bit, if you guys have the NLP knowledge, okay, so it will be good. So I will just stop sharing this one, okay? And a few questions I can take from the chair.
PAUL: So…
PAUL: Alright, so you can let me know in the chat that, yes, I want to ask a question, so I will unmute you.
PAUL: Rajat Khanna, okay, Rajat is asking…
PAUL: Okay, well, guys, fine, fine. More than 50 people up to it, I can't take 50 questions.
PAUL: Yeah, it.
Rajat Khanna: Yeah, I have, one question. So, the first question is related to, query and, prompt. So, once, like, we, ask a question to a LLM, like ChatGPT, okay? So, it goes as a, first, as a query, means from prompt, the query is being driven, and then, when, when the frozen LLM…
PAUL: From the prompt queries driven? No, this is incorrect.
Rajat Khanna: Okay.
PAUL: See, query is just the question that you are asking.
PAUL: Behind the scenes that prompt is going. Internally, you also don't know if, like, OpenAI has used very specific dynamic prompts that you don't know about. You are just passing your query to the system.
Rajat Khanna: No, so if I ask, like, who won, the Bihar election today, okay, so I have just given a question to a LLM, okay? Now, it needs to… it needs to answer, those things. So, it will be a query, or it will be a prompt, my question is.
PAUL: ready.
Rajat Khanna: Okay.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, and…
PAUL: Anything that you ask to write to LLM, it is always a query.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, so then, prompt engineering comes in, like, whenever we are asking,
PAUL: Now, in the prompt, it will say that, okay, the result of the VR elections, I need it in CSV format, markdown format, to a structured output, okay? In that way, if you want to structure it, it means that the LLM, the response from the LLM already came. Now, that response, you want to manipulate to a certain structure very specifically.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, so in Phil, you can provide.
PAUL: some examples also there, like, few short…
Rajat Khanna: Okay, okay, so for example, I asked for a particular programming question, and then those are not correct, and I'm just changing, like, I don't want this type of output, I want to fine-tune with this type of output, so that.
PAUL: Amy?
Rajat Khanna: B-O.
PAUL: Probably, yes. In the prompt, you can provide examples, like this format, this format, this format. Then the LLM knows that, okay, you are looking very specifically for this format.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, okay, thank you, got it. And the other question… But generally.
PAUL: for coding questions, we don't pass it in the prompt. You can simply say, like, Python 3.12, okay.
Rajat Khanna: or those standards that needs to be followed. I was just understanding the query and the prompt difference.
PAUL: Okay, legend.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, and the next question is, so, you are talking about pre-training. So, pre-training happens when we are creating a LLM. For example, we have a LLM, that is being created.
Rajat Khanna: So if we want to change something in the LLM, or might be changing what we have created a LLM, and we want to 50%, like, we want to change, so it will be a pre-training, it will be known as a pre-training, or it.
PAUL: No, no, no, no. Once the model is trained, it is called pre-trained base or foundational modeling. Now, if you want to change something in the model, that will be a fine-tuning task.
Rajat Khanna: Okay.
Rajat Khanna: Okay, yeah, thank you. That's the two-person point. Thank you very much.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, so let me just, let's go with Sai Rahul. Sai Rahul, yeah, Sai Rahul is here.
PAUL: And Rithvesh… Okay, because there's a few questions only I can take now.
sai rahul: Hey, hi, Pug.
PAUL: Yeah, go ahead.
sai rahul: So, if you see in the previous class as well, right, in the previous class notes as well, you have written that re-ranking as a part of the overall simple RAG architecture that you were…
PAUL: No, no, no, see, that's an optional thing I told in class. That's why there will be a star mark.
sai rahul: Yeah, yeah. So, is it part of, like, advanced track, or would re-ranking be also part of the simple name rank?
PAUL: Because advanced rag only. Generally, when I'm trying to building a rag, re-ranking… the idea is, once…
PAUL: you are getting good responses from your neighbor ag, then you switch to advanced rag. That is an optimization that you are doing. Then you will move to the next architecture. It's not like in one shot you try to do everything.
PAUL: It's part of Admaster, okay?
sai rahul: Got it. Thank you.
PAUL: That which…
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yeah. Hi, Pon. So, basically, I have two questions. Number one, in the notes side, you have written context plus prompt plus query. And, when I was seeing the PDF, it is written as that we have to first give query, then, context plus query plus prompt.
PAUL: The idea was to mention three things. I didn't mention that order. Order really doesn't matter, because if you do, like…
PAUL: Aha, like, 1 plus 2 plus 3, or 3 plus 2 plus 1s.
PAUL: Okay, because at the end of the day, the idea is that all those three information are getting to the LL. The sequence doesn't matter.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, the second question is that you said about the query routing. Now, the thing is that how… means if I have passed the query, how would the LLM know that… how would we know, actually, that the LLM has the correct information or not?
PAUL: I would re…
Ritvij Maheshwari: Yup.
PAUL: That you have to do, probably through prompts, and prompts you might write that. If you feel that you don't know directly, say, no, okay, now this is where the RAG architectures will come into the picture.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, got it, yeah, thanks, that's.
PAUL: Okay, it means that some type of, yes, an evaluation, or probably, like, see, simply, like, if nothing, that the world's most simplest evaluation, use a different LLM.
PAUL: Okay, to do the evaluation. Probably, if you are working with ChatGPT, use the Gemini model to do the evaluation. That is, like, LLM as a judge concept. Later on, I'll be discussing, but that is the easiest way.
Ritvij Maheshwari: You have asked that if we pass 100 questions and it gives the correct response of one question, means that the user has to verify this, that,
PAUL: No, no, nothing user will verify. The idea was that, I really don't know. The user might ask any question. So I told that at least there will be a 1% probability that the LLM might know the correct answer. And 99% of the time, it's going to the rack. Okay, that can be for sure.
PAUL: Okay, but according to research, we have seen that, okay, more than 30% of the time, the LLM knows the answer. Okay, and 70% of the time, it doesn't.
PAUL: So, that's why. That's why I've taken just a bare minimum 1%, so that… that, yes, that LLM has been trained on a vast knowledge. So, at least I feel that one… it will be correct. That is that.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, okay, got it, yeah, thanks.
PAUL: Next, how… Amit and Shuresh.
PAUL: Hand is released.
PAUL: Oh, my head is not raised.
PAUL: Alright, ahmed, Ahmed, Ahmed.
PAUL: Myth also hadn't not raised.
PAUL: Let's, people, please raise your hand also, it's not like you have written in the chat.
PAUL: Let's go with Abhijit Proshti.
PAUL: Don't worry, I know the time, so… IQ will start from 10.50.
PAUL: A widget?
PAUL: Okay, Abhijay, no persons that look like Lakshmi, I can see a Lakshmi.
PAUL: I have a question you have written.
PAUL: Sanket Maheshwari. Sanket, Sanket, yeah, Sanket also I haven't…
Sanket Maheshwari: Yeah, hey, Paul.
PAUL: Do you have some books?
Sanket Maheshwari: Just a quick question, regarding the rewriting and the expansion. So, don't you think the rewriting and expansion are almost
Sanket Maheshwari: Similar. We are trying to do this procedure.
PAUL: No, no, no, see, expansion you do when you have less information. The idea is to add more related terms.
Sanket Maheshwari: Okay.
PAUL: In rewriting, you have the same set of words, same meaning. You just try to rephrase it in some other way, so that the context remains exactly the same. In query expansion, there is lesser context, so you add more related terms.
Sanket Maheshwari: Oh, oh, okay.
PAUL: Got it? Clear?
Sanket Maheshwari: Yeah, yeah, thank you.
PAUL: Okay, next.
PAUL: Hmm, anybody else?
PAUL: Sahil is asking, sir, query rerouting means… query rerouting means that whether you want to very specifically invoke the parametric memory or the non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Amit, Amit, Amit, you have raised your hand just to it.
PAUL: I could not see. Anybody else? Yes, Mahajan, again. Okay, yes, Mahajan, I can see.
PAUL: Okay, after this… SLM has a RAG. SLM has a rag, really, this question.
PAUL: is incorrect.
PAUL: SLM has a rack.
PAUL: Why do we freeze LLM after It to get the prompt.
PAUL: The LLM is always frozen.
PAUL: Okay, Nigel, Narula.
PAUL: Please go ahead.
PAUL: That's Mahan?
smahajan: Yeah. So, hi, Paul.
smahajan: So, I have query, I have question, like, we're talking about pre-retrieval methods. So, in your experience, how efficient are they? Like, do they really help in improving the answers?
PAUL: Yes, there is a very specific research paper for this.
PAUL: You have to really decide, because at the end of the day.
PAUL: In every solution you are building for a client, there is a response time.
PAUL: Okay, now, really, how you have to optimize that response time? So, yes, pre-reterable plays a role.
PAUL: I cannot say very crucial and a major role, but at least a small role, because really, you can save time if you don't want to evoke the retrieval process. Once it goes through the retrieval process, you can easily take around, like.
PAUL: 20 seconds to 30 seconds, it depends upon what type of embedding model and LLM that you are using, but that time might go to, like, 30-40 seconds or so.
PAUL: If you are using complex models and, like, the best embedding. So, if you can totally ignore that retrieval part, and if you are confident that, yes, the LLM moves this particular information to, like, some type of evaluation criteria, then it becomes much easier.
smahajan: Okay, and next question is about query rewriting. So I couldn't get, like, if I am using this query rewriting, and, I mean, there is a question, will I…
smahajan: rewrite the question and send both, like, the rewrites and the query together to the LLM, or…
smahajan: this one.
PAUL: Nothing to the LLM.
PAUL: Generally, what happens, you do it internal.
PAUL: the external user doesn't lose. So, for example, if you are doing the implementation, for the same question, you can create, like, two separate
PAUL: Similar meaning samples, or rephrased version, in simple terms. Then, you will be looking into the output of those three, and you will see that, okay, more than 70%, you have set a threshold, more than 70% or 80% is matching, you know that this is correct, simply through the answers.
smahajan: Okay, okay, okay, okay. Okay, so, I mean, I'll be deciding before posting the answers to the user.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, likely.
smahajan: Okay, okay. And is there any library to rewrite the queries?
PAUL: simple. This is simple Pythonic implementation, not a big deal.
PAUL: Okay.
smahajan: Yeah, that's.
PAUL: Because everything is custom function. It's not so much directly, I don't think Inuity is providing this. Simple logic, like in two code cells. When I'll be showing you the implementation, it will be much more clear, okay?
smahajan: Okay, sure, thanks.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Alright, guys, it's 10.50, okay? Just give me 5 minutes, okay, then we will start, okay?
PAUL: Because already I've taken a few questions, others I'll be taking, don't worry.
PAUL: Hmm… desktop, I think this is very seamlessly go.
PAUL: Take me all of 5 minutes. Just wait in 5 minutes, I'll be back.
PAUL: Sorry, guys.
PAUL: All right, guys, so let's get back to our discussion.
PAUL: Okay, we have 30 seconds, fine. Can retrieval take, both parametric? Yes, by default, Ariane, it's both always, okay?
PAUL: Then you can configure, based on intercession logic, that whether to go to parametric or to non-parametric.
PAUL: Kapil Gupta asking how important, will be understanding reinforcement learning along with LLM.
PAUL: Reward-based systems are actually good, okay, but really, in RAG or agentic RAG, we haven't seen those systems. Later on, probably in future research, we might see, but for now. Yes, Salmana, I'm getting.
PAUL: Creating a RAC application is like creating fine-tuned model, no.
PAUL: you have to think about the weights and biases. If you're not changing the weights and biases, I cannot, say that,
PAUL: you are actually changing the main model. In the RAG, you are provided just external data sources.
PAUL: Alright, so… Let me start sharing…
PAUL: Will we do stemming? Stemming, I prefer lematization much more, Anirud Pawan.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Alright, so, question…
PAUL: All right. So, routing, simply in terms of routing, so whether you want to activate the retriever or the LLM, you have to take that decision.
PAUL: Then comes rewriting. Okay, so how many of you know the meaning of rephrase? Like, anybody has used something like quintBot?
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: So, it gives you, Paraphasing.
PAUL: Okay, not used, it's fine, but, the core idea, paraphraser, okay? So, for example, if I search here…
PAUL: Okay, so… If I copy this sentence very specifically, and I paste it here.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And if I do a paraphrase here…
PAUL: Okay, now if you just try to, look into… Both dancers. Okay, so…
PAUL: Okay, so here, like, Wikipedia is a free, created and edited by volunteers around the world, the Wikipedia Foundation holds Wikipedia, and it is maintained and generated by volunteers worldwide. So, the core context and the meaning always remains the same after a rephasing operation.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I told the, word very specifically, like, rephrase or reformulate, okay? So this is a simple example that you can think.
PAUL: Hit?
PAUL: Finally, that comes, okay, which is a query expansion. It means that
PAUL: to do a better context fetching operation, but you have just very less words at any point of time, then you will try to add much more related, I can say, terms or words in simple terms.
PAUL: Sir, best use for avoiding plagiarism, yes, correct. That's why people have built a lot of rephrasing tools. Okay, now let's get back to our notes.
PAUL: Okay, now, the pre-retrieval things we have already discussed, okay? So, with respect to pre-retrieval.
PAUL: I don't know why this line is coming.
PAUL: Alright. Now, with respect to post-retrable, now everybody focus on the post part.
PAUL: In the post part, three things are written. One is this re-rank.
PAUL: Then comes Summary, and then comes Fusion, okay? R-rank, summary, and Fusion. Very, very important task. I feel that if you are building a good
PAUL: rag system, okay, this, should have these three functions, okay? So let's try to understand the re-rank, okay, and then summary and fusion.
PAUL: So, with respect to post-retrable.
PAUL: So, in simple terms, what is the meaning of post-retribill? I can say that you have the top K chance.
PAUL: Now, on these top key chunks, you want to apply some type of operation.
PAUL: Okay, so some type of operation. Okay, that… it means that the similarity search operation, or the semantic search operation, has already taken place. And from there, you've got the top keychards.
PAUL: It's a page underline. No, it's not an end line. Let me just stop sharing, even I am feeling…
PAUL: Okay, white is coming.
PAUL: Okay, now it's gone, yeah. Fine.
PAUL: Now, so in the first one that you have is re-rank.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Now, re-rank simply means that you want to perform a reorder operation, okay, by relevance.
PAUL: reorder.
PAUL: by relevance.
PAUL: Okay? So generally, there are re-ranking models, okay?
PAUL: Who does it for you?
PAUL: re-ranking models, which are available in Hugging Face.
PAUL: I'll be showing you them, okay? So, based on relevance, it will try to
PAUL: Basically, reorder. It means that, if you have the top K chunk, so let's take K as top 10 chunk.
PAUL: Okay? So, like, your chunk 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, okay? So, similarly, you got. Later on, after re-ranking, it can… it is possible that, okay, your chunk 3 came, okay, then 4 came, then 1 came, then 2. Okay, a complete reordering that we tried to do.
PAUL: Okay, so based on the user query, okay, from the user query, you will always get the relevance, exactly what is the end user looking for, and based on that. So, there are re-ranking models which are available directly. These re-ranking models are completely open source, and paid models are also available.
PAUL: Okay? So…
PAUL: top K. K is a parameter. K can be anything. It can be 5, it can be 10, so it's a hyperparameter in simple terms. When you do the… when you invoke the retrieval, from the vector databases, it will get the top K charts.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: The term is called re-ranking, because first you get the top K chance. They have a specific rank. Then again, on top of that, again, you do a rank operation. So that's why the term re-ranking comes.
PAUL: Because the first ranking is based on the scores, the similarity score. Okay, and then you do the ranking based on the relevance. Okay? So because of that, the term re-ranking, it means that second time the rank has been done.
PAUL: All right. Now, there are a lot of models that I'll be talking about during the implementation, but this is the main purpose. Okay, the idea is that, okay, you try to sort out the chunks in a better way, so that they will…
PAUL: Have better relevance at any point of time.
PAUL: So then comes your summary.
PAUL: Summary means, in simple terms, compression.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is to compress something that is referred to as someone.
PAUL: Okay, so… and I can say that compress… the retripped… content.
PAUL: Okay? Now, compress the retrade content, okay? The idea is to make it shorter. Okay, now, one simple example I'm just giving you, just try to understand. Okay, probably in your chunk.
PAUL: One, you have 128, okay, in your junk.
PAUL: This is 1, this is 2, again, you have 128. And then there is a sudden drop, okay, probably in your chunk 3.
PAUL: Okay, where it has only 32.
PAUL: At that particular point of time, okay, so we try to compress the entire thing into a single chunk.
PAUL: Okay? So, the idea is that it won't be a chunk anymore, rather than it will be a summarized, retrieved content, okay? So, which is referred to as the summarized content.
PAUL: retripped content.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Generally, this happens, okay, we prefer, compression, okay, so sometimes compression is good, okay, and sometimes it is bad. Why?
PAUL: Whenever you are doing a summarization operation.
PAUL: During a summarization operation, I can say that there is some amount of info loss. Okay, info loss will be there, always understand.
PAUL: Info loss will be there.
PAUL: Okay, probably, like, this is a dynamic number, so really I can't say exactly what is the proportion of amount of information that we are losing, but there will be some type of information loss.
PAUL: I think everybody agrees, if you're doing a summarization operation, okay, of a research paper, and you get the entire 20 research papers in just 2 pages. Okay, I can say that yes, a lot of information that has been removed.
PAUL: Okay, so generally what we try to do here… okay, so this… you have to think about, this is not a concatenation operation.
PAUL: Don't think about, I'm doing a concatenation operation of chunk 1, chunk 2, and chunk 3. Okay, this is not a concatenation operation.
PAUL: Okay, so during summarization.
PAUL: If some things which are, okay, like, repeated, so there can be an information which is same in chunk 1, same in chunk 2, and same in chunk 3. So, in the summarized version, that same information will be removed, like, 3 times, and it will be only one time.
PAUL: Okay, so this is just an example I'm giving. So it becomes a much more complex, compressed, retrieved, okay, content. So, like, this actually helps you in maintaining why it is good.
PAUL: Okay, at the end of the day, you have to understand why.
PAUL: Maintaining.
PAUL: shorter, context… window… Faith.
PAUL: This is very, very important, because every LLM has a context size.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, you have to maintain the context size. So, whichever LLM you are working with. So, for example, if I give an example with, like, Claude, okay, in the 4.5 version, it has a 2 million, okay? So that's why, like, 2 million tokens. So, you know that there is a certain limit.
PAUL: Okay, and the idea is to increase this limit, so that's why there is a research currently going on, but the actual implementation, they have not shown it, even in the
PAUL: In your forum, somebody asked about that. Okay, so yes, the idea is to increase the context size, but right now, we have the limitation. Probably in the next 1 or 2 years, you can increase the contact sign at least by, I can say, 3 times, 4 times.
PAUL: Okay? And you have to understand, if your context size increases.
PAUL: If it increases, your response time decreases.
PAUL: Your response time decreases.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I feel that, summarized, you should perform always a summarized operation. But again, to generate this summary takes some time. Again, in some milliseconds that you'll be getting.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why. If everything, see, if context size increases, your token consumption increases.
PAUL: A lot of things. If your token consumption increases, Then… price increases.
PAUL: Okay, so a lot of things. So, that's why I feel that a summarized version is a really good operation. It helps you to save money, okay, and then to get faster responses also.
PAUL: So that's why, overall, a very good operation. Okay, and even, like, in our practical implementations also, we'll be doing this.
PAUL: Yes, response time should be more, response time also increases, exactly. Cost also increases, because of much more token consumption.
PAUL: She was telling accuracy of RAG is 100%. It depends upon the rack system that you are building.
PAUL: Huh?
PAUL: Alright, now I will finally come to the part with respect to fusion.
PAUL: So, what is the meaning of fusion, guys?
PAUL: Yes? Simply, what is the meaning of fusion in English?
PAUL: like, to combine multiple things, I can say.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: So, a fusion between two things.
PAUL: what have I written? Just wait.
PAUL: If the context size increases, the response time decreases, token consumption increases, and the price increases.
PAUL: Okay, okay, okay, okay, okay, sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry, sorry, I have written decrease here.
PAUL: Okay, yeah, yeah, yeah, sorry.
PAUL: My mistake, my mistake, this one. Yeah, it will be increased.
PAUL: Everything increases, actually. That's why. Always remember that. This also increase.
PAUL: And this also, okay? Yes. Okay, so it's not decreased, I have written it wrong, okay, it's increased. Alright, now, back to Fusion.
PAUL: So, with respect to fusion.
PAUL: In, simple terms, the idea is to combine multiple type of sources, okay? So,
PAUL: Now, what type of sources combine?
PAUL: information.
PAUL: both this.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that you should have multiple sources, it's not only about that. Okay, now, one simple example.
PAUL: With respect to RAG, okay, so your external data sources that you have.
PAUL: what they can be, okay? It can be any type of files that you are processing, okay? Then, other than files, it can be APIs.
PAUL: You can use APIs also to make some type of API call, and from there you fetch the information. Or probably some type of tool calling operation.
PAUL: Okay? Or it can be some type of MCP server.
PAUL: Okay, so so many things comes into the picture.
PAUL: So, that's why, because till now, majorly, we are talking about external data sources, but these are all type of external, like, through tool calling, you can make a data source. Like, it is not always necessary that tool calling refers to a data source.
PAUL: But yes, you can configure your tool calling through APIs. So that's why I've kept all the possible combination of external sources.
PAUL: Through which you can get some type of information.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that more information you get, okay, so somehow the context will be better. But always remember, if you, try to make your context window size bigger, okay, the operation will be much more costlier, but your result will be much more accurate.
PAUL: Because at the end of the day, we want much more accurate answers, so to make our answers much more accurate.
PAUL: There is a trade-off, okay, with respect to that balance you have to maintain, okay, based on the number of tokens, okay, because if you want to get more context at any point of time, yes, the number of tokens will be high.
PAUL: And based on that, the costing for that particular LLM will also go. But you get better answers.
PAUL: So, this particular fusion actually helps us, and later on in our implementation, also in LangChain, there are a lot of other tools that we can integrate with our
PAUL: Like, a simple rag, I can say, or our knee rag. Okay, so that we'll be adding. Do we have a man-in-the-middle problem in the large corners?
PAUL: No, there won't be such problems.
PAUL: No.
PAUL: Okay, so what is Fusion? The Fusion is getting information sources, or multiple information sources. It can be through files, okay, through your local files, it can be through APIs, it can be through some type of tool calling, or it can be through MCP servers. Okay, the idea is to fetch some information.
PAUL: How the, ordering is decided, it builds on the relevance.
PAUL: ratio. Okay, and the relevance, you can find it from the user query. So, based on that, the re-ranking model does it.
PAUL: Fusion? Yes, we use external sources, so we use, very specifically, APIs, In Linux?
PAUL: and MCP servers. Okay, files are there, for sure, but we don't use tool calling.
PAUL: Okay, rather than, we have embedded the tool calling through an API. Okay, so that's why. These three are the main ones that I feel that you should have, because going forward, at any point of time, if you want to give a web search capability, okay, web search capability, it means that, a simple example, a Google
PAUL: Google search.
PAUL: Okay, a Google search tool that you want to add to your rack.
PAUL: Then, can I say that, yes.
PAUL: Okay, my rag can respond to all the latest event, yes or no? Please let me know this.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, a simpler Google search tool. Similarly, it can be this Google search, it can be an API from Google directly.
PAUL: Okay? Or probably, some type of MCP server. Okay, so that's why, like, these are all the… there are more options, guys. Just now, I'm just discussing this four. Okay, now the sources can be, like, different type of databases than others, but for now, I'm just keeping it general.
PAUL: So, this is fusion. Fusion means more data sources, more context, and more accurate answer that you are looking for.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, now this part is done. Okay, and finally, rest of the architecture of advanced drag is exactly same of the name rag.
PAUL: Okay, so only this… Component was added, and this component, which we have already discussed.
PAUL: So, right now, I feel that you always start building from NAVRAC, so similarly, we will also do… we will start with NAVRAG, then Advanced RAG, okay? And finally, the final architecture, which is basically the modular RAG, where everything is totally a plug-and-play module.
PAUL: Okay, so is this part clear for advanced rag? Then I will move to the next part, which is the, modular RAG.
PAUL: So let me just get back to the paper now.
PAUL: Why, Fusion?
PAUL: occurs after, retrieval. Okay, Mohit, now this is a good question, like, why fusion occurs after the retrieval? So, sometimes, what happens, see?
PAUL: Look into this image.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a post-retrieval task. First of all, see, your contest, and I told you anything after finding the top K chance. Now, it can be that, okay, I invoked my retriever, but really, the answer was not there.
PAUL: Okay, so in that case, you have to probably do some type of external data sources.
PAUL: I hope you get mine, because this is a… Post-retrable technique moinda.
PAUL: Okay, all right. Ravi, can we say Comet Browsers uses perplexity? Is it a RAG system with external? No, there are other things also, okay, with respect to the browser. Fusion is, more of everything that will come with a price tag, and how to optimize the cost, yes. That is a trade-off that you need to maintain it.
PAUL: Yes, David.
PAUL: Yep.
PAUL: What is the sequence of all post-retival actions? There is no sequence, it totally depends upon you, but yes, I always prefer re-ranking first. Okay, once, re-ranking is done, then summarize is an optional thing, like, if you want, you can do it.
PAUL: Because sometimes it's helpful, but summarization always comes with the information laws that you have to understand. So if you are ready for that, okay.
PAUL: You can do it.
PAUL: Okay, and finally, Fusion is very, very important, because without Fusion, it becomes very, very hard to get the latest events or any type of latest information from the web. So through Fusion, we can actually do it.
PAUL: Can't re-ranking update the top K chunks? No, no, no. See, top K chunks will be fixed. Renking will just reorder them, and nothing more.
PAUL: Yes, I'm…
PAUL: Which one is more important, Advanced RAG or Agentic RAG? Agentic rag is a different thing. Agentic rag, it means that you use a framework, and nothing more.
PAUL: That you have to understand, I'm sure. It's a framework. It means that you are using CreeVI, Langraph, Autos, and those type of agentic frameworks at the end of the day.
PAUL: Yes, it's an optimization process.
PAUL: Everything, that's why. So, these are all optimization. So, this is pre-retrable optimization, and this is post-retrable optimization.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: This is also an optimization step, and this is also an optimization step. One is before the retrieval, one is after the retrieval.
PAUL: Alright, I hope this part is clear, and we can move to the next part.
PAUL: Okay, so if anybody wants to know about
PAUL: like, re-ranking models, okay? I'm just showing you ones that I use a lot.
PAUL: I do.
PAUL: Okay, now, this is a lightweight one. Okay, so as you can see, here, BG Ranker, V2M3, open source. Okay, so this is a good one. It has
PAUL: multiple versions of this, okay, that we can. So, in our implementations, we will be using this. Other than that, there are some paid ones also, like Cohari rank as a…
PAUL: Okay, over, agreed, and…
PAUL: Okay, so this is a, like, paid version, not everything is free. Okay, so, yes, this is also good.
PAUL: Alright, with respect to re-ranking models, also, I have shown.
PAUL: It, total depends upon the size and the parameters journey. You can figure out the lightweight one.
PAUL: Alright, now let's get back to our final one, the modular rank, okay?
PAUL: Now, really the architecture that they have given, okay, the idea is that they have given the major components, and now you have to actually
PAUL: I can say that, you can configure this. They have not configured for you, they have just shown you that, okay, now, this is a plug-and-play component. It means that you can use it, you can skip it, really, it is not so much important, okay? So, the idea is, say, search.
PAUL: Okay, now search, you have to think about.
PAUL: It can be as simple, like, a database search, or a web search. It can be any type of search operation.
PAUL: Okay, then comes routing. Okay, now, as I've told you, query routing is different, and this normal routing is different.
PAUL: Normal routing, you can think about routing through different type of pipelines. Now, pipeline, when I'm talking about, you can think about, like, data ingestion was one, okay, and probably your,
PAUL: Retrieval was one. So, there, it can be different pipelines. The idea is that you can use any component, and you can remove any component. There is no restriction.
PAUL: Then there is the prediction. Okay, so prediction is basically generating hypothetical answers. Okay, and for that, you have a concept. Later on, I'll be talking about that. Okay, ID. Now, this is also a…
PAUL: this particular technique that you have. Okay, now this is also a post-retrable, technique. Okay, so, which is good. It consumes, okay, it takes a little bit of time, but this is really good.
PAUL: Okay, so… Through this also you can do.
PAUL: Okay? Because here, all advanced topics are written. Then comes, rewriting already, we have discussed re-ranking, we have discussed red is the final answer that is coming. So you can see retrieve and red, these are in orange months, very specifically.
PAUL: Okay? And then you have memory, it means that adding some type of memory, external memory it can be, or an internal memory. Then you have your fusion module here, again, completely plug-in module. You can attach it, you can detach it. But if you look, see.
PAUL: in the center, whatever the things are written, okay? They are pretty much the most important one. Like, retrieve, rewrite, read and re-rank. It means that you should always use these.
PAUL: Other than that, like, routing, optional. Okay, now demonstrate.
PAUL: demonstrate, like, is providing examples.
PAUL: the best way of showing you would demonstrate is Okay, DSP paper.
PAUL: Dsps, Stanford NLP. Okay, yeah, Stanford DSP paper.
PAUL: Okay, now… This is a framework also anybody has heard about?
PAUL: Dspy?
PAUL: T-S-P-Y, anybody has heard about?
PAUL: Okay, so, like, very specifically, through multiple examples, you can provide this, okay? So, a few people might have used it in their organization.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, like, yeah, using DSPY, you can actually pass, and you can see right now, like, it's a famous project, so many people are using it also. Okay, so you can… here you can do a lot of, optimizations. It can be with respect to React Agent, Chain of Thoughts, and other stuff.
PAUL: Okay? So, that's why very specifically, like, to perform these type of operations, I can say that, demonstrate. Demonstrate, that's why the best paper, that is, which is based on DSPY. So, here, at every point of time, it gives a demonstration with multiple examples.
PAUL: Okay, so, very, very good, I can say.
PAUL: With respect to implementation.
PAUL: Okay, other than that, there are no other things that… because for memory, okay, I'm just showing you, okay, like, I don't know, previously I've shown you mem0,
PAUL: This is there. Okay, that you can always use a memory layer. Okay, there is something called as memory.
PAUL: Okay, which comes from Gibson AI.
PAUL: Gibson,
PAUL: Okay, so this is another project. So, these type of projects, that can be included with your lab, okay? As you can see, memory and open source SQL native memory engine for AI, okay? So, similarly, like, it can be integrated with Langchain, LLM, and pretty much, you can see right now.
PAUL: Like, in trending. So we know that, yes, these things that can be implemented.
PAUL: So that's why… so here, everything that you have, it's a plug-in-play module. It means that if you want to… if you don't want to use something, simply, like, you can remove that.
PAUL: Okay, because at the end of the day, when you are working in an organization, you have to really decide which component to pick. I cannot say that all the components should be there in your access to.
PAUL: It totally depends upon you and your use case. In your use case, like demonstrate, you might feel that this is of no use to you. You can remove it. But yeah, if you feel that routing, at every point of time, by default, you need to invoke your parametric and your non-parametric memory. Remove routing also.
PAUL: Okay, so it totally depends upon, and through analytics, you get more deeper insights that, okay, how to customize the system going forward in later features, which becomes an incremental process.
PAUL: Okay? So, that's why, like, you have to understand, so these are the main, I can say, plug-and-play modules, which you can easily switch.
PAUL: Other than that, if you look into what are the things which are new, only memory and demonstrate that I feel that which is new here, okay? Other than that, it's pretty much the same stuff.
PAUL: And, I think there is a 2020 paper… Adjust wheat.
PAUL: Why cut up…
PAUL: Okay, so… very specifically with respect to demonstrate, search, and predict, okay? So, there is another paper, like, if you want to really go in depth with respect to the demonstrate, search, predict.
PAUL: Okay, so where actually… what happens? Okay, so here are a few examples which are given. So, it makes your retrieval process somehow better, but again, like, really, I cannot say that it will directly help. So, this paper was there back in 2023, very specifically with respect to fetching better context.
PAUL: But, yes, I feel that it is not always necessary. Okay, so it becomes a plug-and-play module, in simple terms.
PAUL: What can you do in routing?
PAUL: In routing, you have to generally decide, like, which memory you want to invoke. Okay, like, I always prefer to invoke the parametric memory. Okay, if I don't get response from the parametric memory, then only I will invoke the non-parametric memory.
PAUL: Okay, so it totally depends upon the architecture. What is the use of memory? Memory is very, very important, guys.
PAUL: So, I see memory, it means that whenever you are building a full-fledged system, according to your SDLC, for every user, you have to maintain the conversation. No.
PAUL: It can be through Cache, okay, so that's why. So what happens, basically? So, if you remember ChatGPT, okay, it remembers.
PAUL: So, anything that you have asked previous. So, how is that? The idea is that provide the context across different sessions, because when you are building a chat system, there will be multiple sessions. So, across the sessions, if you want to share that context.
PAUL: So, it's very, very important memory. Memory can be short-term memory, it can be long-term memory.
PAUL: Okay, so it totally depends upon your, software, like, your architecture that you are building.
PAUL: Can we search in relational and distributed databases? Yes, you can do that, Christian.
PAUL: For agent, memory, yes. In agent, it's also the same stuff that comes.
PAUL: Why we need such… Why we need such?
PAUL: Because if you want to do any type of web search operation, or any type of external stuff from where you want to get the latest event, so yes, it is important.
PAUL: Now, query routing, that, generally comes here, and, routing is basically, see, actually, when you are building a modular RAG architecture, you will see that a lot of agent-type stuff that comes.
PAUL: So, this routing can be with respect to agents also. Okay, so that's why I told you, here routing, don't think only from the memory perspective, also think from the pipeline perspective.
PAUL: Okay, so for example, if you have 10 agents, okay, now those 10 agents, which agent will communicate with which agent? So, in that way, also, you can define the rules.
PAUL: Okay, so this is a example that has been kept here. So, for example, if you have 10 different agents, now you have to understand how the agent communication is being done, and how you want. So, probably, you want a route
PAUL: through which agent 1 can be called to Agent 5. Then Agent 5 can call to Agent 10. Okay, so in that way, you have to define a routing mechanism.
PAUL: And then, so, like, it totally depends upon your RAG architecture that you are defining. So, it's better to say a pipeline for now. Pipeline is a generic term. The idea is that you can invoke any pipeline.
PAUL: Because of within a pipeline, you can think about there is a function called through which you are communicating between two different agents.
PAUL: Okay, so what was the logic involved when… Okay.
PAUL: MCP will sit in the Fusion part, okay? So somebody's asking, what was the logic behind the, re-ranking?
PAUL: Through user query, we will try to find the relevance, and based on that relevance, okay, we will try to pass it through the re-ranking model to sort out the documents, or reorder the documents, as simple as that.
PAUL: Alright, because going forward, for re-ranking, there will be a separate class for embedding, don't worry about that. Okay, we will go in-depth with respect to practical implementations.
PAUL: How do we demonstrate in basic meaning?
PAUL: Demonstrate means providing examples. It means that whenever you are working with LLMs, okay, you, if you are learning any programming language, you might ask it to provide multiple examples. That is the meaning of demonstrate.
PAUL: Okay, and for demonstration very specifically, that's why I showed you. Like, if you want to go through, like, demonstrate, I don't use it always, but I feel that, yes, this is a framework sometimes which help you. Because, I feel that the alternate of demonstrate is using few-shot prompting.
PAUL: This is a very similar thing. If you are really working with few-shot prompting, okay, the same thing later on, again, I don't want to add it. So, it becomes,
PAUL: sometimes I feel that it's a headache, but a complete framework, as you can see, we released DSP. Now, this is the same framework that I was showing you, okay? So, which is widely used.
PAUL: So, this is much more programming rather than prompting, but prompting also does the same task.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Alright, so let's move ahead.
PAUL: Okay, because there are other things also in the paper that we need to discuss.
PAUL: Demonstrate is not prompting, you have to understand. I use prompting because, at the end of the day, the output…
PAUL: It's pretty much similar. There will be some type of differences, but I feel that, yes, few-shot prompting does that ask.
PAUL: Like, for, anybody who has heard the term prompt?
PAUL: Automation or prompt op… optimization.
PAUL: Very specifically, if you want to make your prompts automatic, everything automatic, it means that
PAUL: And during runtime, it should generate the prompt.
PAUL: At that particular point of time, DSPY is very, very important, because using DSPY, you can actually do those type of stuff, because this is much more of a programming framework, which help you in the automation of prompts.
PAUL: Yeah, so very specifically, I use it for that particular purpose, but yes, okay. So, if you want, later on, we can talk about this, okay? Because this is a post-retrable technique, okay, that will be much more used.
PAUL: Alright guys, now let's complete our paper discussion here. Okay, so we have already gone through the three major architectures. Okay, so based on that, the patterns that comes around. So here, as you can see here, the DHSP paper that has been mentioned. Okay, first of all, like, provide
PAUL: some examples, then comes your search operation, and finally comes your predict. So, can you see here, is there a retriever? Yes or no?
PAUL: Is there a retriever?
PAUL: So, that's why. Because this is an optimization technique. So, really, it doesn't matter with respect to RAC. It is just a small, optional component of RAC.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I'm telling you. Like, DSP cannot do a retrieval.
PAUL: But, once your retrieval task is done, later on you can do the optimization. It just… and, this prediction is written, so these predictions are basically hypothetical embeddings.
PAUL: Okay, so yes, this is an optional thing, but at the end of the day, you have to understand, retrieve and read has to be there if it is a rank.
PAUL: These two operations are the most important one. Here, also, you can see an advanced track. Okay, so there is a rewriting. Rewriting is coming from query rewriting, basically. So, rewrite, retrieve, re-rank, re-rank is coming from your post-retrable technique, and finally comes your read operation. So, this is another pattern.
PAUL: And then finally, the iteration. So, this is a research paper, okay, where you try to evaluate your result, almost. Okay, so first of all, you can see retrieve, read, retrieve, read. Okay, now, very specifically for this particular operation, okay.
PAUL: What happens?
PAUL: If you feel that, at any point of time, the query which has been passed by the user, if it is not
PAUL: So much good. Okay, so probably you can rewrite that, and again, get your answer. Again, if you feel that the answer is not up to the quality, then again, rewrite the question, again, get the answer.
PAUL: So, it becomes an iterative process completely. So, when I will be discussing this paper, I'll be letting you know about these particular patterns.
PAUL: Okay, so for now, like, this part we'll be discussing later on, because this paper is important, inter-redgen. Okay, because there is a continuous loop that keeps on going, okay, and where you define the number of times that it will be looping through.
PAUL: Alright, so let's move to our next part.
PAUL: No, search is not a retriever. Okay, don't think search is not a retriever.
PAUL: Alright, so let's move to the next part.
PAUL: Okay, right now, here you can see methods.
PAUL: So, these are all research paper, guys. Okay, so, like, so many research papers are there. Now, you can simply
PAUL: Okay, look into a few of these ones, as I have told. Okay, so really, a long list of research papers are here, but again, not all of them are necessary.
PAUL: Because these guys have done… these people have done the survey, so in that survey, they have taken different type of data… databases.
PAUL: And they are looking into, like, what type of data that they are retrieving. Okay, now, retrieval, so, like, sometimes we create chunks, it can be sentences, it can be sentence pairs in that way. Augmentation stage, pre-training. Okay, so based on that, you can find different type of papers also.
PAUL: Okay, so a long list of, your rack methods which have been provided.
PAUL: Alright, now… Those are different things, logical routing and semantic routing.
PAUL: Alright, so… external knowledge. Okay, now, this part that comes, okay, with respect to
PAUL: So, can you look into this graph? Okay, because this graph comprises of a lot of things.
PAUL: So, the prompt engineering part. Okay, so the idea is that, what are the things that can be changed at any point of time?
PAUL: So, two things are there, the y-axis, okay, and the x-axis. In Y-axis, you have external knowledge required.
PAUL: Okay, so external knowledge required meals.
PAUL: your external data sources. And if you look into this hive.
PAUL: All the rack components, NAV rack, Advanced RAG, Modular RAG, these are all in high states. Because for RAG, we always require external knowledge, okay?
PAUL: But for prompt engineering, it's low, because really, for prompt engineering, we really don't need those things. It is really of knowing
PAUL: Okay, so that's why, for prompt engineering, okay, so you don't need external data.
PAUL: Okay, the amount of data that you can create, for example, very specific to Fusion, okay, probably you might provide 10 examples, but again, that cannot be compared to an external, knowledge. So that's why the prompt engineering part is low. In the RAG, everything will be towards the higher end.
PAUL: Okay, and external knowledge required, can you say modular RAG? The idea was to include different things, so the amount of data will be higher.
PAUL: So, can I say that if the amount of external knowledge is higher.
PAUL: The cost of the solution will be higher, because I will be getting multiple contexts from different type of data sources.
PAUL: Okay, so…
PAUL: That's why I feel that, like, modular rack consumes the highest amount of data, because it is connected… because of the fusion component, you have to understand, the core component that comes here is basically the fusion. Because of the fusion, okay, and some others.
PAUL: I can say, like, very specifically, if you're using, like, demonstrate, okay.
PAUL: Then also, I can say your token consumption increases.
PAUL: So, because of these type of things, the external knowledge required with respect to rack-based systems, it is always high. Whereas model adaptation, what is the meaning of adaptation, first of all?
PAUL: It means that any type of model that needs to be changed or modified.
PAUL: Okay, so you can see that with respect to model adaptation, okay, fine-tuning is there, because in fine-tuning, you actually change a model.
PAUL: Okay, but with RAG. So, you have to understand model adaption and RAG, they are totally in different directions.
PAUL: Okay?
PAUL: Because here, your external knowledge is not so much required.
PAUL: Okay, so… and, when you are trying to build a fine-tuned model, then again, you need dataset. Okay, because of data set, somewhere the amount of data will be in the medium, so in between low to high.
PAUL: So, I've given there very specifically fine-tuning to somewhere in the medium part, because at least you need a good amount of data to do a fine-tuning operation.
PAUL: So that's why the model adaptation is best with respect to fine-tuning. Okay, but the model adaptation
PAUL: With respect to RAG, it is not required, because we never change the model with respect to
PAUL: So that's why this part is low. And then there are a few advanced techniques right now, if you look into, like, retriever fine-tuning, collaborative fine-tuning, and generator fine-tuning, okay, which is all of the above. It means that combining RAG
PAUL: Plus prompt engineering, plus fine-tuning.
PAUL: Okay, so there is a very specific paper that we'll be talking about, which is referred to as RAG.
PAUL: Very combined RAG with fighting.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why in your course, there is a very specific module of fine-tuning that we'll be talking about, which will be RAG, okay, with respect to your model fine-tuning.
PAUL: So, that is one of the most advanced, I can say. But again, costly operation, for sure, because at the end of the day, it's a model adaptation operation. It means that you change the model weights and biases. So, yes, the training time will be towards higher side.
PAUL: Yeah, so the,
PAUL: I hope everybody understands this and what they are referring, because these are prompt engineering, COT. What is COT? Anybody knows about chain of thoughts, tree of thoughts.
PAUL: Few-shot prompting, standard prompt, okay? So, these are a few prompt engineering concepts that generally comes. If you don't know, probably in a prompt engineering lecture, I'll be talking about these things, okay? But these are just different types of prompts that you have.
PAUL: So, always remember, in RAG,
PAUL: We never change the model. This is very, very important. Now, when we change the model, it becomes a very unique use case, okay, like Raft, where you actually perform a rag-based fine-tuning. Okay, so that is this all about…
PAUL: all of the above approach, okay, where you try to train your retriever. It means that you will be doing the retrieval operation multiple times. Okay, and based on that, it will try to save the weights and prices.
PAUL: Okay, so it's completely recreating a new model on top of some type of foundational model.
PAUL: So, we will always start with this part, where we won't be doing a model adaptation, but probably after the, I think, in the third month or the fourth month, your model adaptation will come with respect to fine-tuning the wrangles.
PAUL: Okay, so I hope this, simple image gives you a rough idea exactly what is going on here.
PAUL: Can we move to the next part now?
PAUL: Okay, alright, now…
PAUL: Okay, so yes, Heidi and other things will come later on, fine. Embedding, adapter.
PAUL: For a fine-tuning adapter is required.
PAUL: LoRa adapter. You have heard about LoRa adapter, Q LoRa adapter?
PAUL: Can we change the LLM once RAG is created?
PAUL: Yes, you can change the LLM, always.
PAUL: LLM is just a component, okay, step by step.
PAUL: Alright guys, now focus on this part. This part is important with respect to your incremental improvement of any type of rack system.
PAUL: Okay, so this part, I feel it's very, very important, and if you are actually building a system, okay. So, yes, you need to do at least iterative approach or an adaptive approach. I do not prefer recursive approach so much. Okay, based on practical implementations, I feel iterative and adaptive does the job.
PAUL: But sometimes recursive is also important, okay?
PAUL: Alright, so let's focus on the first one, okay? Now, these are basically the approaches which are taken to make your retrieval process much more better. So that's by iterative retrieval, the first one that comes. So, these are all retrieval.
PAUL: Like, iterative retrieval, recursive retrieval, adaptive retrieval. All, so 3 types of retrieval that we have.
PAUL: So, the first one that we have, is the provide more context information.
PAUL: So, providing more context information at the end of the day. So, how you can provide more context? Can I say that you can…
PAUL: To do this retrieval step multiple times.
PAUL: And there is a judge, and this judge is basically a separate LLM that you can think about. Okay, who will take that evaluation? So the evaluation is done through an LLM.
PAUL: If this judge feels that, okay, the output that is coming, okay, it is of no use, okay, then again, retrieve, again, generate, again, judge. So, judge will pass the answer, then only you will be getting the final response.
PAUL: So, you have to understand this generated, whatever is coming from the LLM, the generated information, okay? So, that is always being evaluated, and iterate n times. So, you decide what will be the number of N.
PAUL: In simple terms.
PAUL: So I feel that, yes, this process is good.
PAUL: How many of you know about the concept of LLM as a judge?
PAUL: LLM?
PAUL: The judge.
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: LLM as a judge, okay, if you don't know about… there is a concept of LLM as jury.
PAUL: Okay, where you use multiple elements, okay?
PAUL: This concept is also there. Jury, I think everybody understands. Multiple things that comes into the picture, okay. So, you can use a single LLM, which is referred to as judge. Multiple LLMs, which is referred to as jury.
PAUL: Okay, so for evaluation. Generally, like, jury is a costly operation, so I feel that judge does the job for you.
PAUL: And, like, many times, like, many students have asked me, like, for evaluation.
PAUL: Okay, and for evaluation, people always use some other elements. It's not only that one LLM does the job. If you want to do evaluation, okay, you can move to some other LLM. So generally, what I do if I'm doing something in OpenAI,
PAUL: Or probably with Anthropic-based KPIs. Okay, then I probably switch to Gemini.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is to use the top 10 available models, having good context window sizes.
PAUL: to do your, at least, experiments. In that way, you know that, okay, I can re-evaluate my LLM-generated answer at any point of time. So what the judge is doing, it is just evaluating
PAUL: the generated answer.
PAUL: So, very, very important here.
PAUL: If the answer is incorrect, we know that the retrieval process has failed.
PAUL: So, right here, we are not using any external tools. Otherwise, if it fails here, so generally what happens, there is another component where you actually connect
PAUL: this through a different API, and you can fetch information from online. Okay, that is also possible, but right now, this is a… I can say, isolated system, so no other external APIs are connected, but that is also a possibility. So, this iterative process, I will say that, yes, it's a good one.
PAUL: Okay, so… but… What is the main con? Can anybody tell me of this, if something is iterative?
PAUL: what will happen to the end user? The end user will feel that this system is really very, very slow.
PAUL: The first thing is slow. Cost will come later on.
PAUL: Because even if we try to increase the money here, okay, or if we try to spend more money, then also we know that getting the response will be a problem.
PAUL: Because at any point of time, whenever you are using a judge component, judge or jury component, you have to understand that, okay? So, yes, there will be a problem with respect to the response time. It means that probably
PAUL: 30 to 40 milliseconds that can be added on top of your original response. Maybe more, because this end times iteration that you decide, whether 5 times, 7 times, you always select an odd number.
PAUL: Okay, so based on that, it totally makes the system slow. So I feel that somehow there is a bottleneck.
PAUL: You have to understand, accuracy always comes with a trade-off.
PAUL: If you're looking for good answers, accurate answers, so this is basically the trade-off that you have with respect to a rag system.
PAUL: Alright, now.
PAUL: With respect to this process, so the first is the user will ask the query, then retrieve. What it will retrieve, the top K chance. After getting the top K chance, it will finally generate the answer. The generated answer will be, checked by some type of judge. Okay, so here…
PAUL: the judge will evaluate, okay, and now, decision, like the max number of times, whether it can be 10 times, so there is… n is basically a threshold number that you do select. Okay, if no, iterate. If yes, simply will be getting the response.
PAUL: We never modify the query. We only change the retrieval.
PAUL: You have to understand, guys, we don't modify the query.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: The original query of the user remains the same, but you can add an optimization, like a query rerouting, those things that can be done. But the original query will be the same at the end, okay? Behind the scenes, if you are changing it, that is the optimization that you are doing.
PAUL: Okay, so this is good. So, sometimes what happens, so generally it is called an incremental learning process, because in the first retrieval, yes, something that might be left, probably second time that it might have fished.
PAUL: But, I feel that this is…
PAUL: not up to the month, because adaptive is the best one that we can do, but iterative, yes, people have used, so it's good.
PAUL: So, here you can see in Figure 5, in addition to the most common ones, retrieval rag also includes 3 types of retrieval augmentation process. Okay, so the iterative retrieval involves alternating between the retrieval and the generation process, alternating because multiple times the…
PAUL: Retrable will be invoked, so based on that, yes, multiple times a generation will come, allowing for richer and more targeted context from the knowledge base at each step.
PAUL: Then the middle one is recursive, so this one I feel that. Recursive is good, but again, like, for complex queries, at any point of time, if you feel that, the simple concept of query decomposition. It means that you are passing a query of 10 sentences.
PAUL: So, do you think that in one shot I can get all the context from the vector TV?
PAUL: your retrieval cannot do it. Then, probably, what it will do, okay, he will try to break it into multiple sentences, and then you will try to fetch it. So, whatever the context that you are getting, so you will keep it, again, on top of that, you will concatenate the new context. So, simple, I can say.
PAUL: context concatenation operation with the query decomposition operation, which will go on. So, yes, this is, like, not every time it is required. If you feel that, okay, then only it should be invoked.
PAUL: How many of you know about query decomposition? Please let me know.
PAUL: Decomposition means if you have three sentences, you try to break it into one sentence, one sentence, 1 sentence. If you have a paragraph, break it into multiple sentences.
PAUL: Then, if you want to find, whenever you are invoking a retriever, please don't pass the entire paragraph, rather than pass the first sentence, then the second sentence. In that way, try to get multiple contexts.
PAUL: Okay? And then you can perform a summarize operation on top of that, and then directly pass it to the engine. So, query decomposition, even in practicals, I'll be showing you, it is very, very important.
PAUL: So, right here, now, this is a breakdown, complex problem, step by step. Okay, in simple examples, if I'm, talking…
PAUL: So, the query is coming, retriever, generate. Now, you can see, with respect to the retriever, I told you, query transformation slash decomposition. It means that the big paragraph will be broken into multiple sentences.
PAUL: And then each sentence will go to the retrieve, and finally, like, you will be getting multiple contexts, then that context concatenation, and finally you will be getting the results.
PAUL: So, this is good, but again, this is a very long process. If you are working with recursive-based query decomposition problems.
PAUL: the response time will be higher. When I'm talking about higher, you can at least think about more than
PAUL: 35 seconds, because this operation can take only close to 4 to 5 seconds. Not in milliseconds, guys. This operation takes 4 to 5 seconds.
PAUL: Because your context window will become very, very big.
PAUL: because of that, okay, so the, your token consumption also increases, okay? So, pretty much a costly operation at the end of the data type field with respect to the recursive.
PAUL: Now, the next one that we have is basically the adaptive one. Okay, now, this one that I prefer much more, okay? Later on, even I'll be talking about adaptive rack. So, very specifically, there we focus. Now, here, can you see there is something called as retrieve on demand.
PAUL: Okay, so retrieve on demand, what is the meaning of retrieve on demand?
PAUL: Please let me know. It means that whether you want to invoke the retriever or not.
PAUL: Or directly pass it to the LN.
PAUL: Now, there is a judge who will decide.
PAUL: So, basically, who does the decision? The LLM is there. Okay, so the LLM is there, who will be doing this particular decision, that whether you want to invoke the retriever or not.
PAUL: Now, this is one of the fastest operations, guys.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why I prefer adaptive much more, because here you can see, this is one route.
PAUL: And this is the other route. If you think about this particular route, it's pretty much the same like here.
PAUL: Okay? But this route is there. This route actually saves a lot of time.
PAUL: Okay, so here you know that if the judge decides the retriever doesn't need to invoke this complete
PAUL: I can say flow, that can be ignored, and directly you can go generate and response.
PAUL: So, really, like, this is, I can say, one of the best ones, okay?
PAUL: So now let's… I'll look into some examples, because with respect to adapting at any point of time.
PAUL: Judges… judge will be always LLM, so don't get confused at any point of time in all of these three. Okay, whenever there is a judge written, or a jury written somewhere, it will be an LLM at the end of the day.
PAUL: So,
PAUL: Let's take some examples of these three features, okay, which will help you to understand each of these things. So, first of all, with respect to
PAUL: this one, query decomposition. Okay, so I don't know, because few people might have heard the term first time, so recursive, actually, the main thing is query decomposition. So, let's get back to our notes.
PAUL: Because I think after this, you have only one major diagram, and then we will be done.
PAUL: Okay, so… notes.
PAUL: Because from going forward, it will be all practicals, guys. Today is the main…
PAUL: theoretical last class. So I know it's a bit boring, but yes, really, few fundamental concepts that I feel that you guys should be familiar with.
PAUL: Okay, so let's try to understand, query decomposition a little bit. Okay, so how it happens.
PAUL: I told you, like, paragraph to sentences, but it's not necessary every time, it has to be paragraph.
PAUL: Okay, so let's try to understand.
PAUL: So, the first part, if I ask a question, okay, so something like, okay, I have to take a big sentence, because I have to break it into
PAUL: Okay, so, alright.
PAUL: I'm taking a bigger one, okay? I have…
PAUL: Okay, so how does the GDP… countries… dot… Hosted.
PAUL: Olympics… After… 2000.
PAUL: Great.
PAUL: Now, if you try to reason this question, can I break this into multiple questions or not?
PAUL: Okay, and probably, like, let's try to do some type of comparison here. I will just add a compar…
PAUL: Okay, so now, if I want to really get the answer for this, okay, so the first question, I can say Q1. Can I say that,
PAUL: First of all, I need to find the countries who hosted Olympics after 2000,
PAUL: Okay, so the first question will be, like, countries.
PAUL: Hosted.
PAUL: Olympics?
PAUL: After 2000.
PAUL: First, I need to, because really, we do move the country. So, this is one of the first questions.
PAUL: then your Q2 will be something like that, okay? Now, once you know these countries, so, for example, if I say… okay, I'm taking random names, guys. Okay, Spain…
PAUL: Goodies.
PAUL: Australia.
PAUL: Okay, now the next question will be, like, GDP.
PAUL: Up.
PAUL: Like, one question will be Spain.
PAUL: then your Q3 will be GDP of… Greece?
PAUL: Then comes Q4 will be GDP up.
PAUL: Australia.
PAUL: Okay, now from here, you have to fetch. So, can I say that, yes, you have? Okay, and finally…
PAUL: I can sit at compare all of them.
PAUL: Okay, it means that, because previously I told a paragraph into sentence, but you have to really understand, sometimes that in a single question, there can be multiple questions. So you have to actually break down that particular task.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why this is basically the recursive approach, okay, where you try to break down into smaller problems, and then, like, try to solve it, okay, in a manner, and then finally get your result. So this is query decomposition.
PAUL: I think for everyone, it should be clear.
PAUL: Yes?
PAUL: Country, we did not mention the option, like, country.
PAUL: We did not mention the… how does the GDP of the contractors hosted after 2000 compare? What's a… as a sample, like,
PAUL: What country is missing?
PAUL: It did not mention the option, like, country, then can't be possible. In the main question, this is the actual question, actual question is this one.
PAUL: Okay, now this is the decomposed version 1, D2, this is D3, this is D4, and D5.
PAUL: From each one, we'll be trying to fetch the context, okay? And then we will try to build the response.
PAUL: Yes, we will see query decomposition implementation. Practically will be done.
PAUL: Yes, first, because here, actually, you have to find the countries. So, countries hosted Olympics, so this, really, you need to solve it. If you can solve this question, then only the next question and others, that can be solved.
PAUL: Is this part clear, guys, with respect to query decomposition?
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: So, this query decomposition. Okay, now this is the recursive approach.
PAUL: That you have, okay. Now comes adaptive. Adaptive approach, the best paper that I can say is the, SRAC paper.
PAUL: Okay, because, here you have much more of a logic. Okay, so if I take this…
PAUL: Just wait, I'm just getting the…
PAUL: Oh, beautiful.
PAUL: Goodbye.
PAUL: Alright, so in this particular approach, if you look, it's much more of a, decision logic algorithm, okay? Because directly… and here's some type of confidence that needs to be generated, okay? So, I will say that the judge
PAUL: your judge, output.
PAUL: Will be a threshold confidence.
PAUL: You have to remember this. It will be a threshold confidence, okay?
PAUL: Now, this particular confidence, which will be thrown by, okay, so, a simple, like, if… the confidence… Okay.
PAUL: is below that, okay? So, whatever that
PAUL: generated answer from the LLM that is coming, or the user query right now.
PAUL: Okay, so if confidence of the generated answer, okay, is less than the threshold.
PAUL: Okay, then simply what you will do, trigger.
PAUL: Your, retrieval.
PAUL: Otherwise, what will be the condition?
PAUL: Another condition, guys, Aleph.
PAUL: If it is… Okay.
PAUL: Another is content. Okay, so can you see here, there is a concept of spatial tokens.
PAUL: generate special token slash threshold. So, it's not only threshold, so there are certain tokens that have been very specifically added for adaptive approaches, okay? So, one of them is retrieve token, okay? So, using a retrieve token, or there is a,
PAUL: IS, IL… when I'll be talking about CellPrack, then I'll be talking about these tokens, because these are very special tokens. Otherwise, the most common tokens anyone has heard about
PAUL: Yes, in LLMs, what are the most common tokens? Anyone.
PAUL: Because this is the most basic answer that I'm asking. EOF, correct. EOS correct. CLS, correct.
PAUL: Okay? Start token correct, end token correct, SAP token correct. Okay, yes, few people know. Only…
PAUL: 6 people have told. Okay, so whenever you are working with, any type of them, okay.
PAUL: Clive, VIT, no.
PAUL: No, no, no, no, I'm talking about tokens, guys, okay? So, these are very, specific tokens, so when you are actually generating something at that particular point of time, it's very important. No, tick token is separate.
PAUL: Alright, contains, here, very specific, tokens for now, that I will create here.
PAUL: So, you can actually pass this, okay, as very separate tokens.
PAUL: And a few of the common tokens which are widely used here is retrip token.
PAUL: Yeah, so Retrieval is one very specific type of token which can directly invoke the retriever. So, that's why it's widely used, that's why the name of the token is also Retrieval tool.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And, these type of tokens in this adaptive, is referred to as reflection tokens.
PAUL: the name to these tokens, because these are not LLM-based tokens. They are very specific to RAG architecture, so that's why the name Reflection Tokens that have been given here.
PAUL: Okay, so then, the next step is…
PAUL: Trigger retrieval, okay, here also.
PAUL: your retrie bill.
PAUL: and continue. Now, when you are actually using a token, so directly retrieval will come. Else…
PAUL: Your final step, okay, which is basically, this one. Okay, generate and respond. Okay, that is…
PAUL: main one, so I will just write here, continue generation.
PAUL: So, this is a simple algorithm based on this particular token-based approach. So, you have to understand, at any point of time, so this judge… can you see this judge that comes into the picture?
PAUL: This judge will actually throw that
PAUL: special token. Okay, so the judge, so here, so once, if this is done, then in the next step, so judge will throw the special token.
PAUL: Then the retrieve and continue. It means that this is the second level of judge.
PAUL: The first judge is only deciding whether you need to do the retrieval or not. Then the second judge is, basically looking into the quality of the response. If it feels that it is below a certain threshold, then again, it will basically throw this
PAUL: particular token, the retrieve token. When it throws the retrip token, we know that you have to do, again, the retrieval process, and again, continue. So that's why it becomes completely a repetitive step in simple terms.
PAUL: The idea is to continuously do the evaluation also. Now, this is implemented in your cell track. So, when we'll be talking about cell track, I'll be letting you know about this particular architecture.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: So, can you please repeat? I have repeated the entire process, please let me know, or do I need to do that one once again?
PAUL: In iterative, does it rewrite the sentence before decomposing? No, for now,
PAUL: In iterative process, there is no decomposition. Only in recursive process, there is decomposition.
PAUL: A reflection token, okay? So, see, this, there are different types of token. I am just telling you.
PAUL: Like, see, at the end of the day, you know that EOS is an end of sentence, okay? So, or SOS is a start of a sentence. So, similarly, this token, it is called as retry.
PAUL: But actually, the name is Reflection Token.
PAUL: Okay, this token that you have… Okay.
PAUL: Similarly, there is a token called as ease.
PAUL: Okay, there are some other tokens also. So, because I don't want to go in-depth, so they have a very different category. Okay, so something like continue.
PAUL: These are… okay, now all these are called as reflection tools.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: And what it does, basically, the main meaning is sell… Reflect.
PAUL: The idea is self-realization. It means that you do this step, okay, just because to improve your answer.
PAUL: Okay, so retrieve and continue.
PAUL: Alright, so for now…
PAUL: this part that we have done, okay. So, again, I will just, let's go through once more, and then…
PAUL: Okay, so let's get back to our paper.
PAUL: Screen, I think there's a text or two, okay? So, iterative process is the most common one. Here, what happens, basically, okay, you are just repeating itself. It means that till the time, the judge will be happy with the answer, okay? It will keep on repeating.
PAUL: Okay, because at the end of the day, what happens? Just think about, you have iterated n times, n is 10, and by the 10th time also, the judge is not happy. Then do you think that you will be getting a response? So, at the end of the day, there is no response on it.
PAUL: Okay, so… but that's why here, very specifically, the last time, the max time, because you'll be setting, because we cannot say to the end user that after 10 times, also, the judge is not happy, because of that, I'm not giving you answer.
PAUL: We cannot say that. So, whatever will be that max time, that threshold that you have set, okay, based on that, you'll be getting the final response.
PAUL: So, here, can you see that there is a bypass? It means that even if the judge fails.
PAUL: Okay, just because of that max time that I'm providing. Okay, so it can do that. I can say that though the answer might not be good, then also it will be thrown as a response. So, really, like, this is…
PAUL: One of the cons, I feel, but this is how the system that they have designed, very specifically for iterating.
PAUL: Okay, so here's, so always take numbers in, lower numbers, probably 6 to 7.
PAUL: Okay, I feel that's 6 to 7 or 5 to… because we'll be doing the implementation of this also, where I'll be taking Judge, probably as ChatGPT, okay, and then we'll be looking into that.
PAUL: Yes, Rajesh, you were telling me this is not useful in inter… totally depends upon you. If you are building rack-based systems, then only these type of things are required. If you are not building directly, really, for one year or two years of experience, not required. If anybody is much more and they are building complex systems, then only it's required.
PAUL: Okay, so these are, incremental processes you have to understand, like, anybody more than 5 years or 6 years. For them, these things are much more important. Rather than 1 year or 2 years, if somebody's there, I know these things will be a little bit boring.
PAUL: Alright, so, the core part, I have already told you, recursive and adaptive, okay?
PAUL: Now, because here, the core part was all about this one new thing that got added, which was the special token, referred to as reflection tokens.
PAUL: Now, finally, I think, hmm… Single hop, okay, these are different type of tasks.
PAUL: I think, final one will be there. Okay, now this will be the final one.
PAUL: After this, we are done, because at the end of the day, this is the entire RAG ecosystem that we are going to learn in the upcoming months.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, I think it will take maximum 10 minutes more, and then we will be doing the completion.
PAUL: Everybody's saying, like, when will the class end?
PAUL: Really, like, we take a time, like, close to at least 3 hours.
PAUL: Alright, so everybody focus on this part, because the actual architecture comes from here.
PAUL: So, first of all, the RAG ecosystem, okay, which is basically the downstream task.
PAUL: It means that RAG can be built for what type of task. One is dialogue.
PAUL: It means simple conversational text. Then comes Q&A, question answering, the most common one, like chatbots, I can say. Okay, like, everybody's building chatbots.
PAUL: It can be open domain question answering also. Okay, dialogue-based also chatbots that you can think about. In simple, conversational dialogue. There also, I have seen people are building
PAUL: jackboard-based systems. Then comes summarization. This is a tech summarization operation that your RAC can help you with. Then comes fact check, or fact verification, one of the most important ones, through which you can get citations.
PAUL: Okay, so these are all different types of downstreaming tasks that can be done using rank. So this, that's why, referred to as a downstream task.
PAUL: Now, what are the technology stack? So, LanChain, Llama Intex, Flowwise.
PAUL: and AutoChain. Okay, so, like, in this course, we will be talking about Langchen and Llama Index much more. And flow-wise, this is much more of a no-code-based solution. Okay, so…
PAUL: We are focused much more on code, rather than on no-code. And then comes, Autogen. Autogen is another framework, very specifically, AgentTic.
PAUL: Okay, so these are few of the major tech stacks that have been mentioned, but this tech stack can be increased
PAUL: To a lot, okay? But these are the most common ones.
PAUL: Now, the rack paradigm. I told you about 3 racks. The name rack, always start with something small, then add functionalities.
PAUL: Then add complete, like, whatever the other functionalities, to make a complete, robust solution. Okay, so, like, in modular rack, all the components are not required. Whichever you feel, that only you can do.
PAUL: Now, here, inside this, now the main things that comes. Okay, the ones that will be going in deeper with respect to practical implementation. One is chunk optimization.
PAUL: Okay, so we have to look into different type of chunking strategies.
PAUL: Okay, what is a perfect chunk size? Okay, there is no… not a single place where it will be written. This is a perfect size, this is a perfect size. Nobody knows that. Okay, because this is a hyperparameter, you have to select based on your data.
PAUL: Probably for me, 1000, it works. Probably, in your case, only 800 needed, 600. So, these are complete hyperparameters.
PAUL: Hyperparameters, so these things that we'll be talking about. Then comes iterative retrieval, yes, we'll be talking about this. Retriever fine-tuning, we'll be talking about this one also. Query transformation, yes.
PAUL: Breaking down queries into smaller queries.
PAUL: Recursive retrieval, adaptive retrieval, context selection, dual fine-tuning. Now, this will be at the last that we'll be doing, because this is a very complex and, job. It means that only I can show, you cannot do it.
PAUL: Okay, it's such type of task. Retriever fine-tuning, much easier. Generator fine-tuning, this also that we can do.
PAUL: So, right now, these are a few of the simple techniques for track. Now, all these things which are written, we'll be doing the discussion and the practical implementation of all those things. Only, I think, in class, dual fine-tuning, you guys cannot. You need to spend money. Okay, in dollars, so…
PAUL: So that's why the idea was to give you the idea that what are the things that we are going through? Because, see, right here, embedding is not written, but you have to understand, I'll be talking about embeddings and other stuff, all those things in detail, because from tomorrow, we will start with the practical implementation.
PAUL: Key issues in Rack, what to retrieve, when to retrieve, and how to use the retrieve.
PAUL: Okay, these are one of the major issues that needs to be addressed.
PAUL: What to retrieve?
PAUL: Can anybody say what to retrieve?
PAUL: When to return?
PAUL: Okay, now, because these are, like, every time you don't need to retrieve. Okay, so that's why your adaptive rack came into the picture. Okay, or basically that adaptive architecture.
PAUL: All right, then comes RAG prospects challenges. So, rag in, long context length, okay? So, yes, if your context length is very, very big, okay, there can be a use case where your RAG context has actually surpassed your LLN. Okay, in that case, what happens?
PAUL: Though the LLM will throw you the response, but you will feel that a lot of information that has been removed.
PAUL: Okay, it happens all the times.
PAUL: Okay, then comes scaling laws, production ready, okay, now these are practical implementations rather than this. Modality extension, image, audio, video, code.
PAUL: ecosystem, so these are symbols. Okay, now, evaluation of RAG, retrieval quality, general quality. Now, these are a few of the metrics where, like, we'll be using RAGAS in this course widely, but there are other metrics also, like.
PAUL: two lenses there. But, in our course, very specifically with respect to the tools, Ragas that we'll be taking. Benchmarking, majorly, like, recall and RGB that will come, CRAD, much more lesser that we'll be using.
PAUL: But these are the major ones, and if you look into, like, answer relevance, context relevance, answer faithfulness.
PAUL: These are, like, must evaluations. If you are building a rack, this thing should be there. If it's not there.
PAUL: Okay, then it means that you have not implemented any type of evaluation strategy. It totally ram Baru said, what we say. Okay, it means that things are working, but really, at any point of time, you have to really take that.
PAUL: Okay. So, I think now our main paper is done, because in the next upcoming months, we'll be focusing much more on this technology stack, rather than much more on the architectures. It's only when we discuss the papers.
PAUL: Because going forward, I won't be taking an entire class, max 20 minutes of paper discussion, then directly I'll be jumping into practical implementation.
PAUL: Okay, so, yes, today's, I think this part is done. It's 12.20, I told you, it won't take a lot of time.
PAUL: We will explore language fuse. If you see, if it is an open source, then tell me. Okay? Sorry. If it is open source, tell me.
PAUL: I am ready to bring open source stuff always. Like, somebody suggested, the Rift paper. I totally fine. We can go through. But, the practical implementation is not available, because that paper is really promising that I found.
PAUL: It was a good paper, I think whoever, told in the chat with respect to REFT.
PAUL: Alright, so I can start taking questions now.
PAUL: Okay, so guys, step by step, just raise your hands.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Okay, fine, I will be taking everybody's question. I am here till 1.50 PM, okay? So, whoever wants to, go ahead.
PAUL: First of all, so let's start with Mank.
PAUL: Okay, so there is Mayank, then Kaushik Saha, then there is Anshul Singh, there is Rohan, there is AKS,
PAUL: Okay, a few people I have unmuted, so guys, one by one, please go ahead.
PAUL: Why nobody's going out?
Kaushik Saha: the…
PAUL: Yes, we are done with the class. If you want to leave, we can.
PAUL: Yes, papers and references, I'll be adding it in the Notion, don't worry.
PAUL: Yes, go ahead, anyone, please, man, causate, you people raised their hand.
Kaushik Saha: The ball crushing the side.
PAUL: Yeah, across the board, please.
Kaushik Saha: Thing is, when we discussed initially the LLM, right? So, how…
Kaushik Saha: I mean, we are discussing on… on top of the LLM, we'll be using RAG, and we need to select the LLM, right? So, LLM has some context or some foundational details and all.
PAUL: So, how do we understand.
Kaushik Saha: that what we need, right? Let's say we need to use something which they don't have enough details, that is why we are using RAG. So how to choose the LLM for the use case perspective, right? Which LLM.
PAUL: Generally, what happens… so, you can actually… the LLM always knows that… whether it knows the answer or not.
PAUL: Okay, through certain instructions, you can actually do that stuff. But, as you told, like, see, my idea is always using generic LLMs. For example, if you are doing any domain-specific tasks, for example, in healthcare. Now, for medical, there are very medical specialized LLMs that can be used.
PAUL: So there, you don't need to use ChatGPT and other stuff.
PAUL: Okay, now that is a different thing. Now, the idea is that how you know that the LLM knows or not? Okay, that evaluation can always be done through a judge, probably some external LLM that you can edit.
PAUL: Because probably through prompts, also, if you try to say that, okay, if you don't feel that you don't know the answer, directly, so yes or no. Through prompt engineering, you can't do that. That's not a big deal. But that yes or no, if it is no, then you can directly invoke the retriever.
PAUL: Okay? If you feel that, okay, it's not telling no, and it's throwing the response, you can evaluate the response through some other LLM at any point of time, and you can get verified.
PAUL: And you can actually do that, check that, okay, output from this LLM and this LLM. If there is a similarity score of at least 70%, proceed ahead. If it is less than 70%, discard, regenerate.
Kaushik Saha: I see. Okay, okay, got it. So, also, can we take this such a way that… because when we'll be building any RAG, maybe we want to, I mean, use some open source LLM, right, instead of using, the expensive one.
Kaushik Saha: So, can we take this LLM as that they, like, we are, as a student who knows who… who taught till 10, and then they need to specialize on the particular topic, so we are using RAC for the specialization. So, can we think in that way? That we'll take.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes, she, like.
PAUL: We have worked on that, or very specifically, we are working on some educational content, okay, for some IB schools, actually. So there, yes, we have. So, but we have done that entire textbooks from those
PAUL: We have taken, we have converted those into documents, and the same process that we have done, maintain a vector table for that particular IB school, okay? And then we have recreated and built a system only for that school.
PAUL: So, yes, you can do that.
Kaushik Saha: Thank you so much, and then…
PAUL: I'd use an educational systems. Yeah, go ahead. Last question.
Kaushik Saha: That, you say that, I think the routing part, in the routing part, probably first, LLM will be.
PAUL: Which routing? Query routing or the normal routing? Like, there were two routing, query routing in advanced track, and normal routing.
Kaushik Saha: very routing.
Kaushik Saha: Where you send it directly to the data source, right? Like.
Kaushik Saha: it will directly, from LLM, it will give the answer, it will not go to RAG or the reference document.
Kaushik Saha: if they feel that it is enough to answer that, right? Something… I think.
PAUL: The idea was that there will be some type of decision logic which will help you to route it towards the parametric memory or the non-parametric memory. That decision logic, if you think about for now, let's take a judge, for example, as another LLM for now, just to think it easier. It means that the query comes, okay, if it really feels that the output, okay, it is of a certain threshold or a quality.
PAUL: that you have decided. Then you don't need to invoke the retriever. If you feel the quality is less, then only invoke the retrieval.
PAUL: in that.
Kaushik Saha: Okay, so in the quality judge, it will be done by any other LLM, or we are re-ranking or something, what we were…
PAUL: It can be done through LLM itself also, through prompt engineering, you can do that, I told you, the same thing, just like last time.
PAUL: Okay, it means that I… when I show you the example, through prompts, you can do multiple things. Okay, so I'll be showing you some prompts where we actually decide that. Simply say yes or no. The LLM can respond in that way also. If it says no, invoke the retriever. Okay, so yes, we can do it.
PAUL: That is…
Kaushik Saha: Thank you, thank you so much.
PAUL: That's a possibility.
Kaushik Saha: Bye.
Kaushik Saha: Thank you.
PAUL: And, Rishab was asking how decomposition was happening within this adaptive approach. The concept of decomposition was the same in the adaptive as well as in recursive.
PAUL: Okay, the same way it happens.
PAUL: the text concatenation process is there. Next, aka Sanchu, anyone, so many people I have unmuted. Weekly COVID, please, guys.
PAUL: Then there is, Kiran Rathur, Nitesh…
PAUL: A few other people also that I'm doing.
PAUL: Yes, please go ahead.
Rohan: I wanted to ask a question on the recursive retrieval. So, when you say, we do the query decomposition, and for each query we do a separate retrieval.
Rohan: Do we combine that for generate, when we pass.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes. See, to make the final answer, you need all the context, no. If there were 5 questions, all the 5 answers are required, okay, then only you can create your final answer.
Rohan: So it's not going in parallel, it's all combined into one context and one call to the generator LLM.
PAUL: Not in parallel means, okay, already making 5 different parallel calls.
Rohan: Yeah.
Rohan: If you just think about, in parallel, if it happens, first.
PAUL: Query, like, it has to find the countries.
PAUL: If it finds the countries, then only it can find the GDP.
PAUL: If it finds the GDP, then only it can compare. I hope you get it. If you're trying to do it general, then it is not possible.
Rohan: Okay. I had a question in chat, it was at the very beginning of the class.
PAUL: Yeah, Tessa.
Rohan: So, you said that you prefer parametric memory over non-parametric. Can you just elaborate on your preference and why?
PAUL: Let's see, if I'm only working with parametric memory, it means that I'm only working with LNF, so I don't need to build right systems, as simple as that. Majority of the time, that's why people are building, like, starting from 2025, the research is on that. People are building much more, that, I can say, domain-specific LNF.
PAUL: So that the requirement of RAG will be much more cheaper. Probably after 4 or 5 years, really, the RAG system that we are building, you can see that there will be…
PAUL: some requirement of RAG will be there, but the responses will be much more better, because if somebody's in healthcare, and if he uses, or he's building a rag with that LLM, okay, the response will be of much better quality. At the end of the day, you have to understand.
PAUL: That fine-tuning, responses are much better as compared to a rack.
Rohan: Okay.
PAUL: You said that you will be kind…
PAUL: Accuracy is always better there, that's why.
Rohan: Okay, got it. You said that we'll be covering, like, a couple of things in fine-tuning, as well, right?
PAUL: raft.
PAUL: Yes, that is the rack fine-tuning that we'll be talking about.
Rohan: Okay, so that's not model fine-tuning.
PAUL: No, no, no, LLM fine tuning?
PAUL: If you want to, I can share a notebook with Laura and Q Laura, but that is not… that is LL. I'm talking with respect to RAG.
PAUL: Okay.
Rohan: Okay, okay. Yeah, yeah, if you could share something related to,
Rohan: the LM fine-tuning as well, that would be helpful.
PAUL: Because I… in class, when I teach, everybody just sit down and see. Nobody does it parallel with me.
PAUL: That's why, when I teach that topic, I feel very less. Previously, I've taught, like, Quora, LoRa, DORA, 4 to 5. Everybody sits in class and they watch.
PAUL: That's why I feel that… I feel that if I ask any questions, if I tell them, neither they can agree or neither. Because to launch that particular infra, you need to spend close to at least. You can think about
PAUL: Because few things that can be done in Google Collab in free version, but again, with a limited set. It means that you cannot bring a proper data set, it's just one small file, something like that.
PAUL: And if you want that, I can share you a few resources, okay? You can drop me a mail based on your requirement that I want to fine-tune this on top of this, okay?
PAUL: Based on that, I will let you know. Because there are a few things in LoRa, QLORA, DORA, Vara, there are certain adapters, so the selection of the adapters, I will let you know that, okay, this adapter is good for your use case, okay?
Rohan: Okay. Thank you.
PAUL: Alright.
Kiran Rathod: Yeah, I bought it.
Kiran Rathod: Kieran here. Paul, I wanted to understand what is… I mean, still, can you give me an example of…
Kiran Rathod: The use case for… or the difference between query and a prompt, with an example.
PAUL: Then now you are confused with this one, just wait.
PAUL: Okay, I'll read.
PAUL: Just wait.
PAUL: app at the rate, krishnag. Okay, just wait, app at the right.
PAUL: Alright, let me show you code only. I think it will be better.
PAUL: This is the Storm 2, I think my wind surf, so I'm ready.
Anshu singh: Okay, don't worry about that. He would do that, no?
PAUL: Okay.
Anshu singh: Yeah.
PAUL: Who is this? Please be on mute.
PAUL: You know, to somebody's eating.
Anshu singh: Okay.
PAUL: Anxious and disabled talking.
PAUL: All right. So…
PAUL: When I am at… see, user queries generally an interrogative question, for now. Okay, so with respect to…
Kiran Rathod: Yeah, I've been reading things.
PAUL: This is your tomorrow's content.
PAUL: It's getting heat.
PAUL: A system prompt. This is a prompt, like, you are an helpful assistant for question-answering task.
PAUL: Use the following pieces of retrieve context to answer the question. If you don't know the answer based on the context, say that you don't know. Keep the answer concise and accurate. And then comes, basically, the context that we are getting from the vector TB, and this is the query that comes from the user.
PAUL: This is the actual prompt.
PAUL: Okay, the quotient is separate. Can you see quotient is just like a placeholder.
PAUL: Okay, that will be asking it separately. So, for example.
PAUL: And I think, like, see, this is the main query.
PAUL: Okay, and then I am invoking the, reaction that I have.
PAUL: Okay, so this becomes your main query to the system.
PAUL: So, this is basically a prompt that you have.
PAUL: This is a set of instruction that I'm telling to them.
PAUL: Got it?
PAUL: Yes, let me know.
Kiran Rathod: Sorry, I'm not able to visualize this.
PAUL: Okay, in tomorrow's class, we'll be talking about… you can ask simply ChatGPT what is a prompt and what is.
Kiran Rathod: But it's giving some different answers, so I was just thinking what exactly is the difference here?
PAUL: What is the difference here? Now, these are the set of instructions that we only pass to the LLM.
PAUL: This is nothing related to the query. The query is related to based on the data sources. For example, if you are adding a PDF, we will ask the question from the PDF.
PAUL: Okay? Now, in the prompt, you can say that, okay, the output.
Nitesh: That is coming from the LLM. I want in this format, that format.
PAUL: As simple as that. It means that somehow you are just structuring the output, the generated output from the LLM.
PAUL: For that, you are passing a set of instructions.
Kiran Rathod: Okay, so can you consider…
Kiran Rathod: a query, simple user query, as an input to the LLM, and the prompt is the structured way that we want to.
PAUL: to the LLM, it means that based on the data sources that you have provided, based on that, it has to be the query. It means that if you are passing a PDF, in that PDF, there is a probably, like, based on that PDF, you are asking the question, okay?
Kiran Rathod: Yeah.
PAUL: That becomes your query. Now, that query, you passed it to your RAG. Okay, and now RAG is basically throwing you the answer. Now, in the answer, you need a certain format.
PAUL: Okay, probably a markdown format, JSON format, so that you are manipulating the output, or the generated output from the LN.
PAUL: So, in that way, the LLM will actually know that, okay, you are looking for this type, or this structured response.
Kiran Rathod: Okay, basically, the prompt is something which we are structuring the output in the format that we want to use it.
PAUL: You can do a lot of other things, but for now, this is an example. That's why it's called a system prompt. Okay, later on, I'll be talking about in Langcham, it's called system prompts. In some other place, it's different, but the core part, it's a prompt. It's basically a set of instructions that you pass it to the LN.
Kiran Rathod: Okay.
PAUL: Okay?
Kiran Rathod: Yeah, and I had one, one, use case. How do we know if that is the right candidate for a RAG or an agent DKI? How do we make the difference between
Kiran Rathod: The two applications that we want to build.
PAUL: See, inside agenting AI, RAG can be there. RAG is just a small thing, just think about a simple Python function.
PAUL: Now, that Python function, you wrap it inside an agent, doesn't matter. Inside an agent, I can do computer vision, NLP, machine learning, everything at the end of the day.
PAUL: If you want HGT calls, it totally depends upon that.
PAUL: Okay, so in aging, I feel that somewhere, with respect to some level of automation that can be done, I feel that it's good.
PAUL: Okay, now, it totally depends upon the use case. If you let me know the use case, okay.
PAUL: And, like, how many people are working?
PAUL: dead.
PAUL: I can't tell you exactly, like, whether it will be helpful or not.
Kiran Rathod: Sure, so should I mail the use case to the mail you provided? Okay. And in this, yeah, and in this course, as a part of the, programming that we're doing hands-on, we'll be building the rack from the nave rack, and.
PAUL: Enhancing it to further…
Kiran Rathod: advance.
PAUL: idea is to start with Langchain, because most of the work that I'll be doing is initially with Langchain more. Okay, then I will jump to Llama Intex and Haystad. So, yes, Nebrag, like, tomorrow the thing that I'll be discussing, it's pretty much Nebrag.
Kiran Rathod: Nevrek, okay.
PAUL: Yeah.
Kiran Rathod: Thank you.
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, quickly go ahead.
Nitesh: Thanks, thanks, thanks a lot, Paul, for the wonderful session. So, I had two query, basically, maybe not the complex one, but just wanted to understand, I mean, I'm seeing that probably this chunk, the data ingestion pipeline we talk about is the very first step, and we replicate, or maybe kind of alternatively calling it indexing as well.
Nitesh: So I'm just trying to understand the indexing. When I say indexing, it's the same thing that, like, chunking the documents, or maybe the…
PAUL: Indexing means chunking, then you convert them into vectors, then you put that vectors into a vector table, that is called only indexing. Yeah, so it's all together, it's like, we call it, like, indexing, right? So… Generally, we say, document indexing, then automatically hold water nodes.
PAUL: It means the embeddings are ready, and you have put them into some type of vector thing, that's why.
Nitesh: Okay, okay, this helps. And then when you talk about the different frameworks, like Langchain, Lama Index, and everything for this technology, to probably help to build REAC systems, does the crew buy also play a role here, or is it, like, a little different? Because, I've seen… okay.
PAUL: In Curve AI, there is a direct rack tool, which is available, that you can directly use it. Okay, otherwise, what you can do, inside an agent, you can just create a Python function, wrapping entire line chain.
PAUL: That I have done in my last class, if somebody's from Agent Tick 1.2. The same thing that I have done here, I have wrapped an entire LangChain thing within an agent, then I have connected it through a preview, and I have done the orchestration.
PAUL: See, whenever concept of agent means what? Within an agent, you will run something. It can be machine learning, deep learning, anything it can.
PAUL: Okay. So, yes, inside a Cree BI agent, I can run a luncheon run.
Nitesh: Okay, so it's always better to kind of understand the fundamentals, like, through a link chain, and the crew eye is just moreover the wrapper, which is also kind of a…
PAUL: Langchain is much market-dominating, I can say.
PAUL: Okay, that's why, because after that, when I come to Llama Intex, little bit less dominating, haystack.
PAUL: Little bit… because there are so many frameworks. Right now.
PAUL: We have only selected 3 for now, I feel that because Haystack is pretty much straightforward. You really don't need to do… if you know the basics of Langchain here directly, you just import, done, import, done.
PAUL: So it's much easier, at any point of time to build bigger pipelines for production.
Nitesh: Yeah, thanks, thanks.
PAUL: Okay, so initially we will cover RAC framework, then we will come to our agent tech framework, which is Langker.
Nitesh: Excellent.
PAUL: Okay, guys, so next.
Satyabrata: Yeah, hi, Paul.
Satyabrata: I have a query related to the outing. Just on example, right? Suppose I'm working on an insurance firm, and I have some, policy information, some regulation kind of information I'm getting from internet, which might be from IRDA, but my organization, I have some, little, little different,
Satyabrata: Regulation kind of thing.
Satyabrata: Whether I want to give priority to my external data, my internal company policy.
Satyabrata: So, when it's getting both, it should be provided to my, data which I'm giving, not by the… given by the LLM. So, is it possible to give some priority kind of thing, in the rack, instead of, depending upon the LLM measure charge? Is it possible to be able…
PAUL: Yeah, like, you could set a priority that, first.
PAUL: it will go to this one, external, then it will go to that one. It means that both the calls that you are making at the end of the day.
Satyabrata: Yeah, partly.
PAUL: Exactly, you have to make that decision logic that, okay, from there, I'm getting one output from there, but actually, like, out of those two outputs which you need to evaluate, okay, probably through human in the loop, or through an evaluation criteria.
PAUL: Because both the contexts, you cannot send it.
PAUL: Exactly. You need to pick up the correct context and then move it. So, in that way, yes, it is possible.
Satyabrata: So, human in the lupus study, I think, right? Or do you think as.
PAUL: In your case, I feel that, you know, see, generally what.
Satyabrata: Right.
PAUL: If subject matter, expert is required, okay? The guy who decides that, yes, this is correctly generated.
PAUL: Because, really, like, till now, I have seen that there is 1% mistake whenever you are working with elements. So, at least if it is a very sensitive area, like healthcare and other stuff, it's always good to do a human in the loop.
Satyabrata: Gotcha, gotcha, thanks.
PAUL: Next.
Michael Sampath: I have 3 questions. One is, Chunk optimization.
Michael Sampath: How to find the correct chunk size.
PAUL: It depends upon your data.
Michael Sampath: Yeah, but I'm using Llama, and I'm still struggling to find the right chunk size. I keep changing…
PAUL: This is a hyperparameter. See, when somebody says that this is a hyperparameter, there is no… it means that I can show you that there are 10 different junctions.
PAUL: You can build child-parent relationship, but nobody knows the number.
PAUL: It's just a hyperparameter that you have to play with. For example, I always start with something bigger, okay, and then I try to make it lower.
PAUL: Because bigger chunk size is also not very helpful. I have tested with 1600, sometime with 2000, really, it was not helpful.
PAUL: Sometimes I feel 600 and 800 does so jump, but more practical approach, I feel, something around 900 and below 1,000, that works for me, for generic use cases, but again, not for all.
PAUL: If I'm working with code files, okay, then the chunking strategy, differs.
PAUL: See, like, you have to define your chunking strategy based on the document, that's why… because if you are working with code files, then your chunking strategy is different. If you're working with PDF files, then it is different. That's why you have to understand, if you're working with JSON files, then it is different.
PAUL: Understand, junking changes, always.
PAUL: Okay, so it really depends upon your data. So, for example, when I will teach, if I take… I think I will take one example where I have at least 3 to 4 different, documents, and on top of those 4 documents, I have to use Mada Chanker.
PAUL: Then you have to create some type of semantic, hierarchical, chunker, okay, and then you have to do that in a particular implementation.
PAUL: Okay, so really, I cannot say this is the best chunk size, and this is the best chunk overlap.
PAUL: Okay? Really, it depends, okay, upon your data. Little bit we have to analyze, and then little bit test that we have to do, with probably 3 to 4.
PAUL: chunkers, main chunkers, which are available, okay? So, and I'll be talking about a specific library also, that is used widely for chunking.
Michael Sampath: Thank you. And one last question is, talking about specific LLM, industry-specific LLMs.
Michael Sampath: Is there a website or a place I can find, for example, healthcare…
PAUL: We have to do that research, no, because these type of LLMs will be built by research institutions. So they will be open source for sure, but you have to know that who is doing that particular research.
PAUL: Okay, directly I cannot say. You have to do a search, basically, through papers, because for every LLM, there will be a research paper. Because in that research paper, they will be publishing, this is the data set that I have used, this is the benchmark that we are getting. So, through research papers, we can easily fetch it.
Michael Sampath: Thank you. And one… before I just wind up, the last question is, I'm creating an offline RAG. Will modular RAG work on an offline rag?
PAUL: If you are creating an offline rack, few components of modular rack that you can give.
PAUL: Okay, and a few things that probably removed, demonstrate, not required. Okay, and it's totally offline, it means that it won't be having any type of web access.
PAUL: Okay, then that search operation, also, like, API call and all those things. Local means everything from your PDFs only that matters to you, and with that, whatever the LLM has knowledge. No external tools for API calls, like Google, Taverly, these type of calls that need to be done? Yes, sir.
Michael Sampath: Yeah, it's not work then. Okay, yeah, got it.
PAUL: Okay, then not required. Then it becomes much more about advanced rack. Advanced rack, you have to think about more than 50% of the world uses advanced rack.
PAUL: Modular rack components, those are plug-and-play, so anybody wants to use them, plug it, test it, because…
PAUL: If you add all the components, the price increases too much. If you are working with API-based calls like OpenAI, Gemini, Anthropic, really, the cost increases.
Michael Sampath: Okay, thank you, thank you, Paul.
Rahul Parihar: So, Paul, I have… I have shared a notation file and my understanding of, in a diagrammatical way, if you can open that.
Rahul Parihar: My question is.
PAUL: you have shared.
Rahul Parihar: in the… in the… The question in the host and panelist question.
PAUL: I don't have access to that.
Rahul Parihar: Okay, I don't know.
PAUL: Just simply… just tell me, no, what.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, yeah.
PAUL: Exactly.
Rahul Parihar: The question is, about… see, the…
Rahul Parihar: Curie constructions, we are talking only on vector database, but there are… in real time, there are relational database, there are graph database, so if I'm doing a CURI translation by whatever means, like multi-curi, or fusion, or decompose, or setback, or hide, you know.
PAUL: First of all, your query decomposition, when you are doing… so, generally, like, an LLM is used to decompose your query.
PAUL: Okay, because we really don't have a database for that. Okay, you can do that, but, like, fusion and other things, it's the first step to make your retriever active. So, how we were reaching fusion and other things post-retrieval, that I cannot understand.
PAUL: Query, decomposition, this is the first step, where you break something to smaller questions. The idea is to solve each one of them, to fetch context, then again, solve. The idea is step by step.
Rahul Parihar: But the idea could be different, right, Paul? Like, if I'm getting to the right question, my cushion… my… I'm setting a question, getting an answer.
Rahul Parihar: putting that answer into another question, then getting an answer, then putting that answer into another question, till I get the final, fine-tuned question. That is the right question.
Rahul Parihar: determined to be sent to the, to the LLM.
Rahul Parihar: I needed to know that process, like, what would that process look like, and how we can fine-tune our question, because my understanding is asking the right question is important here.
Rahul Parihar: Connect?
PAUL: Alright, so you are talking about the entire how decomposition works that you want to see.
Rahul Parihar: Correct. What would be the basic process or techniques of fine-tuning and answering the right question to the LLM, based on the.
PAUL: Fine-tuning, we don't do fine-tuning of queries or that. Decomposition process, I can show you. Probably, I think, in one or two frameworks, that is supported also. Directly, you can use that, and you can look into the underlying, whatever data code that is available in GitHub. That part, you can always check, no?
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
Rahul Parihar: And I figured…
PAUL: For query decomposition, generally, see, what most of them do, they will use a certain LLN.
PAUL: Okay, using LLM, they will try to break it down.
PAUL: Because without an LLM, it is not possible to break that.
PAUL: Because some things that might be less, but again, the LLM also showed up context about that query, at least, somewhere around.
PAUL: So, that query decomposition, majorly, I have seen it, Haystack, Llama, it's done through LNMs.
Rahul Parihar: Okay, okay.
Rahul Parihar: But what are the… where are these relational DBs and graph DBs being used, you know, and how… how is my question… can be passed to this
Rahul Parihar: Just not to the vector store, but to…
Rahul Parihar: To a real-time relational, DBs, you know, or graph DBs, if that makes sense.
PAUL: Graph tag is totally different, because the database completely changes, like Graph databases, like NeoForge and others, that are being used.
PAUL: Okay, so yes, it is being used, but you have to understand that whether your data that you have, whether it's in such type of tree-based structure, basically for new 4G, we prefer graph-based structures, data, like tree-based in simple terms, where there is one entity related with other entity.
PAUL: Do you have such type of data? Because I'll be taking some examples very specifically. I can pass these PDF documents also directly to, Neo4J, okay? And through that also, I can use a re-triple operation. But we have seen that really, because those databases are not optimized for semantic scoring, as simple as that.
PAUL: To do an embedding comparison, those databases are not used. So that's why I like VectorTeam. I can show you that. Directly, I can pass it, and these type of databases are not also optimized to store high-dimensional data.
PAUL: In graph that, you can do it, but again, SQL, leave it. SQL and these things. Somewhere I tried in Cassandra also, but Cassandra also doesn't work so much good. Very specifically for images and others. Videos, I prefer Cassandra, but I feel that,
PAUL: like, SQL, forget. Okay, so somewhere, with respect to graph, databases are much better.
PAUL: At least with respect to high-dimensional data, but others are not so much, because it's… it totally depends upon that.
PAUL: Like, how is your data? If you feel that lesser dimensions than others, yes, systems are there. Because I know there are systems, very specifically in Databricks and others.
PAUL: Where you can actually directly, some type of, like, magic tool is where directly you pass the query, you will fetch the information from multiple types of SQL tables, it can combine information. Those things are there.
PAUL: Okay, so, here's… but,
PAUL: Little bit different. That's why for SQL-based systems, generally, I prefer to pick some framework directly, which can help me. So, I prefer VANA much more, I know that it has been used a lot.
PAUL: Okay, so you can connect it with SQL-based systems or NoSQL-based systems, but if you are working with VectorTB and GraphRag, very specifically, directly these things can, like, in RAG, we can work it.
PAUL: The only thing that I feel, not, good about GraphRad.
PAUL: Chamon de… latency.
PAUL: it means that with more higher operations, in, like, when I scale it up, I feel that somehow.
PAUL: There is a latency that increases.
PAUL: Okay, because GraphWrap works really good. When I show you the answer, you will feel… you will see that really great.
PAUL: But, like, scaling it up, because it's on database side, I know, but I feel that, somehow there is an impact, and there are a few other consoles.
PAUL: when I'll be talking about GrabPrab practically, but, in your case, based on the question that you asked, I will say that Grab Crab
PAUL: Yeah, use choice if you're more very specifically with those databases.
PAUL: try to use, like, graph-based, any type of, I can say, details. It's much better as compared to SQL-based or NoSQL-based.
Rahul Parihar: Okay, I'm coming from machine learning background about the model evaluation, where we do accuracy, precision, recall, F1, and AOC, you know?
PAUL: These things here also recall comes into the picture.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, in the same document that you have shared, page number 14 table, where it says summary of metrics applicable for Evaluation Aspect of RAG.
Rahul Parihar: PM, recall, precision, R rate, cosine similarity. Cosine similarity is where I've commonly used it, but the only answer relevancy is… is checkbox.
PAUL: That is only for RAG, no? If you are working with RAG, then only those metrics are discussed.
PAUL: But which are the important… It's important of machine learning. All of them are important.
PAUL: All of them are important.
Rahul Parihar: Did you find the number that is in there.
Rahul Parihar: If you're trying to build up a domain knowledge, and you want to judge and identify whether my domain is getting built in the right context or not.
Rahul Parihar: how do I get to that, metal.
PAUL: You need to have your own test set for tech to do the evaluation.
Rahul Parihar: Yes, I have my test set, a larger test set, that's why I am asking that.
PAUL: the test set, then you can actually do the evaluation, based on the responses that are coming from the LM.
PAUL: You can pass, you can use similarity scores, and there are a few metrics that are available in Commed, Galigio, multiple frameworks.
PAUL: Through which you can directly use, these mentioned metric, metrics, like faithfulness, okay, then comes relevancy, okay, all these metrics directly. Like, if you try to use RAGAS directly, they are available.
Rahul Parihar: And all metrics are relevant, like, or there are top 5?
PAUL: At least out of 6, at least used 4.
PAUL: That, I can say. Generally say, it's not… when you actually implement with a framework, nothing you have to do.
PAUL: You have to just run the code, everything you will be getting in one job.
Rahul Parihar: Hmm.
PAUL: You don't have to run, don't think about Y4Y6.
PAUL: I will say that at least the major ones, the… in Ragas, majorly there are 6, I can say. Like, relevance is there, okay, faithfulness is there. Like, 4 major evaluation methods are there. Okay, but for that, you need to have a test set, that's why. If you don't have a test set, then you can't implement it.
Rahul Parihar: Okay.
PAUL: Also, evaluation will come probably, I think, after a long time, like, after your second month, when I'll be talking with respect to RAGAs and tools, I think, whichever framework is there in your service.
PAUL: There are so many other frameworks also. You can check LAU, you can check Commitment.
Rahul Parihar: No.
PAUL: NOPIC also, that has been, that is available. Okay, so most of you.
Rahul Parihar: I just made my space available to everyone, you know, if you can look on that thing, and I will stop here and let you… let Anne wait for the…
Rahul Parihar: For that graph.
PAUL: All right, so let me just move to other participants.
Rahul Parihar: Yeah, sure.
PAUL: Mmm…
Mudassar Hakim: people.
Mudassar Hakim: Well, that's it, yeah.
PAUL: I hope I'm one of them. Let me just include others also.
PAUL: David, Sael, Sykesh, Arga… Tidesh, I think, Morgana? Yes, many people. Yamutas, go on.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, so with respect to our iterative and adapt… adaptive rag approach.
Mudassar Hakim: I understand there's a judge, and there is a threshold.
Mudassar Hakim: I'm just trying to understand the difference here, because in both of them, there's going to be some kind of a threshold that tells to stop iterating.
Mudassar Hakim: But how does the confidence score or the threshold change?
Mudassar Hakim: In the adaptive world.
PAUL: Don't change it, we keep it fixed.
PAUL: For example, in any type of machine learning, deep learning, any type of task, we don't change the threshold. It means that if I set it 0.8, 0.8, I cannot change it dynamically, because that's the sufficient logic.
Mudassar Hakim: Interesting, because I thought it's adaptive, that's the reason why I felt… Okay, so then in that case, all the… all the.
PAUL: If it is adaptive.
PAUL: At a certain point, if you feel that the threshold becomes 0.8, it means the quality is bad. Simply, 0.8 when I'm talking about, I know the quality is good, that's why. Higher number that you can keep. You cannot keep lower numbers.
Mudassar Hakim: Correct. So, in this case, then, maybe my understanding is in a different way, because I was thinking that the confidence score is changing. So, are we seeing that the confidence score or the threshold is same across all the three?
PAUL: Threshold will be set, and the confidence score is basically which will be thrown, by the judge.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, so threshold and confidence score are two different things here.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes. Threshold? In every application, we set our own threshold.
PAUL: Right. Threshold cannot be, like, at least in machine learning everywhere, majorly, I've seen, we set our own threshold that we can take it. You can change that, like, but,
PAUL: Like, the idea is you cannot make it dynamic, that in the runtime, every time. We have to keep it fixed.
Mudassar Hakim: It is not…
PAUL: Oh, fuck.
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, threshold part is fixed. So, are we saying that the confidence score is what differentiates the iterative and the adaptive part?
PAUL: Because that will be compared, no, the confidence score with the threshold. For example, if you give 0.8, and here, you are getting 0.6. Simply, I know that it is neglected. It means that, again, retrieve it, again generated.
Mudassar Hakim: So, in iterative, we are not considering the confidence score there, right?
PAUL: In iterative, yes, there is a judge, no, that will basically say the threshold.
PAUL: Otherwise, how we will know that you have to do the retrieval task again?
Mudassar Hakim: Right, but then, what is the difference? Because in adaptive also, we are relying on the same.
PAUL: This step is common for everywhere, just wait. It is common for everywhere. It's not like that, it's not common. So, this step is fixed. It means that here also iterative, only… see, here in recursive, that query decomposition part came, okay?
Mudassar Hakim: Yeah, yeah.
PAUL: This is only the new part. Other than that, it's pretty much the same stuff, just like here. Here, it's not written iterative, but here also.
Mudassar Hakim: I'm talking.
PAUL: It's like…
Mudassar Hakim: It must be adaptive and iterative versus…
PAUL: Yes, here also, in the algorithm, if you have, when I have written, see, generate special token slash threshold, inside this special token, you will have that information to, retribain, which I told as replication tokens.
PAUL: Okay, now that is the signal. Again, you have to do the retrieval process.
Mudassar Hakim: So this special token is not their iterative.
PAUL: No, no, no. Patient local is only there in adaptive. It's not there in iterative or in recursive.
Mudassar Hakim: Okay, okay, so my understanding was wrong, maybe I was referring to them as confidence score, maybe I think it's a special token.
PAUL: No, no, no, it's only in adaptive, it's only in adaptive. It's only adaptive. That is the special token, which is… see, the special token is, within the brackets, retron.
PAUL: As simple as that. And then you have continue.
PAUL: Okay, it means that if the judge, or basically the LLM, throws the continue, it means that it is getting the response. But if it throws the retrict, okay, then again, back to invoking the retriever, generating, and then again re-evaluating it through the judge.
PAUL: Okay.
Mudassar Hakim: the same happening in iterative also, right? The cycle between judge and retrieve. The only difference is here we are using a special token.
PAUL: Yes, and here it's much more of a threshold stack bias.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it. And also, we have an additional generate path, right, which I can see in adaptive, from judge to response.
Mudassar Hakim: Literally won't demand.
PAUL: Yes, retrieve on demand, it means that, whether you want to pass it directly here or to this. So, this particular decision-making is being done by the church.
PAUL: What is the on-demand means?
PAUL: Simply means, the… it will take whether to invoke the retriever or not.
PAUL: If it doesn't invoke, directly generate response time.
Mudassar Hakim: I'll give you a full…
PAUL: Which is the…
Mudassar Hakim: Very interesting.
Mudassar Hakim: Got it, got it, yeah, yeah. Okay, thanks, thanks, Paul.
PAUL: Okay, so that's why here are two judges. One judge is responsible to take the decision whether to retrieve or directly go to the LL.
Mudassar Hakim: Like, whether to do that.
PAUL: If it goes to the LLM, then it will go… that's why I get two judges very soon.
Mudassar Hakim: Cool, cool. Thanks, Rob.
PAUL: Oh, great.
Suraj D S: Apple, Mr. Sula.
PAUL: Kaya Surich Mont.
Suraj D S: Okay, so could you please provide us a glimpse of how this re-ranking, model works?
PAUL: Yes, I will provide it in the re-ranking class.
PAUL: It's not like that. Today only I completed re-ranking. We have a very specific class for re-rank, where I'll be showing more than 5 re-ranking modules. Okay, and how it impacts the answer.
PAUL: So, in that class, I'll be talking about… because, see, re-ranking is basically reordering the top keychums that you have, based on the relevancy provided by the user query.
PAUL: The idea is to reorder. It means that if you have the top 20 documents, out of those top 20, I will sort it out. That, okay, now this is much more better for me. Okay, I feel that the… here, in this particular chunk, I have better context.
PAUL: In this particular chunk, I have better context. So it totally depends upon the relevancy, and the relevancy comes from the user query.
PAUL: Okay, so if you don't worry, because with the practical implementation, in the practical implementation, I will be just using a model in Excel that automatically it is done.
PAUL: Because those are pre-trained weights and biases directly in the model of the BGE ranker or the coherence.
PAUL: Yep.
Suraj D S: Okay, and another, thing that I need to know, how do you remember these number… these many number of papers? Like, is there any tricks that you…
PAUL: There is many number of…
Suraj D S: Papers, papers, research papers.
PAUL: I don't say it like that.
PAUL: There are people around me.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, there are, like, 10 to 12 people are there. Who shares me, like, I share, we share in that way it happens.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, a little bit, in that way, majorly, because I know that
PAUL: Few things are important, and a few things really not important, because when I showed this branch today, okay, really are many papers that I don't know here.
PAUL: Okay, so really it happens, okay? Because in the first one, I only know very few papers from you.
PAUL: Okay, because if you ask me, like, Santa, Aurelia, I don't know, Uprize, I don't know. Okay, Zimi, I don't know. So, a lot of papers that I've never heard, neither could find them. If you directly search MKTOT.
PAUL: Okay, just try to search, you won't be getting any results.
PAUL: Okay, so all the papers you don't need to read, only just make sure you know the three papers. If you know at least 2 to 3 papers in the interview, it becomes…
PAUL: Much better to discuss with someone at architecture level or anything, because that becomes a ground truth, because this is the actual ground truth. And with this ground truth, you can actually have a very good discussion and a debate.
PAUL: Okay, so always focus on 3 to 4 major papers. And in the sports world, you'll be covering more than 15 papers.
PAUL: majorly on the inferencing part. So, this will be pretty much clear, like, going forward. Because, like, I will be doing HIPO implementation and other implementation. In those implementation, I'll be telling you in starting 20 to 30 minutes, and then next 90 minutes, I'll be just doing the mechanical.
PAUL: Maybe?
Suraj D S: Okay, thank you. Thanks, Bob.
PAUL: Okay, next.
ARGHYA: gone.
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
ARGHYA: I have a… I have a different kind of a question. So, the question is, so we are working on… build some new,
ARGHYA: RAD services a lot for our organizers, right? We don't have that much of project for this. Now, what I understand is, as we go from 9 to advanced to regular RAD, right, there are no
ARGHYA: components that get added, and at the end of the previous components are basically another same or a different LLM, which we are trying to achieve some tasks. Like, in a naive rack, we are invoking the LLM once.
ARGHYA: Right? But as we get more advanced, and we add new components, right, the LLM gets used in multiple weeks. Since you've worked in this for some time now.
ARGHYA: Can you let us know how much of a cost difference it may bring from, like, when we go from monthly to a little bit of advanced bag.
PAUL: Knipe is much more cheaper, it's for sure, because it's a direct LLM call. Now, it depends upon the LLM that you select.
PAUL: Always remember, the LLMs with the higher context window sizes, they are much more cost…
PAUL: costlier. So, when I'll be telling you on the class, like, LLM selection.
PAUL: Okay, like, rich LLM to select, and Y to select that one.
PAUL: Okay, so there I'll be talking about that stuff, because, like, if you are working with Gemini models, if you need a very big context window, probably I will go with, Sonnet 4.5, it has pretty much 2 million, okay? Whereas in Gemini models, it can be, like, 32K.
PAUL: So, like, really, like, you have to know that LLM architecture and your problem statement, if you're working with big, big documents, then, really, like, that context window matters to us.
PAUL: So, really, we have to look into the LLM architecture, and based on that, we can say… because if you go with higher, like, bigger context window LLMs, the cost per million tokens is pretty high.
ARGHYA: I mean, I think that is an important… because, like, based on that selection.
PAUL: I will let you know, because in cost optimization class, I will be talking, because, see, everything has a cost. Embedding has a cost, LLM.
ARGHYA: Territ.
PAUL: Has a cost. Your vector DB has a cost. Everything has a cost. Okay, so I'll be talking about that on… with respect to the number of vectors. Generally, with respect to vector databases.
PAUL: the cost discount based on the number of vectors and the dimension size. So, even if you're increasing the number of dimensions, I can say that, yes, you'll be getting better results, but again, the cost increases. Just double.
PAUL: Okay, just think about if I'm working with 768 dimensions, and if I directly go to 3072 dimensions. Okay, the cost just triples, you can think about. So, that's how the vector TV guys charges us.
PAUL: Okay, so yes, with respect to cost optimization, I'll be talking about it, because in our production, exactly what are the things that we have taken, and you have to track the analytics of your total system, like how many
PAUL: tokens are being used, and others. So, all those tracking mechanisms that needs to be developed. That is only for the backend guys.
PAUL: Okay?
ARGHYA: Boom.
PAUL: All right, next, I think, anyone can go, there is… yeah, yeah, go on.
Mitesh Shah: Hi, Paul, Natasha. So, thanks for the detailed description of RAG, okay? But my concern right now is, if we have a relationship database, along with, let's say, some PDFs and other stuff.
Mitesh Shah: Still, do you prefer we go for VANA directly, or should we implement our own rags and systems?
PAUL: You can build your own. Building your own will take much more time. Just think about it. If you have… it totally depends upon the delivery. Somebody ask me to deliver it in 3 days, 4 days. If I have 6 months, I will be building it from scratch, for sure.
Mitesh Shah: Okay, got it. Thanks. Second,
Mitesh Shah: still, do you prefer to go for an offline LLM for testing right now, or, like, paid LLMs, token by.
PAUL: If my data is sensitive, if my data is sensitive, okay, I will never send it to OpenAI or Anthropic, or anybody.
PAUL: Okay, because it… it is really a… like, in long term, there can be problems. I don't know with OpenAI, though it's a public-listed company, okay, but what can happen? So, it's better, that's why.
PAUL: So, if your data is sensitive, always keep it. If it's related to finance and other stuff, always use a local one.
Mitesh Shah: Got it. My next question was related to that. We typically create our own custom GPTs, right? GPTs, and in case Gemini is something else, but in that case, can we directly call those GPTs, through an LLM, like, for generation?
PAUL: Custom GPTs… see, GPTs are all LLMs. Okay, like, there are, like, GPT1, 2, those are SLMs, but going forward, starting from 3, it has been LLMs much more. So, like, you can use any language model.
PAUL: So, right now, starting from 2025, everybody is trying to build their own FLMs.
PAUL: Okay, the idea is that you don't need so much information.
PAUL: For an organization, if you're using a ChatGPT model, do you think that, really.
PAUL: Because it has been trained on vast amount of data, so really, that, we feel that we don't need. Rather than you can train an LLM, that is much better and cheaper solution, always. Because in your case, how many dogs? Probably, if you take entire 50,000, if I'd say, max, like, 1 million dogs.
PAUL: Okay, so in that case, it's fine.
PAUL: No, hold on.
Mitesh Shah: I think you… my question was a little different. So, in ChatGPT or OpenAI, you get an option of creating your own GPDs, right?
PAUL: Okay, I got it, got it, got it. In there, you have that particular option. Okay, but actually, that is not available through an API, no.
Mitesh Shah: Okay, yeah. That's what I was… I was wondering… I tried it, but it's not all.
PAUL: Okay, no, no, no. That you cannot do.
Mitesh Shah: Next, for the, the iterative part, add recursive, and then adaptive, right? The main concern for me is, the query decomposition, can it happen before retrieval, specifically for recursive or adaptive?
PAUL: It always happens before the retrieval, no, because what you want to retrieve? For that, you need a specific set of questions that will be decomposed from your main query. So, it always happens before the retrieval.
Mitesh Shah: So, in adaptive case, a judge will decide it will go for retrieval, and there it… a decomposition might… may or may not happen, right?
PAUL: If it… if the retrieval is invoked, okay, then only that decomposition part will take place.
Mitesh Shah: Perfect. And are we going to work on something on TUNE versus JSON? Because what I've heard is Tune is a new JSON for LLMs.
PAUL: attune.
Mitesh Shah: 2 Tou-O-N.
PAUL: Okay, tune is the new JSON for LEMs. Alright, I will check this one.
Mudassar Hakim: Token-based, notation.
Mitesh Shah: Yeah, yes.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: Alright, yes, we can take this, probably, like, once we complete this, these are… you guys can keep it as a bucket list, okay, like, additional topic that needs to be discussed, and later on, like, once we complete, then we can have additional classes for this one.
Mitesh Shah: Last question, from my side. See, I am not able to get that concept of demonstrate in the, the last, framework.
PAUL: Demonstrate, actually, what happens, see, demonstrate, really, to understand, demonstrate, you have to read the paper of the SP once. Okay, really what happens, it means that from its trained sources, okay, it will always throw you multiple examples to demonstrate that the answer is correct. The idea is that it's not only just one
PAUL: generally what happens, when you ask ChatDPT or anything, okay, it only throws you the answer. But if you ask it, provide me more examples. Okay, in DHP papers, what happens? By default, it's search. It's not only one result that comes, okay? Always, it will be with…
PAUL: I… at least I have seen 3 or 4 examples that it happens with. Okay, so a little bit, if you at least go through the DHP abstract, it is written there, perfectly. You will get it from there.
Mitesh Shah: Yep, thank you. Thank you, Juan.
Yashwant Raut: Hi, Paul, so…
Yashwant Raut: I have the question related to the multi-tenancy. So, like, how we can, implement the multi-tenancy, like, the department-wise.
Yashwant Raut: data need to be visible, let's say the finance data need to be visible only for the finance people, and the HR data need to be visible only for the HR people, so…
Yashwant Raut: How we can, implement the multi-tenancy?
PAUL: It's just, like, department-wise, you want to restrict something.
Yashwant Raut: Yes, or the data segregation, usually when we build the, let's say, the product that we need to put into the production, so the roles and permissions.
PAUL: Okay, so, see, for example, if I take… and just think about, you can segregate it in vector databases also, or you can create multiple collections within a vector database, one very specific to HR documents, one very specific to finance documents, one very specific to that.
PAUL: Okay, and then very specifically, when you are invoking the call to the backend, then you can call a very specific collection of a vector database.
PAUL: Hit me, right?
PAUL: You won't be calling all the collections, rather than a single collection.
Yashwant Raut: Okay, and within that same department, like, suppose the senior authority person has the different view, or they can actually go and analyze the data differently.
PAUL: Then, category-wise. Collection-wise, inside collection, you have categories. Then you can… that is the last level. After category, there is no level.
PAUL: So, generally, that's how, majorly in Pinecone and other, we have seen. So, it's just, like, first you have that, index. Index is basically the collection. Within that collection, you have the category, which is referred to as the last.
PAUL: So, there you can do a filter, like, in a normal database, you can do a filter operation there also. Like, now, there you have to apply the filters very specifically based on the means.
Yashwant Raut: And, any, recommended database, like the Pine Phone, or the Open Source, or any, any, like, don't see how you…
PAUL: Everybody has the same functionality, I cannot say, see, Pinecone, like, see, it really depends upon… yeah, Pinecone is for them who really don't want to, spend a lot of time on the embedding, because in Pinecone, there are hosted embedding models. Even re-ranking models are also there.
PAUL: It means that directly API call, and done. Everything API call. You don't need to do. Otherwise, in other databases, where you have to take care completely of your embedding, you have to take care completely of your rethinking, so those things. So, in that way.
PAUL: Yeah, you have to decide. So, I figured all vector databases, at the end of the day, it's pretty much the same. Few are adding few features. Okay, generally for scalability, like, when I'm talking about billions of documents, and that has released as one of the best.
Yashwant Raut: Which one?
PAUL: sillis.
Yashwant Raut: Seals, okay.
PAUL: Zilies, that is really good. Yeah.
PAUL: Alright, boy.
David E: Yes, David, coming to you just…
Yashwant Raut: And the last one, the last question, Paul. So, like, suppose then we need to…
Yashwant Raut: have the, cross-collection queries, like, suppose the… the CU12…
Yashwant Raut: get the CEO has some queries, and the answer could be actually across the collection, like, we need to go and analyze the financial data, HR data, and some other department data. Then, those things also, we need to go and do it manually, like, hitting the multiple, let's say, the
PAUL: Then you have to arrange a call in such a way that the search, which will happen, it will be in those collections very specifically, like you told, like the finance there, HR there. So you will be telling that, okay, in these collections, you have to do all the vector search. Then, from there, you will be getting the context.
Yashwant Raut: Okay, thank you. Thanks, Bob.
David E: Yeah, hey Paul, thanks again for doing this class. I'm coming in from the…
David E: other end. I'm trying to understand where tools like NE10 fits into this entire landscape, because it seems to be easy to implement a rack system within NE10. You just get an AI agent, you plug in an embedded model memory, etc. So, you know, so these concepts.
David E: of a naive rag, advanced rag, and modular rag. It's, you know, it's throwing me a curveball. So I'm trying to understand where can I.
PAUL: Okay, cool.
David E: all these things.
PAUL: Okay, okay, okay, fine, like, from tomorrow, we will start with the practice, okay? See, in MA10, it's very, very easy, whether, like, MA10, Flow-wise, all the no-code tools, it's just rackdrock each of the components, okay, and it becomes very, very easy, I know that, okay. But here, it's much more, like, if you're building a…
PAUL: product, really. If you're building a service, NA10 is good. But if you're building, actually, a product, okay, to build a product, really, like, going forward, you need much more control, because really, I don't know, like, from day one, do you want your business to be dependent on such a…
PAUL: So, where we need much more power, then I feel that, yes, the entire backend should be at least in your control. So, in those cases, and here, the customizations, like,
PAUL: can be done in a lot of things. It means that incremental changes based on new implementations that comes around. In maintenance.
PAUL: I will say very limited.
PAUL: It means that all… everything that cannot be connected. It can be connected, like, for example, the Fusion part. We can make separate API calls.
PAUL: Okay, and that we can attach. But again, I feel that if you want to attach an MCP server there, it can be a problem. Okay, so, like, few things that can be done, and few things that cannot be done.
PAUL: So, at the end of the day, having a complete backend is much more powerful. So, but if you have a simple service, just like a feature, one or two features, in that case, it's fine.
David E: Okay, so if I'm understanding… Okay, go ahead.
PAUL: POC, if you want to create an MVP, okay, within 3 or 4 days, if you want to show a demo that, yes, I have the capability to deliver this particular stuff. Okay, in that case, I prefer anything, just for prototyping. But later on, to build a full-fledged product, I need a complete solution.
David E: I see. So, just to put it in… so that I understand what you just said to me.
David E: Anything, as you mentioned, for proof of concept, MVP, and maybe for a small enterprise, a small mom-and-pop shop, but for an enterprise environment, you would need more control, and if you want to have it, of course, the security, etc, you would implement it the way we are being taught currently.
PAUL: Yes, exactly correct.
David E: Okay, okay, okay, okay.
PAUL: Whoa.
David E: Oh, thanks. Thank you.
PAUL: Alright, next.
Atul Rastogi: Yeah, I just want to ask, I was implementing one rag system where I have some database, PDF files, let's say, heavy containing medical information, and then I just want
Atul Rastogi: the data to be stored in Pinecone, I did everything, but at the end, I saw that the huge amount of data is to be stored in Pinecone, and they will be charging huge amount of money for that. And similarly, the input tokens and output tokens to the LLM, OpenAI, they were, you know, again charged through the API route.
Atul Rastogi: So, the cost is so much for this, doing this, although blank chain, everything is free, testing is free, but when we really build a big system… So, how to manage this? I mean, is there any way that we can put our own server and everything there?
PAUL: Management, you have to pay the bills, even if we pay $3,000 just for vector data services, okay? See, you can optimize things to a certain level.
PAUL: Okay, that's the only thing, because Pinecone, I think 3GB, free limit is close to 2GB, I think. I don't remember 2 or 3GB, something like that is there. Okay. It's really, like, for everything, you need to pay money. See, if you're not making an API call, then you have to spend some amount of money on the infrastructure cost. It means…
Atul Rastogi: Is there any open source database which I can implement in my own server?
PAUL: For large data. Yes, yes, COMA and others are there, but again, for them, you have to host it somewhere, no.
PAUL: You have to create a cluster, you have to host it, see, everything there is free. But free things, you have to create your own infrastructure in some cloud, okay, or somewhere, okay, and then you have to use it.
Atul Rastogi: No, that is fine. I will take a hosting and server of…
PAUL: Who's gonna do that?
Atul Rastogi: But after that, I will not be paying for the data storage, transfer of data, everything.
PAUL: Yes, yes, those things, but for the server storage, you will pay, no, at the end of that.
Atul Rastogi: Yes.
PAUL: That is cheaper. That's why people always prefer using a custom hosting solution, even for bigger, like, for vector databases. When you move into enterprise solutions, they will say that, okay, bring your own cloud, okay, and they will do the setup.
PAUL: And simply, directly that you can call. You can do the setup by yourself also, not a big deal.
Atul Rastogi: So, Amazon is offering these services now, I think?
PAUL: Amazon is also… I guess Amazon is offering.
Atul Rastogi: Okay, thank you.
Rahul Parihar: Yep.
Rahul Parihar: Databrick and S3 would be another, you know, route.
Rahul Parihar: cheaper route.
PAUL: No, see, now the question comes, like, if you want to save embeddings, if you want to save your documents, that is fine, S3 and others. But if you want to save your embeddings, then S3, no ins…
Rahul Parihar: But Titan embedding would work right, like, with,
Rahul Parihar: If you are using AWS strands rather than Langchain, and using all AWS internal structure, I think we reduce the cost by, like, 70%.
PAUL: If you use everything, see, generally what happens, whenever you are working in some organization, there are long-term contracts, okay? In long-term contracts, by default, you get 50-60% discount.
PAUL: Okay, so for example, if I'm committed to AWS for 10 years, by default, any service that I use, I know that it will be at least 30-40% cheaper, or maybe more than that.
PAUL: Okay, so in that case, yes, for sure, we can achieve that close to 50%.
Aks: Hi, Paul, what should I say?
PAUL: Yes.
Aks: So my question is a generic one. Like, since this course is about RAG,
Aks: And the advanced version of that can probably PTK area.
Aks: So, I come from a technical background, Mundi, but not specifically to machine learning. I know,
Aks: nuances of programming language types, and…
Aks: Some of the libraries, like some Python, that's right.
Aks: Just wanted to ask, is it mandatory for us to…
Aks: Absolute knowledge of, machine learning, deep learning.
Aks: for that sake, and NLP and Gen AI, before, completely understanding what we are,
Aks: Doing in this course, or,
Aks: we can still be a RAG for a identic AI engineer for that sake, even if we have don't…
Aks: 100% of the clarity of the previous content.
PAUL: See, like, in Gen AI Engineer, if you're looking for these AI-based schools, Gen AI-based schools, then the fundamentals are required. See, at, after 6 years or 7 years of experience, they will ask you questions, because these are the fundamental things.
PAUL: It means that the idea is that if you are telling me you are having 7 years of experience.
PAUL: Okay, then, at least in the past 7 years, just think around, starting from 2018. So, these things are pretty much going. The idea is that you have the knowledge. Probably, based on the project that you have worked, okay, a few things that you might not know. But at least I can say that 60% of the stuff, the fundamentals you have to know.
PAUL: Because I cannot say that one can know everything, but at least based on the project, in the project, what are the things that you have worked on? Your personal struggles, how you have overcome? Okay, now those stories are pretty much important.
PAUL: Okay, because how that impact was there, okay, how you scaled up, how you solved a particular problem. So.
PAUL: Well, really, it depends upon the experience.
PAUL: Okay, so, for example, if somebody comes, just a fresher. You want a fresher, nothing will be asked so much.
PAUL: Fresher, they will look into the practical implementations much more as compared to the theoretical understanding and decision, because that guy won't be taking decisions, will be just taking, the decisions which will be made by the leaders.
PAUL: Okay, it totally depends upon that rule and the amount. Once you cross that 5 to 6 years, you really need to understand, because the decision-taking things are important.
PAUL: And to have a right instinct, you need to know the fundamentals.
PAUL: Otherwise, like, if you start reading papers, okay, you will say that, okay, I don't know this. Then, again, an older paper that you will… then again, once you read, then again, some older. So it happens. So I feel that the fundamentals should be correct. If your fundamentals are correct, then at least it helps you
PAUL: More than 40% to take a good decision.
Aks: The only confusion I think a lot of other folks might be having is that since this area is moving at such a rapid pace, and probably some… for some of the folks like us.
Aks: Where we did not,
Aks: get onto this train of, like, ML and VL, like, a couple of years back, and now we want to learn all of the concepts. It becomes a challenge that we have to start off, do we
Aks: Start off with ML, and take the complete partel.
PAUL: See, if you directly want to start, I can say that you can skip ML also, because this is much more deep learning. Directly, in deep learning, skip computer vision also, directly focus on the deep learning NLP part, and then directly start working here. The idea is that you should have good,
PAUL: knowledge of the transformers, okay? That is the main point, because in NLP, there are things, but a lot of things are deprecated in the classical NLP field.
PAUL: Okay, the deep learning NLP has pretty much overtaken right now, so at least starting from deep learning, you should know this.
PAUL: That I feel. If you don't have so much time, but at least the fundamentals of deep learning, because if you are training something, an LLM or anything, you should know what is an optimal cell.
PAUL: you should know what is weight decay. These are common things. It means that if you have studied the fundamentals, then most of the things will be clear. Otherwise, you will see that, okay, now what is this parameter? What is this parameter? What is this parameter?
PAUL: Okay, that's fine.
Aks: Correct. All day. Thank you so much. Appreciate it.
PAUL: Yes, anybody else? Let me know in the chat.
PAUL: What is the process? There is no such process.
PAUL: Okay, Sahil, again, Sahil, Aratia, Saita Jay, people have already raised hands. Any other questions you have?
saiteja: Hello, sir. Thank you for the session.
PAUL: Yeah.
saiteja: I was asking, sir, how… I'm a fresher, sir, so how… like, what are the technologies they will ask me in interview for, like, AI engineer, or AML engineer, or development for less AI they want. So, what are the.
PAUL: Thanks, Mike.
saiteja: Nothing from me.
PAUL: directly, whatever version or a draft of your current resume, send it.
PAUL: Because I cannot send that way. I have to add on those things, what are the things that are missing, then I will let you know. So, what is your current resume? Okay, share me that, then I will tell you, at least you need to know this, you need to know this, and you need… in that way, I will make the point. Okay, so drop me the mail with your current version.
saiteja: Okay, sir, where is the mail?
PAUL: app at the rate, krishnag.in, EAPP at the rate, Kresh.
PAUL: Nike.in. I'm sharing it in the chat, please take it from there.
saiteja: Okay, okay. Sir, one more question, sir.
saiteja: Sir, how, how does, yeah, that, yeah, judge works, like, how, how, how does it get context? So, we are training, WAG, because the LLM doesn't know what specific field, or, I mean, specific field, so how does
saiteja: it, it will say whether it is correct or wrong. Like, for example, law. LLM doesn't know about Indian law specifically that much, so how does judge get context so it is right or wrong? How does it work?
PAUL: How does that know?
PAUL: The example that you told, what is, loss? Just repeat once again.
saiteja: Law, law, sir. Law, law, LLB.
PAUL: Okay, law LLB. Okay, huh, probably, like, if… now, this is a domain-specific question.
PAUL: Boop.
PAUL: If you ask for donor-specific… Yes, you know, sir.
PAUL: Yes, yes, I am telling you that only. So, you can ask always the LLM whether you know or not, whether it knows or not. Okay, through prompt engineering, you can do it, okay, and others. Again, tomorrow's example, directly in the prompt, you can ask it. Simply say no, or simply say yes. Okay, based on that, you can take a decision.
PAUL: Okay, otherwise, if you want.
PAUL: some type of output to be generated by an LLM, then you can actually evaluate the output using another LLM, which becomes that LLM as a judge concept.
PAUL: So, your internal LLM that you have, other than that, you can use an external LLM just for the evaluation purpose.
PAUL: Okay, so when I will show you the practicals.
PAUL: it will be much more clear. Because, see, anything, you can directly ask the LLM, and you can simply say in a structured output that, yes, I am looking only for two things, yes or no. Leave the generation part.
PAUL: Okay, see, if simply it says yes, it means that, okay, it knows the stuff. If it knows, then it means that you have to look into the generated output. If it simply says no, you know that now you have to invoke the retriever directly.
saiteja: Okay, sir.
PAUL: So, during practicals, things will be much more clear. Right now, it's much more theoretical, I know that, but from tomorrow, we will start with the simple one, and then we'll move to advanced and the other versions.
PAUL: Alright, Nagapan, I think you have raised your hand. Nagapan.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Yeah, so for the POC, right, you highlight that we can start with the knife rag, right? So, while we go for development, shall we start with, knive rag, followed by…
PAUL: Always start with NIBRAD, then move to Advanced Rad.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Okay.
PAUL: And then only pick up the components from modular rack which you feel that it is important in your use case.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Okay, okay. So, is it possible in the production that NIVRAG will be there, or it should be in the production the advanced stuff?
PAUL: For the production, it will be much more advanced, right, with few components of model effect.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Okay, okay. So, and the second question is, let's say if we do the normal application development, we just follow, development, UAT, SIT, such kind of things, right? Production. So, how about while we do this January point of view rag, do we follow such kind of things, or how it would be?
PAUL: Few things are changed, I can say probably 10-15%. Rest, 85% SDLC, the same thing as a normal
PAUL: Software engineering, lifecycle, those things. Like, once you containerize it, anything, then the rest of the protocols remains pretty much the same.
PAUL: Probably 10-15%, that depends upon, like, how you have designed your complete system, like, based on microservices.
PAUL: Okay, now, which one? Like, for one vector TV, one microservice for data ingestion phase, one microservice for retrieval part, one microservice. So, that particular architecture that you need to decide. Because at the end of the day, the entire thing can be controlled through a Docker Compose, and later on, like, we can put it in an EKS cluster and others, anywhere.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Okay.
PAUL: So, 15-20%, few things are there, other than that, I don't think any other media change.
Nagappan Thanneermalai: Okay, okay, thank you, yeah.
PAUL: Alright.
PAUL: Yeah, Harga, I think he was telling something. Yeah.
ARGHYA: Let's test football.
ARGHYA: I took the above name?
PAUL: I could not, get you, can you be a bit, a bit louder?
ARGHYA: Am I audible right now?
PAUL: Yeah, yeah, better.
ARGHYA: Yeah, what I wanted to mention is, like, we are going to have a session where they debug the RAG application server, right? And I guess that's going to be the time looking.
PAUL: We are going to have a session on what?
ARGHYA: Debugging the application?
PAUL: debugging, exactly in debugging what? Because…
PAUL: like, Python programming debugging that I want to be showing.
ARGHYA: No, lanchoon, right? That was the one that…
PAUL: Exactly, like, what we want to debug.
ARGHYA: So, let's say I want to see… I want to see.
PAUL: Because debugging is much more a development task, rather than teaching, debugging is a very tough task.
ARGHYA: No, no, not… I don't mention… I don't… I don't… I don't mean by them line by line, I mean for… in general, right? I do some… I do the, checks through Landsmith, but maybe something, I do in an incorrect way, so it's… is it possible if you can… whenever you're going to keep them.
PAUL: There is something, like, you can let me know, because, really, like, exactly what you want to debug, the idea is, as you told Lancemith, the idea is that you are taking care of some type of metrics on conversation that you were keeping in some place. Okay. Now, exactly, like, what do you want to debug?
ARGHYA: So let's say I want to see the… so, for example, last… last day I mentioned, right? One of the issues I was missing was, I was seeing multiple… in the refriever section, I was seeing multiple accounts of the same document in my article, which…
ARGHYA: Which I was able to see in Lance with, right? Like, I was in a drop 20, and I saw that the 18th of them were the same, so…
ARGHYA: Some examples, common examples like this, this is, like, one of the common examples, as you mentioned, right? If we chunk and embed incorrectly and store in our… slow redundancies in our vector databases, right? So, what are the common issues that… that come up, which we should be mindful of? Something.
PAUL: Because, see, that's why you let me know your exact requirement, okay? Then I can let you know, because the embedding operation that you told, that is totally separate. There, generally, we test with few type of documents, then we move to batch.
PAUL: engineering part. Okay, then we tested a batch of loads and other stuff that comes into the picture, then comes with database operations, but really, like,
PAUL: Tracking and debugging there, really, like, when we are doing any uploads.
PAUL: generally, like.
PAUL: We take account of the total number of documents uploaded, total number of chunks available, those things, but really, like, there is no separate to, like, landsmith or anything that we use very specifically for that particular operation.
PAUL: So, like, exactly your requirement, if you can be much more specific, then based on that, I can give you.
ARGHYA: Well, I'll practice at some more examples soon.
PAUL: Exactly, just in case.
ARGHYA: I'll understand, but, like, debugging is going to be pretty much the most important thing for any software development thing that I think.
PAUL: Yes, that I understand.
ARGHYA: The way that we debug is an important part, so that… that will… like, if… since you have been working in this for some time now, so…
PAUL: Here, it's much more about evaluation, really, to say. It's debugging, it means that few things, yes, that instinct part comes with a little bit of experience, that part I can share. Okay, but, really, like, few things are there that are really hard to discuss. So, like, based on your specific requirement, I will let you.
PAUL: Okay.
PAUL: All right. Next, I think there is Naga. Ridvish, again, you have raised your hand. Sahil, you have raised your hand.
Naga: But what's not her in?
PAUL: Yes.
Naga: Yeah, so I have a question on the hallucination. So, are there any advanced techniques at which we are going to
Naga: Discuss about, like.
PAUL: Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, how to solve the problem of hallucination, we'll be talking about that.
Naga: But…
Naga: So, any specific techniques, we are going to… or, like, embedding-based, consistency checks, those things we are going to do, or any…
Naga: Because… and then, how do you… how do you identify the… if there is a hallucin… if the model is hallucinating, or, you know, how do you know whether it's…
Naga: One way or the other.
PAUL: A few things are there, like LLM overconfidence, like, context window poisoning, okay? A few things, because very specifically, like, with respect to semantic chunking, okay.
PAUL: hierarchical chunking, it too happens. Okay, now, it's something like, we'll be talking very specifically with respect to, like, re-ranking and confidence scoring also. I feel that generally with respect to hallucination, LLM as a judge really works very good.
PAUL: Okay, it cannot be a scenario where all the 10 different LLMs, or LLM as a jury, okay, that part is also there. Otherwise, sometimes, very specifically with respect to hybrid search strategies that we can include, where we can mix our sparse vector search with dense vector search.
PAUL: Okay, so there are a few techniques, so majorly 3 to 4 that I'll be discussing in the class.
PAUL: Because your retrieval verification is important, your generation verification, because few verification things are there that needs to be done. Because if a second LLM actually reviews the answer for hallucination, it becomes much better at any point of time.
PAUL: So, it's called COV, if you look into the concept of chain of verification pattern, it's there.
PAUL: Okay, so where you generate each answer, and then you actually try to have a look for a factual, claim for that answer. So in that way, we can…
PAUL: But, to a certain extent. It's not like, I can say 100% foolproof, because 100% full-proof, it becomes much more costlier solution if you move towards jury-based solutions.
Naga: Okay.
Naga: I have one more question, on, like, are we going to discuss the multi-hop rack? Like, we have one rack, and it's giving the…
Naga: say… and then it's actually exchanging the, no, like, the data with the other rack, like, with the multi-hop, right? So is there any such scenarios we are going to discuss?
PAUL: Multi-hop, I don't think it is there. It's pretty much new here in 2025. You can keep it in the bucket list.
PAUL: Okay, because always look into the syllabus, because I don't think in the syllabus it is there. I have to check the syllabus also, once again, about this question.
Naga: Because this is a common scenario, right? Multi… multi-hub, right? Because it's… say, I assume, like, you have.
PAUL: Multi-off rack is not a common scenario, just think if, in your organization, if there are 10 different rack systems, okay, then it can be a scenario.
PAUL: But if it's only a single track system.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, I… you can create, but generally, I prefer a single rack system inside DAC to keep everything much more separated. Probably, I can change the vector TV and other stuff.
PAUL: But the system should be a single one, rather than… so it totally depends upon that. Okay, so you can keep it as a bucket list, but I think in the syllabus I could not find it.
PAUL: Multi-hop is not the multi-hop reasoning, so generally we teach in the LLM class.
PAUL: No, it's not there.
PAUL: All right.
PAUL: Okay, I think, no more questions.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Hello.
PAUL: What it is…
Ritvij Maheshwari: fall under the bus.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Sorry, Paul, just one. Actually, the thing is that, as I discussed with my manager that I'm learning this kind of things, and, my manager is also working with a separate guy. He's also working on a rag-based application only, so what he is doing is that we received a rulebook or a methodology kind of thing. What he wants to try is that, if I just enter my… that
Ritvij Maheshwari: rulebook into a LLM, right? There can be a separate… many rulebooks that we receive.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Like, for example, there is a strategy we receive, we just code it. That's my job to do it. But let's say if that, what he wants is that AI should read that rulebook, it just summarize that rulebook.
Ritvij Maheshwari: and then it, it just goes into my, the folders and see that, is there a particular code or a function that is written there or not? If it is written there, it can just fetch it from there, and if it is not, then it can write the functions based on the markdown language that is written in the PDF. Now, the guy that has done that work, he has just
Ritvij Maheshwari: track the first part, that is, he can summarize the rulebook, but he was not able to do the markdown and the mathematical formula from the rulebooks. So my question to you is, my manager asked me this question, is it, first of all, is it possible to do this?
Ritvij Maheshwari: Second thing, am I… would I be able to do it after, let's say, 3-4 months after this course? And what would be the cost? It means if you can get a rough estimation of this cost, that… whether we want some kind of GPS, because my manager has to also take an approval and assign to me this project. So, I just want to know your opinion on that.
PAUL: Generally, like, like, formulas are there. Now, formulas, but, really, I need to look into, like, whether they are in Latinx.
PAUL: If latex is there, it is fine.
PAUL: But if there are images, okay, then it means that taking, like, probably some type of image-based embeddings.
PAUL: The solution that you are telling, yes, it is possible, but how you are doing that data parsing mechanism, that is important.
PAUL: That is the main breakthrough. In the river, really, like, whatever the things that I have told today, the most toughest part is data parsing.
PAUL: Okay, the thing that I've taught today, everything is easy. Only the data parsing is the toughest part, because how you want to extract that information?
PAUL: Okay, now that is the main game changer. If it is in Latinx, it becomes easier for any type of LLM to understand, but if it is with respect to image, then it means that you have to create an image of that, and then image embedding that you have to save. So there, it becomes a little bit complex.
PAUL: That part, you need to look, because really, I've not worked with formulas, okay? But, that part. If it is in Latinx, it's much easier. If it is not in Latinx.
PAUL: Okay, then probably, like, how many formulas are there? I will think about converting them into Latinx, because Latex is much easier for alums to understand, rather than, direct embedding of a formula image.
Ritvij Maheshwari: So, two things, Paul. Number one, when you say latex, means, generally, these… we receive it in form of PDF or Word. Now, in Word, it is generally on latex, but when we are converting from Word to PDF, the… I don't know whether that PDF has the latex
Ritvij Maheshwari: Incorporated in that. Means, is it or is it not?
Ritvij Maheshwari: If it is a PDF.
PAUL: That I cannot say securely. If it is that latex is rendered, okay, during the PDF generation, okay, then I think we'll be losing the latex information. It will be probably in the docs only.
Ritvij Maheshwari: And what about, let's say, if I just convert that PDF, somewhere I do that, that, I just convert that PDF into, let's say, the Jupyter notebook, that is Markdown PDF, I just write those formulas, would the, would the LLM would be able to read that Jupyter notebook, Markdown.
PAUL: No, no, no, no, no. Jupyter Notebook, the idea is that if we even convert those.
PAUL: formulas into Latinx, somehow. Okay, it becomes much easier for the LLM to understand, because every LLM understands Latinx directly.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, okay, this is the first part. Second part is, what is the cost means, would I require some kind of GPUs or something like this, so that.
PAUL: GPU is not required. See, it totally depends upon few things. Okay, like GPU, do you… do you feel that you need a vector database which is running off on a GPU? Okay, then comes, do you want to host a model?
PAUL: then these type of questions arises. Like, if you are looking to set up your own infra, okay, then also, like, at every point of… because running some operations on the GPU, for sure, it will be much faster. Like, there are some embedding models which are very good, but they need GPU.
PAUL: Okay, so, like, it's a trade-off. So, somewhere you feel that, okay, I can manage around 100 milliseconds.
PAUL: Okay, now that decision needs to be taken care, because when I'll be talking, with respect to, like, time, like, at every component, how much time it takes, then you can actually take that decision. But GPU is not a compulsory. Without a GPU also, I can have an embedding model, re-banking model, everything.
PAUL: But the operations will be much more time-taking. So for every operation, you can take around 10 milliseconds to 20 milliseconds, much more.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it, got it. Means, in my thing, I think time would be a thing, because I can give even a one day to train my model, so in my thing, I think that time would not be an issue for that. But yeah, coming onto.
PAUL: See, what happens if you're using an embedding model, okay? Now, generally, what happens, then you always need a GPU, because if you're using a GPU-based embedding model, because the first things in the rack, the query will come, and that query will be converted into embedding. So, continuous GPU usage that spike around.
PAUL: Okay, so that is the major problem. If you are going with embedding, like GPU-based embedding models.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, because that I need to then, ask my IT team, because we can't do it in Google Collab at all, because due to.
PAUL: No, no, Google Colab, forget it. I'm not talking about in Google Cloud also. I'm talking about a proper AWS G5 class instance, very specific to AWS. In other cloud, also, they are available. Similar instance, where at least you have a
PAUL: T4, okay, with 16GB of RAM. Okay, because few embedding models take 32GB of VRAM.
PAUL: Few take 18. So, that model selection, when I'll be talking about the embedding models, in that day class.
PAUL: these things I'll be talking about. Because few things serverless GPUs are good. But in case of RAG, only the main problem is you cannot work with serverless, because whenever you are going with serverless, the concept of
PAUL: cold start and a warm start that comes into the picture. Okay, but if continuously, if somebody is using your system, then it's good, because you need to launch a GPU instance behind the scenes.
PAUL: Okay, because I have built a solution like that. Okay, so yes, you can do it, but it will be a costly. So, if you have a…
PAUL: hardware in your office, a GPU, then it will be much more cheaper. AWS and others, the bill will be pretty much fine. So I can say that the solution that you'll be building without GPU, you can build it only
PAUL: there will be a lag with respect to the response guy. And as I told, that if the concept of image embedding comes into the picture, in some case, I'm just taking it. Then you need GPUs for sure.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it. For English embeddings.
PAUL: It takes a lot of VRAM.
PAUL: That's why Clip and others, they are really, like, on CPUs, really, they cannot work so much in a good way.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it. The last thing that… the last question, that would… that, that my local LM Willem, would that also be able to interact with the local files? Like, say, like, say, Python code, the functions that I've said, that… would that be also possible? Yes or no, maybe?
PAUL: Yes, there is no problem. People are building some systems, you know, like, for example, they have an entire codebase, they expose it, okay, to a local LLM, they create a complete documentation. Yes, these things are there.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Perfect. Okay, yeah, that's it. It means I'll speak to my manager once about this conversation, and maybe, if possible, I will also… if there is any doubt, I'll also mail you at the same email.
Ritvij Maheshwari: And this mail ID that you have given, app at directchrishnak.in, is this your mail ID, or is it a team mail ID? Means, how would this be reroute to you? Means, should I write something on the subject, or…
PAUL: This is the… not team, this is the development. I am the ad guy, so I only use this email.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Okay, sweet.
PAUL: Only the product team, yes, only the product team uses this email. So, that's why anything… because there are other subscriptions that I have, everything, my VectorTV bill, everything comes in this email, so I track this email much more.
Ritvij Maheshwari: Got it, yeah, okay, okay, yeah, sure.
PAUL: Alright guys, it's going to be 2 o'clock, the other batch will start, okay? So tomorrow's class, very, very important. The practical implementation will be starting. A lot of queries can be there in your mind, because it was much more theoretical, but from tomorrow, okay, next week also, it will be much more practical-oriented.
PAUL: Okay, less theory, or much more. So, everyone, just be sure you are attending tomorrow's class, okay, and the upcoming 3-4 classes.
PAUL: Very, very important to build a strong foundation of at least one framework. If you are good in one framework, really, you don't need Lama Index.
PAUL: and Haystack. You can do everything in LangChain, okay? So, very, very important. Please don't miss these classes.
PAUL: Alright guys, so… bye everyone, thanks for joining.